Hello everyone, my name is Hossein and I want to talk about my presentation for our class
which is on state space models for an introduction to Mamba model.
So just to give you a little bit of background and the kind of problem we are talking about
here is basically it's a sequence to sequence modeling so you can imagine that your input
it can be a sequence of tokens, sequence of images or any other modality and then you
want to transform this input into some desired output and in the between you can use different
kind of architecture so for example you can think of RNN to actually perform this task
for you or convolutional network to do this task with you or transformers to perform the
task but for this data space model and Mamba tries to perform this task more efficiently
and they are basically as I said an emerging architecture that tries to be more efficient
in computation so to give you a little bit of background before we go into the details
of the architectures and also some theories on these models, foundation models specifically
large language models are pre-trained on massive data and then they are fine-tuned on
downstream tasks that's what people usually do and the key factor in these foundation
models is that they in almost all of them the predominant architecture used in them
is transformers and the main reason why people use transformers is because of the core attention
layer it has that has the ability to actually recall the previous tokens and also do some
in content learning but it comes at some heavy cost and as you can see for example the number
of tokens that you can actually pass to these large language models are limited for example
to 1024 or even lower and that's because the attention mechanism is very costly it's quadratic so
given your input of sequence length n in order to get your attention matrix you need to do
n squared multiplication so that's a very costly operation and as we are all in computer science
we know that n squared is not a very desirable number when it comes to runtime analysis and
basically structure state space sequence models for intent to address these issues and try to come
up with an alternative architecture that can actually perform the similar task with similar
accuracy but at lower cost as I said many sub there are many sub quadratic time
architectures such as linear attention gated convolution and recurrent models to try to
actually replace transformers computational inefficiency and what can we say about structure
state space model is that they are they can be somehow interpreted as a combination of recurrent
neural networks and convolutional neural networks and we will see throughout this talk how we can
actually derive this kind of interpretation and I will go through the details of their derivations
but as I said the main motivation for structure space models is to try to
do the task for longer range sequences so that we can actually cover for example millions of
tokens as input so the size of the maximum sequence left that we have we see in many of these large
language model can be extended to a million and also it should have the capacity to capture
dependencies over tens of thousands of steps but as we will see there are many struggles that
comes with these s4 model specifically when it comes to meeting the same kind of accuracy and
performance that transformer model has and the next model that I'm going to cover which is
mamba tries to actually address that specific problem to s4 so as I said the goal in a state
space model is to efficient modeling of long sequences and the solution is basically built
a neural network layer based on state space model so actually you can use rnn for
and modeling long sequences because as you know rnn has some internal state and this internal
state is actually constant so the inference time of rnn is actually linear in contrast to
transformers that's that is n squared because of the attention computation but the problem with rnn
is that during the training you cannot make them parallel like the way that you can work with
transformers so if you already know the sequence beforehand which is the case for training you
should actually do it sequentially because of the way that rnn are structured which is a
composition of functions so it can because the training cost is really high for rnn people have
moved to transformers so s4 tries to actually bridge this gap so have a good running time at
the inference time and also have some linear have the capability of being paralyzed during the
training time so we try to answer this question using state space model
so the question is what is the state space model basically you can consider a space space model
is some kind of a mapper that maps or basically a better to say a function that maps a one
dimensional input signal u of t into an n dimensional latent state x of t so x has dimension of n
and u has dimension of one and then it projects x into one dimensional output signal y of t
it's actually coming from the control systems so this idea existed for many years before even
the emergence of deep learning but
as you can see it's it's basically based on the differential equation that
in this particular equation on the right you can see that the gradient of x which is of
dimension the x is of dimension n is basically a function of x and the input u and then the output
y is the projection of x plus some d of u sometimes i think particularly in this paper
they actually neglect d and just talk about a b and c in their formulation
you should also consider that while we have simplified the equations to one dimensional
input and one dimensional output signal you can consider this as you can also generalize
all we are saying here to a multi-dimensional input and output
if you want to see this whole equation from the viewpoint of deep learning you can see a b c and d
as parameters that will be learned during the training by gradient descent and as i said for
simplicity basically we can discard d for the rest of the conversation
so this figure actually shows the relationship and shows the importance of the a matrix
which actually somehow it preserved the history of the previous states basically
and as i said ssm was first introduced in control models in 1960s and as i mentioned x has much
higher dimension than u and y which is our input and output and whatever we are discussing here is on
u y and x are continuous here and our function of time and we will see how we can discretize that
because what we are dealing with sequence modeling in deep learning is that we are not talking about
the continuous functions we have discrete functions
yeah so basically you can use ssm for different kind of tasks like continuous
continuous representation recurrence representation and convolutional representation
and we will go through each of them in details
now let's talk about how we can actually discretize the continuous ssm formula so that we can actually
use that utilize that in deep learning as well
we need to do some additional work after that but this is the very first step
so let's say the problem now is that instead of having some continuous function u of t
now we have u not u1 u2 and so we have some discrete inputs basically
and the way that we do that we should discretize this sequence this continuous function with a
step size delta and basically we can see delta which representing the resolution of the input
for example in the images and u sub i can be viewed as a sample from function u of t
so here basically we can see how we can derive this discretization so given the formulas I just
showed you we can actually use Euler discretization so xt plus delta which is our step size is equal
to xt plus delta times x prime which is the gradient of x so basically you can rewrite that by saying
xt plus delta times a of xt plus b times u of t because x prime t here has this
a particular formula so we just substitute this right hand side with x prime t to get this one
so now the next step is just to simplify the previous equation to get i plus delta times
a times xt plus delta b ut so and you can basically name this
multiplier as a bar and name this one as b bar so this way you can see that starting from xt plus
delta which was the step size we wanted to use to discretize the continuous u of t function
we can actually derive this nice form to actually represent x in a discrete format
so basically we can actually see this discretization as some kind of recurrent
representation that we have in recurrent neural network
so basically instead of what happened here is that because of this discretization instead
of working with continuous function u of t and y of t now we work with u sub k and y sub k
which indicates the k indicates the time steps or each of the tokens in our input sequence
and as you can see now the equation becomes a recurrence on x sub k very similar to the
recurrent neural network and if you want to use the same terminology that we have in RNN
you can see x sub k as basically the hidden state which is carried out in RNN
as I said the main thing about RNN is that there are more efficient and inference time because
they don't have that quadratic multiplication you just need the previous state and as soon as you
have the previous state you can get the output but the problem with them is that you cannot
paralyze them and so in the training you cannot train a model which is sequential because all of
your GPUs should have some kind of parallel computation to get the most out of the GPUs you
have so that's really important thing so just to make clear that we understood this relationship
between SSM and RNN is that if you write down the equation so x sub k is actually
function of the previous state which is multiplied by a bar plus the input
times the b bar and then the output is just a projection of the next state by the matrix c bar
very similar to the recurrent neural network. Now let's give some mechanical example to better
understand how these things actually works so consider mass attached to a wall by a spring
with forward position y t so y t shows the position at time t and we have the force which is our input
u of t applied to the mass and we also have other parameters like spring constant mass
and friction that exists now we can relate everything with the following differential equation
which is m times the acceleration which is the second gradient of second order gradient of
position is equal to the force u of t minus b times velocity which is the gradient of y
minus k y t so this is just a physical formula but the nice thing about that is that you can
actually rewrite this physical formula using a b and c matrix we just saw in SSM and using these
kind of parameters and if you put it if you just multiply these with the y with the u and x you
get to the same equation and basically as you can see a relates all of these terms together so it
has a very important role in actually holding the equation together and so basically here c shows the
first dimension of the hidden state and the second dimension as I said is the velocity
and a relates all of these terms together and the following is just the code of the
of this whole equation using SSM so it's just a simple
code you can see it actually
on the author's page that I have put as a reference I don't want to spend too much on this
and this is just an example of how the SSM actually models this so given the force u of k
you can get the and the position y k you can actually see the
see the place that the object will be based on the prediction done by SSM sorry the position
is actually predicted by the SSM so in this example we just use one SSM with two hidden
states but we can stack many SSM together in deep learning model
as I said the problem with the current formulation we have is that
the training time so basically the main issue here is that okay we have this nice
formula so far but how can we actually train the model if it is sequential so we need to actually
try to dig a little bit deeper here to actually transform RNN into some kind of representation
that can be paralyzed and we use we actually have the opportunity to fully exploit the
capacity of our GPUs one way to do that is actually we can turn the RNN representation
into a CNN representation by actually unrolling it and why CNN representation is better than
RNN representation is because you can actually do training of convolutional neural network
in parallel so you can you don't have the training problem of RNN which is blocked and
recurrent SSM can be actually written as a discrete convolution and let's see the equations
by unrolling them so you start with x sub k a bar plus b bar and so basically this is the
general formula we have and y sub k is c bar k c bar times x sub k
so x naught is actually b bar times u naught and based on the equation on the left you just
multiply a bar by x naught to get x sub one and if you continue like that you actually see that
there is some pattern actually emerging here which actually you can see the impact of the matrix
a bar which actually somehow it is actually
propagating informations from previous states into new states and we will talk about this a
little bit more when it comes to a hippo matrix and how we can actually make this
recall even more efficient and y naught is actually c bar times b bar u naught
and as you can see even for the output again a bar actually emerges so the matrix a bar has a very
important factor in remembering and recalling the previous states
now as we said for training SSM models we need to actually use better architecture
to make sure that the training can be done in parallel and as we saw that we can actually
unroll the whole equation to get to this final output which is as you can see it's actually
kind of a kernel multiplication this is the kernel multiplication of k bar which is defined
like this to the input input tokens y naught up to yk
so k bar is called the SSM convolution kernel or filter and you can basically see k bar as a giant
filter applied to the input u so the major problem here now is that now we have the problem that
k bar is a giant filter and we need to make sure that the computation of k bar is actually
done efficiently and so but still we have solved the problem of not being able to
have the parallel computation in training time
so basically the main takeaway from this is that now output can be computed without computing the
internal state so as you recall in rnn we had the problem that the output if you wanted to
actually calculate the output you need to have the internal state at time step t minus one
so and for t minus one state internal state at t minus one you need to have
internal state at time step t minus two and so on so you had to do this sequential computation
but now we have addressed this problem using convolution
you
but just to give you a little bit of background on convolution theorem
just to give you a broad definition of how it worked it says that the Fourier transform
of a convolution of two signals so here we are talking about continuous function and that's why
you need to do this inverse first Fourier transform to actually get it back to the discrete one
is the product of their Fourier transform so the Fourier transform of convolution of two
signal is the product of their Fourier transform and the convolution of two continuous signal f
and g is actually can be done like this
so the Fourier transform of a product of two signal is the convolution of their
Fourier transform so that that's the main thing that main trick that we use to actually make the
computation more efficient
and this is just the raw code that you can use to actually do the fast Fourier transform so you
so basically no fft is a Boolean flag to choose between direct convolution and fast Fourier
transform based convolution so when it is activated you first do the
fast Fourier transform from the NumPy library
and finally you do the reverse of the fast Fourier transform to get the final result
so far we discussed about a kind of architecture that we can use
to actually make the computation more efficient when it comes to dealing with
long sequences long range sequences but the question is is this new kind of
architecture is capable of addressing long range dependency and actually it has been shown that
the basic SSM performs very poorly in practice why because of the formula we just saw before it
contains lots of multiplication and that's the thing that happens in RNN because you have
nested multiplication as you saw the matrix A bar
is actually multiplied a lot by itself if let's say the sequence length is really
high it's actually multiplied by the order of that by the order of the sequence length
so you can get the problem of vanishing or exploding gradient and
this actually can create the long-term dependency problem
to address this issue we can use hippo matrix to actually solve this problem
so basically I think now we have we have come to the definition of s4 so what is s4
s4 is SSM status-based model plus hippo plus a structured matrices so what hippo does is
very simple so it uses the special formulas for A and B matrices in SSM so this is A
this is B in the formula that we saw for a status-based model and as we saw in the
unrolling of the status-based model computation for the discrete space
A is basically can be seen as the matrix that captured previous states so it actually decides
how the information is passed through different states so that's a very important matrix basically
and so what hippo does is that it specifies a specific class of matrices of A that's actually
allow the state to be preserved so the model retains its ability to recall previous states
and it's defined on the left hand side here so as you can see the hippo matrix is nothing
other than a triangular matrix where the
where this side of the matrix is zero and only this side of the matrix has values
so this way it has been shown that hippo actually can better preserve the information of the previous
steps and so there is one example here that's using this kind of matrix that basically preserved the
previous state you can actually improve the performance on sequential MNIST classification
from 60 percent to 98 percent so up to 38 percent improvement and hippo matrix basically tries to
compress the past history state and basically approximately reconstruct history using this kind
of formula so basically here we want to see an example of hippo in reconstructing a function
so here the function input function is u which is shown in the black line and x here is the blue
line which has higher dimension as we can see it has multiple line and the red line here is the
output y t which is the reconstruction function so we want y t to be the same as x t and here
after 10 000 steps we want to see how perfectly this ssm dynamic using hippo matrix is able to
reconstruct the function so as you can see at each step the
ssm is updated so starting from zero to 10 000 at each step it is updated based on the formulas
for a and other things we saw and so the green line here is somehow some kind of
weight matrix that tells the ssm that basically the more recent history has higher importance
for me than the older one so that's the only thing that's the same and as we can see here specifically
toward the end so at the 10 000 steps so this is the shot from the 10 000 step
and the ssm is actually is able to perfectly reconstruct the function but as we go toward the
beginning of the function the accuracy drops and here I should say that we have only used 64
hidden states here for our ssm which is much lower than 10 000 so that's really remarkable
that the model has this amount of accuracy and basically this test can be used for online
function reconstruction and you can see more information here on this but the question is
how hippo matrix keeps track of history so as I said it produces a hidden states with particular
definition for matrix A that actually memorizes the history and basically it is actually keeping
track of the coefficient of legend polynomial and these coefficients actually let it approximate
all the previous history and legend polynomial are a system of complete and orthogonal polynomials
and here on the right which is from the wikipedia wikipedia you can see the first six legend polynomial
and here is another example so the red line is our
input and this is again the same reconstruction that we want to actually keep track of and these
blue lines are actually our legend coefficient and hippo matrix actually update these coefficient
on each step and if you actually sum up these coefficient you actually can
reconstruct these if you sum up these blue lines you actually can get an approximation of the red
which is the reconstruction of the history
so ssm neural network so all of the the things that we said is actually we can use it to model a
neural network we now have all the ingredients basically needed to build a basic ssm so we assume
that we are going to learn the b matrix c matrix step size delta and the scalar d
and the hippo matrix is used for the transition a which is what we saw in the definition
and the code on the right is basically a pytorch implementation you can see that
um it first defines the um parameters it first defines the shape of these matrices and then
these are uh first discretize um and then based on the step given and then we do the
uh convolution uh to get the final output
and here as you can see we can also add uh dropouts and layer norm i'm not going to
cover this the code is available so
due to the time limit and here is um the emnist experiment i was saying so here
given the initial few pixels which is shown in white we use ssm to actually predict the
remaining pixels so the green lines is actually showing the ground truth and the red line is
the prediction by ssm and as you can see it has i'm sorry the red line is actually the prediction
by s4 and as you can see the red line and green line actually has a good match
but uh again there are some limitations with
ssm model s4 models particularly they have not performed to the same performance that we have
seen in uh transformers and the key weakness is that their inability to do content based reasoning
so they actually given this sequence it actually the model is incapable of uh
understanding the content and the relationship between the tokens because uh because as you saw
the matrices a b and c are time invariant it doesn't change throughout the time it's constant
and mamba is actually tries to address this weakness specifically
um so let's talk about mamba mamba has several improvement in comparison to previous models
it introduces discrete modality allowing model to selectively propagate or forget information
along the sequence length so it's basically selected when it comes to propagating information
and it also introduces some hardware of their parallel algorithm which we will not cover here
due to the time limit and it has a very simplified architecture that we will see by the end
uh the good things about mamba is that it has a very much faster inference
five times higher throughput compared with transformer it has a linear scaling which is
what we are looking for and uh basically these features allow allow mamba to be used for larger
sequence length up to million which is our final uh goal and it actually achieves some
state-of-the-art performance across different modalities and it's basically comparable with
transformer and we will see what's the main design changes here so basically mamba the key
difference is that it has some selection mechanism so it has the ability to efficiently
select data in an input dependent manner so what we saw in s4 design
was that it was time invariant it didn't actually select a specific input or disregard
specific token from the input so mamba introduces a simple selection mechanism that allows the
model to filter out irrelevant information and remember relevant information so this is
very very similar to lstm so as you recall in lstm we have something called gating mechanism
that actually allows the model to modify forget or keep previous state information
so that's the same thing so that's the main punchline of this work as we see these
forgotten models like lstm are are actually coming back to life so this is something very
interesting to see that these kinds of novelties that existed in previous generations of
neural network architectures are actually have some resurgence in mamba and s4 models which was
very interesting to myself another important thing is that mlp blocks of transformers in
mamba is actually compressed into a single block which we will see
so let's talk about the selective status space block that exists in mamba
so basically here ht is our state so i think you can see here that the notation has changed
previously we call these x but here we call input x and the output is still y here and a
is the main matrix that's still here also keep track of the history here
but one important thing is that in contrast to s4 we have some projection layer here
that given the input x it actually projected and then b delta which is our step and c are actually
a function of a projection of our input x so there are no longer time invariant there are actually
time variants but a stays the same
so let's talk about the selective state space motivation why we need this so the fundamental
problem of sequence modeling is compressing the context into a smaller state that's the main
thing because we want to remember and recall the context of previous tokens if let's say the
sequence length is really large so what's the problem with transformer as i said the attention
is very effective but at the same time very inefficient which is n squared and at the same time
because of the autoregressive inference that exists in both attention and
rnn you need to somehow explicitly store the entire context
so
so on the other hand recurrent model are as i said efficient because they have finite state
but at the same time they are very limited by how well they can actually compress the context
that's really important because the context here is
the main thing that makes the model important performance improve so basically what we want is
an efficient model that has small states at the same time the model should be effective
in a way that the its state actually stores all the necessary information from the context
i say all the necessary information because some of the information are useless so you
can't discard some of the information you don't have to have infinite memory to memorize everything
so we as a human also have limited memory so the main novelty of mamba is that achieves this
balance by using selection so it actually selectively recall previous input tokens and as we saw in
the previous slide the matrices b delta and c are function of the projection of input
actually achieve this result so to give you a better understanding of why this is important
let's consider two simple tasks one of them is copying so the model should basically here
given the input tokens which are different colors and there are some white colors in the
middle so the model in the first task should actually shift the input token by some amount
here this can be easily done by s4 but if you tweak this a problem to something else
which is selective copying in selective copying you actually add these irrelevant input token
which is shown by white boxes here so you basically these are just some noise
and the model should be able to actually preserve the same sequence
of input for colored token in the output so if the input is blue orange red green the output should
be blue orange red green and discard all these white tokens white boxes basically
and one of the things that we notice and we will see the graphs for this specific
example is that s4 model all of them fails but mamba has a very astonishing performance
achieving almost 100 percent accuracy and that's mainly because of the selection mechanism we will
also dive into the algorithm of mamba and see how it's achieved so mamba ignores irrelevant input
and because of its selective copying but s4 actually fails because it does it's not content
aber as you saw the a b c and the defining the s4 is actually not able to
change throughout the time it's not actually function of input but that's what i'm saying
another task is also induction head that the model actually requires to recall
information from previous input to build the next input so here for example if so here it
should understand that after each black colored box there should come some blue color box
and we still see even in this particular example if for example in the test set you
actually put some noise white noises basically white box noises the model is incapable of
understanding that given
basically given this particular input the next thing should be blue box it's incapable of for
s4 but mamba is actually able to achieve and as i said the main difference between mamba and s4
is that mamba relaxes the idea of time transition between input sequences or basically independent
it is not in mamba
okay now we dive into the difference between algorithm of s4 and mamba basically
so as you can see let's start with the s4 here we have x which is in the shape of bite size
sequence length and token dimension
and y is actually have the same dimension as the input x
a has the dimension d which is the token dimension or embedding basically we call this
embedding in large language model and n is basically the dimension of our hidden estate here
and as i say a captures a history and as you can see b c and also have the same
dimensions as a and delta has a dimension of d and we discretize delta a and b to get a bar
and b bar and then we can get our y using the ssm architecture so it is time invariant so
the a b c and delta doesn't change over the time it's the same it stays the same
but for selection s6 is actually things are completely different not completely basically
the input output and the a matrix is the same but the matrices b c and delta are not
constant anymore they are actually a function of x as you can see
that's why they have an additional dimension l here which is dependent of the
time step basically in the input sequence and so basically as i said
this allows mamba to be time varying
and yeah as as you can see the value of delta b and c can actually changes based on the input given
input and as i said the punchline of my presentation is that mamba moves s4 a little bit closer to
lstm by introducing time dependent transition from time step to time step in processing input
sequence but at the same time it still preserves the quality of s4 in time efficiency
and let's see the mamba architecture so here you can see ssm which is
a selective space model that we shown is actually inside here in the mamba and you have the
projection layer which is followed by the convolution and then you have this gating
in the between very similar to the lstm
and let's talk about a little bit about the empirical evaluation so we talked about the
selective copying task which is which the input sequence contains some
white noises the model should be able to discard those and you can see that mamba
actually achieves the highest accuracy in this selective copying task here h3 is actually a kind
of s4 design another task which is induction heads that it should understand that for example
after black token there is a blue token that we discussed and you can see that mamba
no matter what the test sequence length is achieves the highest performance and you can
see that all the other s4 as the test length sequence increases and they fail and this is
for downstream evaluation dna you can see that mamba actually achieves the highest scores
on average accuracy scores on average and that's the end of my talk and i hope you enjoyed it
um can definitely contact me if there is any other questions and thank you have a good day