My name is Ibshah Bairan. I'm an author. I'm going to be talking about how we can
do algorithms more efficiently. Before starting my first work, I would like to
propose these two papers, which form the base for the first chip. I know you're like that.
Yeah. So this would form the base for the first paper, that is the algorithmic networks and branching it.
So this is what the algorithm looks like. So we conclude through all the layers,
and then we autoregressively carry the documents. So what the authors of shallow
weak networks experimented, they experimented on to see how each chip evolved during the
past. So they classified each layer, and they saw that after some point in the
past, the model tends to evolve. Now what is this? If you see the dot, the x-axis represents the layer,
and we have two metric prediction entropy, which shows that it can be one of the
measures of how confident the model is. And another one is the algorithmic line.
It shows how accurate the model is. So we can see that after
yeah, up to 10 layers, the confidence of the model is confused, but it becomes more inaccurate.
So the model is confident on inaccurate predictions. This is what they call over thinking of the
model. So what did we exit at this point? And so this overall mechanism of exiting early
during the past is what the early exit mechanism is. Yeah, so it looks like this. So we
take the output of any of the middle layer, and we proceed autoregressively as we did our
now what metric, how do we decide when to exit? So the shallow deep network uses prediction
probabilities to exit, and the branching act uses entropy scores to exit. So in the example,
the threshold is 0.9. So whenever the metric exceeds this threshold, we exit from that layer.
So this is a pin 9 method. And yeah, the way to draw back is that the higher confidence score
of high probability doesn't necessarily imply that the tasker is correct.
Right, so one of the other methods is to use patience. So here we set a hyper parameter, which
for example, will be set P. So if the model's output at the layer remains same for T plus
one consecutive layers, then we exit at the T plus one layer. So in the example, the patient is one.
And so if the output of the layer remains same for two consecutive times, then we exit at this
layer. Yeah, so this approach uses Albert model as a base model, and it is evaluated on the viewbench
model. And you can see speed up of around 1.5 times. And one thing to notice here is that for all
the tasking viewbench model, the accuracy on development set as well as the test set increases
from the base model. So why is the case? So author claims and proves that as long as this
condition is maintained, the accuracy of the model will increase, which I will not go into
detail now, but we can discuss it again in time permits. And for some, for some of the patients,
certain range of the patients, the accuracy of the model increases for different tasks you can see
the x part such as accuracy and accuracy is the layers, the patients are.
Yeah, now the author is also claiming that it also depends the model, this mechanism also
depends against the development set attack. So this text pooler model is the one, the model that
invades, we ever see the text. So what it means that it changes some token, some words to its
replaces it with its synonyms and the output model changes. So this is what this is one kind
of attack called token manipulation. And so this, yeah, so this attack successfully works on
bird model, bird base model, and it decreases the accuracy from 8.96 to 5.5. So the attack
goes pretty well. And after employing this early exit phase mechanism, the accuracy after the attack
increases from 5.5 to 9.3. So it somewhat depends against the attack. Now why is this the case?
Because we saw that the model reaches the correct predictions at some point in the
power pass, but after that it misclassifies the output. So if we exit early in the power pass then
in general it increases accuracy.
Yeah, so this works on some input samples. So the overall
observation is that for some input samples, we don't need to pass through like compute
to all the layers instead we can exit in the middle. Yeah, so this was the first different
questions here. Can you go back to the previous page? So the attack you are depending against here
in this paper is to ensure that some of the non-crafted sentence or statement that will
generate more statements of the example I think. So it's one of the, like what I would say that
it's one of the pros I could say that this mechanism depends against, so the overall aim was not to
show this, but it's one of the outcomes of the mechanism that it depends against the
attack. Okay, yeah. As far as the defense against additive attacks goes, this is defending against
certain types of attacks that are built for normal LLM models. If somebody knows that they're using
this type of fort circuit system, they just defend like a design adversarial attack that will
exploit this confidence. It's their assessment of its ability to defend the alliance attacks
because they're they're defending against attacks that may not be used on that model.
So one thing that it depends against this token manipulation, the particular kind of attack,
and yeah, it can be possible that we could train the up who learn to accommodate this,
but if you see that accuracy only includes like 5459 points, so it's somewhat different
to this, but yeah, it's possible that it learns this as early as 5. I have one other question.
So my main question is if we're dealing with more general tasks, does this confidence,
do you think that's still effective, or do you think that this is really only effective
when we're dealing with in sample situations? Okay. I'm not sure about this particular mechanism,
but there are other techniques in which we use some kind of calibration set. And it like the
next thing that I'm going to present is it is training, it is calibrated on set and it provides
some finite sample statistical identity. So it works on finite sample, but the calibration set
we can pay, we can update the calibration set and work on the individual institution.
I'm not sure about this, but there are other methods which work, so we'll generalize this.
What's the difference between PABY and Shell?
Yeah, so PABY uses the patients and Shell is the one that uses the branching probabilities
and branching probabilities for Shell and entropy for branching.
Okay.
Yeah, so this algorithm adaptive language model is also an early exit-based mechanism,
but it provides a principal method for increasing efficiency
by remaining confident in the quality of the resulting prediction. So it overall checks the
output sequence and it checks the quality of it. We ensure that the output sequence is of high
computing and it also addresses other challenges. So that will see positive gain more insights or
gain more insight in the office table. So one thing that you want in the early exit-based
mechanism is, yeah, so in attention mechanism, if you want to compute the hidden state of
layer, of some layer, we would need the hidden state of previous layers for all the time
steps, but if we were to exit here, then we won't have these hidden states. So what we
do is it's propagate the hidden states down the layers. So basically copy the hidden states
and so the authors here try to find the impact of it on the accuracy. So they did this while
performing an order contest in which they exited from the layer where the output of the layer
matches the ground proof. So in this case, at this layer, the output is equal to y1. So they exit
from this layer, likewise all the other types. So the only divergence that the output will have
is because of the state copying mechanism. So this was an order contest that they performed
and they found out that the accuracy of the model decreased from 38.32 to 38.24, that's a slight
decrease and on average out of eight layers, it used 1.53 layers. So this indicates two things,
that the state copying mechanism works and there's a great potential for saving compute
if you use only basic poly exit based mechanism.
Then authors also did two kinds of perturbations. First one is sampling based in which
they sampled at a time step, they sampled 10th rank token and for all other time
step, they sampled, they sampled greatly the first rank token that is available. So that sampling
based on layer based in which they selected, I did answer, they selected the output of the
first layer and for and same as above, for all other layers, they sampled greatly by last layer.
And they found out that for sampling based, we were to select 10th rank token
initially in the inference process, the time step, it greatly affects the model,
the accuracy drops very much. And if it were to work on later in the time step, then the accuracy
isn't dropping that much. And one more thing that for the layer based, that is the orange line,
even if we perform this perturbation earlier in the inference, it doesn't drop a case like that.
So overall, what this shows is if the model receives perturbation at earlier time step,
it negatively affects the performance. So what they did is they decide they set different thresholds
for different time steps. So we can use a higher threshold for earlier time steps and lower thresholds
for later time steps. Or we can use a decaying function for lambda based on like we can
configure it based on the temperature. So initially we would have a higher
threshold and later we did in the time steps, different times lower threshold.
Now on what metric do we apply these thresholds on? So they experimented with three
confidence measure. So first the software goes to the difference between top two software's values
and they apply threshold on the difference. Another is the density situation. So they
compute the cosine similarity between two constitutive hidden layers and early exit
classifiers and they decay to classifiers. Classifier to predict the likelihood of exiting early.
Yeah, so we have thresholds, we have metrics. So what this method is, we calibrate the local
or token exit decisions. That is, we calibrate those thresholds such that the global sequence
level constraints are maintained. So that the quality of the final output is in checker
with some arbitrary, with arbitrarily high probability that I talk about it later. So it's a user chosen
probability. Yeah, so what do we need for the elimination set which consists of
prompts to elimination and the global constraint that I talked about? Let's keep the final prediction
in check. Yeah, so the global constraint, so if we denote wildly that it as the adaptive output
and the standard output as bipolar, then any dissimilarity and we have a dissimilarity function.
So the dissimilarity between these two should be less than some tolerance
and the confidence of this being less than some tolerance should be greater than some probability
and this probability is 1 minus epsilon and where epsilon is the derivative
and it is user chosen. So basically we calibrate the lambda using this constraint
and it's not necessary that a given prompt has a single gold answer. It can have multiple
gold answers. So what we do is we bound the risk. So we compare the wildly with the gold answer
or set up gold answer and it should be bounded by the risk of
standard output should be less than some tolerance. So this both this
dissimilarity function and this function we use a standard metric based on the
data set, the method that we use for data set. So here are the three data sets that
they offer. So now we have global constraint, we have the local thresholds. What's the method?
The method is because we specify grid of possible values, possible lambdas, possible
thresholds and that may result in acceptable generation and we choose the lambda using some
statistical tools. So in short we cast this hyper parameter selection problem to multiple
angles this testing problem and this is done by applying this learn then test framework.
So basically it identifies the statistically valid subset of this specified lambda values
and it gives us a subset of this that is valid. Now what does this statistically valid mean?
It means that for example the error radius 0.05. So this means that the optimal risk
is guaranteed to be within tolerance at least 95% of time. So that's why we use this
hypothesis testing problem instead of the hyper parameter selection. So here are some
statistical guarantees. So these are the three data sets, CNN, DN, the list for textualization,
WNT promotion translation and for something. So basically so the three lines that you see here
is the softmax, the orange one is the even state saturation metric and these are the three
metrics that is solid and the X-axis is average decoder layers protocol. So it is like you can
see that softmax has a higher accuracy in almost all the tasks for a given decoder for every
for given average decoder layers. So you can see in sorry you can see in table as well. So
these are the three data sets and so these are different tolerance level that the authors
experimented and they took the for all the experiments they took the error radius 0.05.
Yeah so in all of the experiment the number of average decoder layers used by the softmax is
less compared to the other two and in majority of the cases the speed up that we see
is more in softmax. So these are the empirical results and on an average it uses
round 2 to 1.5 to we see maximum
2.8, 3.5. On an average it uses at 1.5 to 3.5 times it shows it shows 1.5 to 3.5 times speed up
but at a cost of the floating point operation it has more floating point operations involved
in softmax. Yeah so for all the softmax sufferings and it generates the greatest decreasing number of
decoder layers and that's because part of the statement can be increased.
So these two methods where we've gone on the exiting mechanism so in the power pass we evaluate
whether you want to exit at a particular layer or not. Now the third one is
a third one is a bit different so here we sample from the model in a faster way
such that it doesn't make any changes to all
and so by computing the function parallel so to give it an overview so here we have
a draft model and approximation model which is much smaller and efficient
and we use that model to make a guess or to make few guesses and these guesses will be
confirmed by the or confirmed by a target model in parallel. To give an example so suppose
assuming that we have this output from the model till now and we select the like we select
how many guesses we want from the smaller model let's say two so we predict we sequentially
in predict the two tokens from the smaller model it may be 97 million parameters in the
model so now at this point after the sequential prediction we would have three inputs
three setup inputs that we would so that is the quickdown box first one and the second is the
quickdown box jumps and third one that includes over and we give this three input to our target
model which is our that has large number of parameters and we predict but the next token
for all the three inputs in parallel so it for the for the question put it its jumps for the second
it's over and now we compare this outputs with we compare the output of the target model with the
output of the dark model that's the approximation model and if it's correct then we take hand so
this is the this is one iteration of the process of the speculative decoding and if in the best
case scenario is that all the tokens are accepted so and if we take if we have if you made gamma
guesses then we would have gamma plus one prediction at the end of prostitution
yeah and what if one of the guesses is wrong so the target model we have taken eight instead of
jump so we will discard all the predictions that the trap model made after this point
and we'll just replace it with eight
right yeah so this is the algorithm that I just showed so here we make gamma guesses
sequentially then we are using the mq that is our approximation model then we make
uh when we use mq that is our target model then we use this to compute the tokens in parallel
and then this particular block is the modified rejection sampling so it's the method to
check whether uh this to output is same or not so it uses this rejection something about
rejection sampling which is given overview is a way to sample our data from a complex distribution
using as easy like analytically feasible wrap up analytically feasible distribution
is this one such as caution so you can see you can say that this analytically feasible distribution
is our draft model distribution and this is the uh a target model distribution so
in short we try to match the distribution the complex distribution with the help of
this approximation distribution
yeah so what it does is that it guarantees that the output from the system
have the same distribution as those of the as those of the target model
yeah so they're also in like similar to the second model it also checks the
global or global output takes the quality of the final sequence and they call this the whole
process because it's something okay yeah so yes it's just notice that it
completely it computes multiple inputs in parallel so it will require some additional
memory so
yeah so the additional computation resources should be available if we want to use this approach and
and we are using this method we are able to accelerate the inference without changing the
architecture uh without changing the training procedure operating models and without changing
the model models our frustration by using the modified distribution sampling episode
yeah so if we so we have the number of tokens there to be guessed if we denote it as gamma
and we denote the measure of how well the draft model approximates the target model as alpha
so how much they are close will be alpha then if like for a certain gamma like say seven real
outline if the uh measure if they are good the distribution output distribution are closer
to each other there is a high alpha so we will be able to uh guess more number of tokens kind of
easy so if it's seven and if it's seven and the alpha is there it's a coin and then we will be able to
guess round six that is 90 percent of the token property
so in short the alpha is proportional to the expected number of tokens that are accepted
also
for a family of model alpha depends on the size of the approximation model as well
so if the draft model distribution is very close to uh the target target model then it means that
the draft model is bigger as well that it is able to run the kind of representations
so there's a trade-off right so uh between making nq and anti-similar and nq
model to like making the nq model cheap to
do
yeah so what's the one time what time is the total running time of the model so the last row you
can see maybe it's a base so yellow part is the nq part and the southern uh the violet the purple
blocks are the uh one decoding time step and uh the red red so if we use the speculative
speculative decoding then the red line here is the target models encoder and the blue strips that
we see is a sequential run of the uh approximation models recorded so overall it improves the
ball time so decreases the ball time
the yellow one is the uh target models mp is the target models p is the target model and q is the
draft model oh the selector yeah so the larger model will take more time in encoding as well as
decoding compared to the draft models uh
oh okay but why is pool actually this here oh this is pool yeah that's true but it's yeah
so the combination is so there are multiple blue strips here oh i see
so the the larger the cover the more acceleration
but it depends on how uh well like how well the um target model and draft model are
right yeah close to each other in time yeah right so yeah the model is low and they are not
closely like they are not closing up then it to yeah right okay go go back
yeah so they didn't like uh improve the gamma flow right so at some point like the gamma
increasing that's all yeah exactly yeah that's my that would be my other point so we have to choose
optimal gamma yeah okay i see yeah so
yeah so as i said that oh yeah so let's suppose if the alpha is pointed so the draft model and
target model are much closer and here sees the cost coefficient so it's a ratio of the time taken
to run the draft model by the ratio of time taken to by the time taken to run the target model so
that's cost coefficient okay so if it's higher then we can cannot afford to like have incorrect
more number of incorrect places so it will take more time so for c equals to 0.1 we have
uh lower optimal gamma compared to the model that has uh
there is there is much more smaller or much more faster to run so it has higher number
so they have derived this uh particular
uh they have derived this plot as well as this plot using mechanical
generations so yeah we can compute if we know that if we know the uh acceptance rate of
uh the draft model then we can compute this
okay
and yeah so the screen so they used e5 xxl 0.1 million times the target model
approximation of the experiment is at least three yeah 8800 million 250 million and scientists
are looking and yeah they used english to german translation and text summarization to these two
datasets and with uh and they observed that the t5 model with like the balance of this gamma
so the guess tokens and alpha they get around 3.4 to 3.1 speed up around two to three times
oh what is that uh oh alpha is the measure is the measure of how well their draft model
approximates the diagram
sorry i have a question um do you know that one plot where you've got optimal gamma and uh the
measure itself on the axes intuitively i think that the more tokens you're guessing the less likely
your measure of draftness would be like that it's almost as if this is moving in the opposite of
a friendly direction right so if you have to confirm every single token and you've got a higher
probability of guessing that because you don't have like long range compounding errors
so if i've got my small model and my big model right and gamma is how many tokens i'm going to
predict small model and then i compare with my big model and there's a measure of acceptance
based on how many tokens i predicted the longer uh the bigger gamma is the more tokens i have to
accurate they get i would assume the measure for success would go down if the number is going up
it doesn't collect it represents the optimal gamma not the gamma so these are the optimal
gamma values right but for a measure of uh 0.9 so i'm very likely to accept it they have 24 tokens
is the the number of tokens for uh the model that is very efficient to run so we get a poor
more number of calls to the model but if it's if you see that if the model is uh
not efficient to run then the number of tokens are very less so we can afford to have a great
guesses for each model that is that has less runtime then we take this large gamma values okay so this
isn't relating to the actual probability of being accepted but it's how much i can afford yeah
it's exactly what i'm talking about yeah i'll check
yeah so then i'm going to mention that the limitation of this model is that you need extra compute
the memory is less yeah so that's a no yeah one other question when we're doing that confirmation
figure out that we discard what was predicted by the smaller model is that just a single token
at the end of what was predicted that we do and we assume everything else was successful or how do we
kick how much we're confirming because if you were to confirm the whole sequence
then you'd build up like a buffer of lag computation over time because the slower model
would be doing one token at a time and the faster model would have done like 24 so the big model
kicked forever to figure out what's the success no we passed sequentially predict like if we take
like 10 guesses and we sequentially predict all the guesses yep and then we give 11 inputs to the
model to compute in parallel and once the once the target model has completed all the levels
all the 11 inputs then we'll have like 11 outputs right and then we then we confirm
sequentially that uh which token writes a parameter so i guess my question is because the
smaller model runs really efficiently is going further and further and further ahead in the
model as it tries to confirm doesn't that don't you get to a point where you'll never actually
be able to confirm because the smaller model is just so far ahead no no no we limit it we limit it
we limit it by the uh gamma the picture so in one iteration if the number of tokens that are
available here is two then in that iteration we only we only guess two tokens after it and it stops
and it will target model compounds it and then really so the smaller model will have to wait for
the reference but then don't you see the efficiency gain because i'm just bound by the target model
speed again no no the target model only needs to do like just for it i don't know that that's
okay yeah so yeah the the target model still needs to go over all of them but but it's like
the impactful right it's not my opinion that's why that's true yeah yeah that's why i think so
yeah any other versions
i know that this was only the scope of inference but uh i don't know if you're really looking to if
there's any any part of research doing this for training to like kind of train a model that
i think summits the small model that i put summits the large and larger like you mean feedback
you know the confirmation can bring feedback that the small model can learn from
just i don't know that if you do something similar do you train yourself
uh that's interesting point but i'm not sure about the training part
so you mean some sort of distillation yes yeah like kind of
i mean like so you're using small model to approximate the larger models uh
if you do it like yes and if i were to speak back from the model to improve the small models
yes so exactly feedback it's more implementation
approximately like you know you might say okay i'll handle it yeah yeah then there has to be papers
so overall the first two models pavy and calm adopted an early exit strategy
and in addition to that calm also took in into account the global consistency
finally the uh the last approach uh is compatible with the first two models
as well as any other uh dynamic speed up uh yeah that's also my part