Hi, this is Max. Today we will be talking about image generation.
So first, we will go through the task definition and the paradigm method of image generation.
And then we will talk about six pivotal papers, which includes latent diffusion model, image
gen, dot e2, party, pixel alpha, and stable diffusion XL turbo. So let's get started.
So what was image generation? In the context of year 2015, it was all about unconditional image
generation, which as you can see here, those generated image of human faces are uncontrollable.
So there's lack of contributing. And nowadays, image generation is often referred to text to
image synthesis, where you can see here, we have a text. And then with the text, we can
synthesize the image that the image will be aligned to the text. So how is it done?
So for state of the art image generation methods, they actually follow a similar paradigm.
In particular, they will have three major components, including a text encoder,
a generation model, and a latency decoder. In detail, you will first have a text form.
By fitting the text form into the text encoder, you get the text vector.
And then with the text vector and the input latency, you fit them into the generation model,
which could be a diffusion model or other kind of models. And it will produce an intermediate
latent, which can be visible or non visible by human. Then you fit this intermediate latent
into a latent decoder. Then you will be able to get back a synthesized image that aligned with the
text form. So the first paper we're going to discuss is the latent diffusion model,
which is also stable diffusion. What it does is that it basically denies in the latent space
instead of the data space compared to the traditional diffusion model. So you can see here,
it has a VAE autoencoder structure that it contains an encoder and decoder. And during the
training process, the latent was compressed. But how compressed is it?
The down-sampling factor 8 on the latents is actually the best configuration,
such that the latents will be 64 by 64. And in the study, they found that
pixel-based LDM requires substantially larger training times, while too much perceptual compression,
such as 32, limits the overall sample quality. Then you will see that the latents now is 64 by 64.
How about the domain-specific encoder? So during the training process, you have this
domain-specific encoder. During the training, it goes through the cross-attention
to control how the image is going to be generated. After the training,
it becomes like this at the inference process. You have a domain-specific encoder,
which is the text encoder. And then you have the generation model. Then finally, you have the decoder,
such that this is following the paradigm that we mentioned at first. So with the text,
you fit the text into the model, and through the cross-attention, it was able to control the unit
to denoise from a Gaussian noise, so that it was able to produce the intermediate latents here,
and finally pass through the decoder, such that it was able to reconstruct the image
that aligns with the text. So what's the advantage of LDM? Obviously, it provides fast training,
right? Because it starts from a lower dimension. And the distribution of the latents and bedding
is closer to normal distribution. And another great advantage is that you can have tailored auto
encoders, because it can be applied to not just text, but also graphs, 3D data, etc.,
depends on the domain-specific encoder. So there are three core components in the LDM,
which we just covered. It's the variational auto encoder to encode and decode the latents.
Then we have a domain-specific encoder, which in the LDM literature, they use a bird tokenizer
or text encoder. And then they have a unit for the diffusion models, which has integrated the
rest block, and also the basic transformer block. Let's talk about the unit in the stable
diffusion, I mean in LDM. So they basically have a rest net, and then they also have a
attention block with the time stack embedding and also with the prompt embedding. So the time
embedding is used to support the denoising process, and the prompt embedding is used to control the
generation process. So how is it done? In the basic transformer block, they have to cross
attention module. So it goes from self-attention, cross-attention, and then speed forward.
So the self-attention was used to compute the spatial relation, while the cross-attention
allows the text control on image generation.
Then what is stable diffusion? Stable diffusion is actually a LDM trained by stability AI
for text-to-image purpose. They trained on a 256-800 GPUs on AWS for a total of 150K GPU hours.
They spent almost 600K USD on it. And stable diffusion is trained on a relatively huge dataset
called Lion 5B, which contains 5B clip filter image text pair.
So it also, for the domain-specific encoder, they also choose to use the clip text encoder
instead of the breadth tokenizer encoder in LDM literature. We will talk about why in the later
sections. For stable diffusion 2 and XL, so in stable diffusion 2, they retrained
stable diffusion from scratch on a filtered Lion 5B data. And they employed a new text encoder,
which they moved from clip to open clip. So then for SDXL, they retrained the auto encoder on a
larger batch size. And also they have a larger 3.5 times larger unit than the original one,
such that it was able to produce a larger resolution of output.
Then let's move to the next paper. Now let's talk about Image Gen. If you look at the Image Gen
architecture, you will see there is also following the paradigm that I first mentioned. You see there
is a text encoder, a generation model, and also a decoder. But this time, it was instead of the
latent model, it's using a cascaded model, which we will talk about in the following slides.
And then it also has the keyword called dynamic thresholding to improve the generated images.
So what's so special about this paper? Image Gen does not involve latent space,
and this is cascaded model. And then through dynamic thresholding, it produced high fidelity and
photorealism outputs. And then another important insight brought by this paper is that they find
that using a large text encoder improves the performance of the Image Generation.
Finally, they present drawbench, which is a challenging set of problems for evaluation.
For cascaded diffusion models, it's actually a paradigm that using pipelines of diffusion
models that can generate images of increasing resolution. In detail, they use the noise
conditioning augmentation, which is a technique that they find critical towards achieving
high sample fidelity. So you can see having this casc conditional bringing it into the
later diffusion models, it was able to perform super resolution while maintaining the sample
fidelity of the image. In Image Gen, they also employed a similar technique, but they found
that noise conditioning augmentation weakens the information from the low-waste models.
Instead, they introduced the text conditioning in the super resolution diffusion models
as the extra information, and they found that the performance is improved.
And other important techniques introduced by Image Gen is about dynamic thresholding.
So what it basically does is that it adjusts the pixel value of the samples at its sampling step
to be within a dynamic range compute over the statistics of the current samples,
such that with dynamic thresholding, you can see the image having more photobelastic and
having higher fidelity. So let's revisit classifier-free guidance. Instead of joining
training an additional classifier, get an implicit classifier by joining training a conditional
and unconditional diffusion model. This is like a very centric combination of the conditional
and unconditional score function, which they used to trade off for sample quality and sample diversity.
So basically, classifier-free guidance is a better method on diffusion models.
So at each sampling step, the output is clipped by the same bounds of the training data.
In the static thresholding, which is the standard practice, they clip it back to negative one-to-one.
This makes the image look saturated. But in the dynamic thresholding proposed by Image Gen,
it was thresholded to first a certain percentile absolute pixel value in the output at each
sampling step, and then divided by the as, which is basically normalizing it back to
negative one-to-one. These pre-framed pixels from saturation and the image would look more realistic.
So another important insight brought by Image Gen is that they find that powerful text encoders
are unnecessary, and having a better text encoder improved the performance of image generation
significantly compared to increasing the unit size. As you can see here, Image Gen was using
T5-XXL, which is like a very large text encoder, and they achieved the best clip score
while achieving the lowest FID score, which I will explain what is FID and clip score.
So just to revisit those basic Image Generation metrics, FID, also called
fresh heights in the inception distance, it measures the image fatality of a model.
So what it does is that it computes some kind of distance between the real and
generated data points distributions, and then the distance will be a range,
it will be a value range from zero to infinity, such that
such that a lot of samples is needed because you compare the distance
between two distributions so that in order to make it accurate, you need a lot of samples.
But I think, so in fact, more than 10K is enough to use, and also a very low
distance actually might represent something because it's only measuring the image fatality,
but it does not measure the diversity of the model. And then we have clip score, which
let's talk about clip first. Clip is constructive language image pre-training. It's a pre-trained
model, trained on 40, 400 million image pairs. And for clip score, it's just to measure the
image text alignment using the knowledge from clip. So what it basically does is that
clip has a text encoder, and clip also has an image encoder. So we employ the frozen text encoder
and the image encoder, and then we fit the text image pair into the encoder respectively
to get the text vector and the image vector such that by calculating the cosine similarity between
the text and image vector, a higher value indicates that the text is actually more relevant to the
image. And while the lower score indicates that the text might not be that relevant to the image.
But in fact, clip score only like the normal range of clip score is like 0.25 to 0.35.
So it's relatively hard to spot whether the text image text alignment is really doing well.
Then we will talk about .e2. So you see here, .e2 actually leverage the clip to perform the image
generation. More in detail, it used the clip latents to do it. So first, it learns a joint
representation space for text and images. And then at the generation process, it also follows
the paradigm of having an encoder and then a generation model and then a decoder.
So in detail, the text vector, I mean the text was fed into the text encoder,
such that the text vector was obtained. Then the text vector is passed into the diffusion model,
which in this case is actually, instead of unit, is more like a transformer decoder structure.
The diffusion model produced the clip image embeddings conditioned on the input caption.
Then it produced an intermediate latent, which we call the image vector, such that
it was passed to the decoder, which is a cascaded super resolution diffusion model
to produce the image condition based on the clip image embedding and text.
So what was the prior model that produced the clip image embedding condition on the input caption?
In the literature, they actually tried two different approaches, which the first approach
is autoregressive. They basically quantized the image embedding into a sequence of discrete codes
and predict them autoregressively, but they find that the diffusion prior actually performed
much better, such that they modeled a continuous image embedding by diffusion models,
which the diffusion model is a decoder only transformer conditioned on the caption.
So about the decoder, the decoder is also conditioned on the clip image embedding and text,
where the clip image embedding captures the high-level semantic meaning,
and the latents in the decoder model take care of the low-level details,
which shares a very similar idea from ImageGen, because their decoder is basically also a
cascaded super resolution diffusion model, which contains one base model to produce the image in
64 by 64, and then two super resolution models to upscale it up to 1000 by 1000.
So this next paper introduces PARTY, which stands for Pathways Autoregressive Text to Image Model.
Unlike the previous models that are mentioned, PARTY is not a diffusion model. PARTY represents a
research effort by Google done in parallel with ImageGen to explore two families of
generative models, which are autoregressive and diffusion models. The autoregressive approach
by PARTY hinges on the principle of using previous predictions as input to generate
subsequent ones, which is a method synonymous with the likes of language translation in NLP.
Specifically in PARTY, it treats text to image generation as a sequence-to-sequence modeling
problem, where image tokens are predicted in the series that corresponds to the sequence of
descriptive text tokens. The motivation for this research is to demonstrate the ability of
autoregressive models to generate high fidelity, photo-realistic images that reflect the content
density and complexity proposed by the textual description. Here are the main contributions
of this paper. First, it highlights a model state-of-the-art performance in autoregressive
modeling for text to image generation, setting a new benchmark in the field. Second, it marks the
consistency of improvements that PARTY has demonstrated across four different scales
of its architecture, from 350 million to 20 billion parameters, emphasizing the scalability of the
system. Third, this research introduces the PARTY PROMPS or P2 benchmark, a development that provides
a comprehensive framework for evaluating text to image models. Last, the paper also acknowledges
the importance of transparency in research by identifying the limitations of the PARTY model
and detailing these alongside observed error types. So PARTY is presented at the two-stage model,
which has an image tokenizer, detokenizer, alongside an autoregressive model. To desec
its structure, let's revisit the text to image schematic. A text to image model begins with the
text prompt, which is PARTY 2.8 text encoder that translates the input into a series of discrete
tokens. These tokens are then fed into the generation model, which interacts with an
input latent space. Then a model generates the intermediate latents. Finally, a latent decoder
interprets these intermediate representations, constructing the output as a detailed for
realistic image that corresponds to the original text prompt. So in the context of the training
processing PARTY, both images and text are converted into tokens. First, an image tokenizer
breaks down an input image into the corresponding image tokens, which are essentially the visual
syllables of the picture. These tokens are then processed by an autoregressive model,
particularly the decoder part of a transformer network. The output is a series of new image
tokens. Finally, an image detokenizer reassembles these tokens into coherent generated image that
visually represents the initial text prompt. So here's a schematic of the structure as
presented in the paper. It follows a two-stage structure. The image tokenizer and detokenizer
stage in green and the autoregressive stage in orange and blue for predicting the next image
token, giving text tokens and the previous tokens. Each of these components is essentially a
transformer. So PARTY is effectively a transformer-based sequence-to-sequence model.
Let's first talk about the image tokenizer and detokenizer stage in green.
This first stage involves a tokenizer that converts an image into a sequence of discrete
visual tokens during training, and training a detokenizer that reconstructs the image from
tokens during inference. However, there's a significant challenge, which is how to linearize
2D images into 1D sequences of patch representations. The problem lies in the complexity of images,
where even a standard 256x256 pixel image with three RGB color channels results in
196,000 rasterized values. Previous methods tackle this by learning quantized representations
of image patches. However, the PARTY model introduces a more refined solution. It uses a
tokenizer to learn patch embeddings, and the map sees embeddings to a visual code book.
Each entry in this code book corresponds to an indexable location in the latent space.
Therefore, it reduces the complexity of the image data. This is achieved using the vision
transformer or VIT structure combined with a vector quantized generative adversarial networks,
or VQGaN, combined as known as a VIT VQGaN. This approach not only streamlines the image data
into a manageable sequence, but also maintains the richness of the image's information.
Let's now talk about VIT VQGaN in detail. To understand VIT VQGaN, let's start with VQVAE.
A VAE typically learns a continuous latent representation, mapping input data into a
continuous distribution. On the other hand, the VQVAE, which stands for vector quantized
variational autoencoder, learns a discrete latent representation. This shift from continuous to
discrete encoding is crucial because it can help address issues like the posterior claps in VAEs,
where the model ignores the latent variables because the decoder is too capable.
Discrete codes, as shown in the encoder part of the slide,
represent the input image as a series of integers, which correspond to
specific vectors in a predefined embedding space. The decoder then translates these discrete codes
back into a reconstructed image. So this is a more detailed description of the VQVAE architecture.
The encoder, represented by a CNN, transforms the input image into a set of latent variables,
ZE for VF, X. These variables are then mapped to a discrete latent space using a code book
that consists of a list of k vectors, each with dimension D. This code book acts as a lookup
table, where each embedding vector EI is associated with an index from 1 to k.
The mapping from the continuous latent space to the discrete code book is performed by a
nearest neighbor search in the shared embedding space, which is the code book, and produces
the discrete latent variables Z. The posterior distribution QZ given X is defined as one hot
where it is equal to 1 if the embedding vector is the nearest neighbor of ZE of X and 0 if otherwise.
The input to the decoder ZQ of X is then the corresponding embedding vector EK,
where k is the index of the nearest neighbor embedding vector.
The training involves copying gradients from the decoder input ZQ of X
to the encoder output ZE of X. This allows for gradient flow despite the non-differentiability
of the discrete latent space. This loss function here that is used to train the network consists
of three parts. The first one is the reconstruction loss, which measures the difference between the
original image and the reconstructed image. The second one is the code book loss, which pulls
the code book vectors E towards the encoder outputs ZE of X, such that E is a better representation
of the encoder outputs, with SG here denoting the stop gradient operation that prevents the
gradients from flowing into the encoder outputs. The third one is the commitment loss, which penalizes
the encoder outputs ZE of X for deviating from the chosen code book embeddings E,
ensuring that the encoder commits to the code book assignment. Beta is a hyperparameter balancing
term. This loss function collectively ensures that the encoder representations are close to the
code book embeddings, while still allowing for efficient reconstruction. And it maintains the
integrity of the code book by having embeddings that are representative of the encoder outputs.
So next we'll look into VQGAN, which builds upon the VQVAE structure with several differences.
In training, VQVAE uses the L2 loss, which is a standard reconstruction loss focusing on pixel
wise accuracy. VQGAN, however, opts for perceptual loss, specifically the learned perceptual image
patch similarity metric. Perceptual loss differs from the L2 loss by measuring the perceptual
similarity between image patches. Additionally, VQGAN incorporates a discriminator, which is
trained to differentiate between real and reconstructed image patches. For sampling,
VQVAE learns a category called prior over the latent codes in the code book from the training
images, often employing an autoregressive model like pixel cnn to model the distribution of the
latent codes. VQGAN enhances this approach by predicting the next code book index using an
autoregressive transformer model trained with latent codes in training images, likely improving
the coherence and quality of the synthesized images by leveraging the transformer's ability to
capture long range dependencies. Here's the schematic of the VQGAN. The first stage involves
training the encoder e, the decoder g, and the discriminator d, using the vector quantize loss
and the GAN loss. The losses are similar to VQVAE, with this addition of the GAN loss and
modification from L2 to perceptual loss. In stage 2, VQGAN trains the transformer to
learn the relationships between code book entries using the cross entropy loss.
Next, VIT VQGAN further improves upon VQGAN with the following modifications.
First, it replaces both the cnn encoder and decoder with VITs. Then it also introduced
code book optimization to improve code book usage. So first, it uses factorized codes,
which applies to linear projection from encoder output to a low dimension latent space
for code index lookup. This decouples code embedding and lookup. Second, it applies L2
normalization on the encoder output latent variables ZE of X and code book latent variables E.
So the resulting Euclidean distance is effectively the cosine similarity of ZE of X and E.
Finally, in addition, it also modified the loss functions to be a combination of several losses
that are introduced in both VQVAE and VQGAN, including the perceptual loss and the Laplace loss.
So this is the schematic of the VIT VQGAN structure as presented in their paper.
The portion on the right here depicts a code book optimization part of VIT VQGAN
that includes a linear projection from a high dimensional space to a low dimensional space.
This is the overall schematic in the VIT VQGAN paper. It is similar to VQGAN, but only replacing
the CNNs with transformer encoder and decoders.
So now we're back to party stage one. This is the overall schematic of the image tokenizer and
detokenizer training with VIT VQGAN. In party, it also uses a super resolution up sampler to
upsample the output image to 1024 by 1024 from 256 by 256.
So now moving on to party stage two, which involves the autoregressive model,
and it's essentially an encoder-decoder transformer.
The encoder is designed to process textual input and convert it into text tokens,
utilizing a sentence piece model with a vocabulary size of 16,000 based on a sample text corpus.
It has a maximum token length capacity of 128. Meanwhile, the decoder focuses on predicting
the next image token in a sequence, taking as input the image tokens generated from stage
one's image tokenizer. The output from the decoder is structured into a fixed lens of 1024 image
tokens, which correspond to a grid of 32 by 32 tokens for a 256 by 256 image.
So four size variants of party were trained with 350 million, 750 million, 3 billion, and 20 billion
parameters. The encoder and decoder are based on standard transformers, and this configuration
prefers larger decoder for generating image tokens so that decoder has more layers.
So for further design considerations, the authors employed text encoder pre-training
with the intention to warm start the model, but found that it very marginally helps.
So it performs comparably to BERT on glue benchmark after pre-training, but it degrades
after full encoder decoder training. They have listed this difference and unification
of generic language understanding and visually grounded language understanding for future research.
Here is the training loss graph with and without text encoder pre-training. As seen,
the difference is small here. So for sampling, the authors apply classifier free guidance in
the context of autoregressive models, which is used to encourage alignment between generic
sample and text prompt. This is similar to the approach made in Make a Scene. They also use
re-ranking to batch sample images per text prompt, which is similar to the approach used in Dali,
and re-rank the outputs based on alignment score of image and text embedding of a
contrastive captioner's model. So here's a summary of PARTY's training pipeline.
Stage 1 focuses on training the VITB Cougar, which consists of a 32 million parameter encoder
to be used at the tokenizer, and a significantly larger 599 million parameter decoder as the
detokenizer. This stage also learns a set of 8192 image token classes, which are then used to
create a codebook. In addition to learning this visual vocabulary, the discriminator and a super
resolution upsampler are trained to enhance image quality. Once the encoder-decoder framework has
been pre-trained, the detokenizer is fine-tuned during the second stage training while keeping
the tokenizer and codebook fixed to ensure consistency in the learned representations.
The losses during this phase are the same as those used in VITB Cougar.
Moving on to stage 2, the training of the encoder-decoder autoregressive model. Here,
the text encoder is pre-trained. Then, the encoder-decoder are trained together using
Softmax cross-entropy loss, which ensures that the model learns to protect the next image token
effectively, based on the sequence of tokens generated by the tokenizer in stage 1.
During inference, a text prompt is passed through a text encoder, which converts the input into text
tokens. These tokens are then used by an autoregressive transformer decoder that generates the corresponding
image tokens, incorporating classifier-free guidance to enhance alignment between the
generated image and prompt. The image tokens are then subsequently converted from token space to
image space by the detokenization process using VITB Cougar's decoder. Following decokenization,
the generated image may be upsampled to achieve higher resolution. To ensure diversity and select
the best outcomes, the model generates 16 images per text prompt. These images are then subjected
to re-ranking, based on alignment score of image and text omitting of the co-cam model.
The datasets used for evaluations are the MS-Coco dataset and the Cocoa subset of the
localized narrative dataset. The localized narrative dataset has much more detailed prompts as seen
here. Then the authors also develop party prompts, which is a set of over 1600 prompts,
which each prompt associated with a broad category from 12 categories, for example,
animals, vehicles, world knowledge, and abstract, and a challenge dimension from 11 divisions.
For example, basic, quantity, words, or symbols.
Here are the FID score results on zero-shot and fine-tuned MS-Coco and localized narrative
Cocoa datasets when compared with other state-of-the-art text-to-image models at the time,
as well as the retrieval baseline. The retrieval baseline simply retrieves images from the training
dataset based on an alignment score between the text prompt embedding and the image embeddings.
As seen, party outperforms other state-of-the-art models in terms of both zero-shot and fine-tuned FID
scores. Here are some results based on human evaluations on the MS-Coco dataset when compared
with the XMCGAN model and the retrieval baseline, showing that party outperforms XMCGAN in terms of
image realism and image text match, and outperforming the retrieval baseline based on image text match.
On the new party prompts, results show that the larger 20 billion party model outperforms
the 3 billion model as well as the retrieval baseline.
The next paper is Pixar Alpha, fast training of diffusion transformer for photo-realistic text-to-image
synthesis. This paper aims to harness the capabilities of the diffusion transformer
to train a text-to-image model comparable to the state-of-the-art models.
The method is motivated by designing a training strategy to independently optimize
three critical components, pixel dependency, text-image alignment, and image aesthetic quality.
Pixar Alpha also tries to support high-resolution image synthesis up to 1024 pixels,
achieving this with notably reduced training costs and improved efficiency.
The core contributions of the paper are as follows. Firstly, the model's training time
is remarkably short, requiring only 10.8% of the time needed for a stable diffusion version 1.5,
while also using less than 1.25% of its training data.
Second, it introduces this three-stage training strategy which enhances the process by concentrating
on model initialization followed by a targeted pre-training and a fine-tuning stage, with each
stage designed to streamline specific subtasks. Third, the introduction of cross-attention modules
within the diffusion transformer DIT architecture improves text-condition injection while also
refining the entire computation process, particularly in the computation-intensive
class-condition branch. And finally, it leverages a large vision language model,
a lava, to auto-label dense pseudo-captions.
The first stage of the training strategy is to learn pixel dependency.
This stage is dedicated to understanding the pixel distribution of natural images without
the interference of text prompts, essentially teaching the model to the inherent structure
and coherence found within the visual data. It does this by employing a class-condition
diffusion transformer, DIT Excel 2, with 28 transformer blocks that have been pre-trained
on the ImageNet dataset. This methodology allows Pixar Alpha to capture the essence of
visual information. The model is trained on 1 million images over 300,000 training steps.
So this paper leverages the diffusion transformer architecture,
which pivots an architectural change from the traditional unit backbone of latent diffusion
models to a transformer-based model. The diffusion transformer operates first by converting noise
through linear layers and reshaping, followed by normalization and processing through multiple
DIT blocks. These blocks are structured with multi-head self-attention and point-wise feed-forward
layers interspersed with scaling and normalization. The conditional inputs such as the diffusion
time steps and class labels are incorporated into the transformer via AMLP. The adaptation of the
VIT blocks or vision transformer blocks equipped with the adaptive layer norm layers
ensures flexible normalization. So furthermore, the integration of Pixar Alpha with this
architecture utilizes a 250-60 frequency embedding followed by a two-layer MLP.
So Stage 2 is centered on enhancing text image alignment learning. The shift from pre-trained
class-guided image generation to this text-to-image generation calls for accurate alignment between
detailed text descriptions and generated images. So a significant challenge in this stage arises
from the text captions in the datasets, which often lack informative content. Are misaligned
with their corresponding images or present a long-tailed distribution that makes learning from
them difficult? So to counter these issues, Pixar Alpha implements a solution that involves
creating highly informative text captions with the help of Lava, a large vision language model.
By leveraging Lava in auto-labeling pipeline, Pixar Alpha aims to improve the informativeness
of the text data, so thereby enhancing the training efficiency and alignment accuracy.
So here are some examples of raw captions from the Lyon dataset and Lava refined captions.
As seen, refinements can deal with problems like text image misalignment, deficient descriptions,
and infrequent vocabulary, causing this long-tailed characteristic.
So here is the detailed dataset refinement process. So using Lava, the dataset undergoes this
auto-labeling process with prompt that encourage informative descriptions. So particularly the
prompt asks it to describe this image and its style in a very detailed manner. So SAM is used
instead of Lyon, since the segment anything dataset tends to lead to a more robust vocabulary
demonstrated to a vocabulary analysis. So this analysis shows that Lava refined SAM and Lyon
datasets increase in the number of total nouns and the ratio of valid distinct noun to total
distinct noun. So valid distinct noun means nouns that occur more frequently. And SAM Lava is able
to outperform Lyon Lava, so that's why it is used. In this stage, 10 million SAM captions are refined.
So Stage 3 of the Pixar Lava training focuses on generating high-resolution images with a refined
of set of quality. So this stage leverages fine-tuning on data with superior quality,
specifically combining a 4 million image dataset from JourneyDB and a 10 million internal image dataset.
The training in this stage benefits from the foundational work established in the previous
stages, which results in a faster convergence. So the table shows that there are three scales
of resolution used for training in this stage. And as the resolution increases from 256x256
to 1024x1024, fewer training steps are needed in this stage and with a decrease in batch size.
And this reflects an optimization of the learning process due to the high quality of the input data
and the cumulative knowledge from earlier training steps. So here are some design considerations
presented in this paper. So it uses the DIT XL2 as the base architecture and a 4.3 billion
Flan T5 as the text encoder for conditional feature extraction and also a pre-train and
frozen VAE encoder from latent diffusion model for latent feature extraction.
And here within the DIT block, multi-hat cross-attention is used to facilitate interactions
between the model and text embeddings extracted from the language model.
So the authors of Pixar and Alpha modified the original adaptive layer norm layers in the
diffusion transformer to make it more efficient. They found that linear projections in the adaptive
layer norm layer module of the DIT account for substantial proportion, which is 27% of the
parameters. And this large number of parameters is not useful since the class condition is not
employed in text to image generation model. So they proposed the adaptive layer norm single
where all in blocks share the same parameters for time conditions. Global MLP with layer-wise
embeddings are used instead of layer-specific MLPs. So to adapt to this new structure,
layer-specific trainable embeddings are introduced to adaptively adjust the shifts and scales
in different blocks without the class condition. So this preserves the compatibility with
when initialized to yield the same scales and shifts at the pre-trained diffusion transformer.
So here are some experimental results on the MsCoCo dataset comparing the FID scores with
other state-of-the-art models. Although it doesn't achieve the lowest FID score,
it does have the lowest number of parameters, training images, as well as number of GPU days.
So here are some results on the T2ICOM bench, a benchmark for assessing alignment
between text conditions and generated images. And this shows that Pixar Alpha
is very competitive in the categories of attribute binding and object relationship,
as well as complexity. So the authors also conducted experiments on human evaluations
based on generated images from 300 prompts. For this, 50 participants ranked models based on
perceptual quality and text image alignment. As seen, the results show that Pixar Alpha
outperforms other models in terms of both quality and alignment.
Before moving to the last paper, we want to think about what makes a good generation model.
So as we see here, the diffusion models cannot do fast sampling.
Although it provides a good model coverage and diversity and produce high quality
high fatality on the image, we wonder, are there any state-of-the-art methods that
have diffusion models with faster sampling? This brings us to the final paper that we are
presenting today, which is SDXL Turbo. It showcases a technique called ADD,
which is an Adverse Serial Diffusion Distillation, a new distillation technique for text-to-image
models. And there are some special properties of SDXL Turbo that the classifier-free guidance
were not used here. And the main highlights of the paper is that it can do a single-step
image generation, which is extremely fast. It can be even done in real-time, such that
originally SDXL, it has to do like 50 steps, but in SDXL Turbo, you basically do it in one step.
So intuitively, it's actually combining the superior sample quality from diffusion models,
but also the inherent speed of GANs. So let's delve into this paper.
But first, let's revisit the Adverse Serial Models, the Generative Adverse Serial Networks, GANs.
It has a generator which optimizes to synthesize samples that capture the distribution of training
data. Then we also have a discriminator which optimizes to classify the real and fake data.
So during the training process, a generator will generate a bunch of fake images,
while the training set, the actual training data, and the fake data are both fed to the
discriminator so that the discriminator has to tell whether which one is fake or real.
The both generators and discriminators are trained simultaneously in the case that both
have to get better in each epoch during the training just to make sure that they are in
fair fights so that they can learn from each other. The objective is to learn at a point
that discriminator was unable to tell whether the generator's fake image is real or fake.
So at that period of time, it means the generator has been successful chained,
and after that, the discriminator can be dumped into a garbage bin and we only care about the
generator. In SDXL Turbo, it actually has a student-teacher model so it's like a
distillation process where the student is having like a relatively short time step
while the teacher model is using a long time step for scheduling.
So what is that in the training process is that first you have the latent
which is basically compute by the forward diffusion process by adding
noise progressively on it, then you get the XS here, then it got passed into the generator
which is the student model. We're going to train this and it will generate an image
that looks to be what we wanted here. Then it got fed into the discriminator to tell whether it's
fake or not. This is very similar to the GAN methodology but also at the same time
the synthesized output was added noise progressively again to fed into a teacher model
which is a frozen, which is a freezing diffusion model to try to generate again.
But this time it doesn't compute the gradient and then it computes the distillation laws
to see which is like some kind of distant metric between the generated image from generator
and also the generated image from the teacher diffusion model.
So that it penalized the the gradients in the student model such that it was able to learn
the teacher, I mean the student was able to learn how to become more like the teacher model.
In that case, it was expected the student could eventually perform better than teacher
while also fooling the discriminator so that the discriminator was not able to tell
it's true or fake. That means the student has been successfully become a good synthesizer.
And then a generation process, this becomes like a one pass model, not necessary one pass but
it can inference at a very short time step such that you just simply fit a noise
into it and then with some kind of tech conditioning you can generate it with
you can generate it with very low time step such that it was able to compute in real time.
So in detail, the generator was used in network like in unit again,
a pixel space unit as a generator. While the discriminator is a vision transformer with
the dyno objective and the teacher model, the paper used SDXL and also SDs 2.1 as a teacher model.
For the training objective, they employ the traditional gain loss which is the adversarial
loss and then they use the hinge loss with the gradient penalty which divides from the GP gain
paper. And for the distillation loss, it's simply a weighted L2 loss which the CT is
the alpha t according to the time step defined by them.
So in summary, we cover six pivotal texture image models in this presentation including
latent division model which is the first work to use the latent like the compressed latent
and also the cross-attention. Then we have image gen paper which is a cascaded division model
to do text to image generation. Then next we have Thor E2 which utilizes the clip embeddings
and the latents to synthesize high-quality image. Then we have party, a transformer-based
auto-regressive model and then we have pixel alpha which is a diffusion transformer.
Finally, we have an SDXL turbo which utilized the adversarial distillation from SDXL.
We also did cover some common metrics for t2i I mean text-to-image models including
fasciitis inception distance which measures the image fidelity and also clip score to measure
the image text alignment. In fact, there are more t2i models to explore so we can see here there are
more than six latitudes that we just covered and we hope people who listen to our presentation
will rise more interest into this area. Thank you.