Hello, and then it's kind of along with me, it's Jerry. We will be talking about large
language models in lecture 9 of CEF 886 recent analysis on foundation model. What is large
language model? Now, in order to cover our agenda for today, we will focus on several
different types of large language models in terms of architecture. We will be focusing
on DPT3, T5, Codex, Lama2, and so on. We also focus on supervised learning and compare them
to other types of learning. You're free to stop aside any time and ask questions. We
do have a set of questions at the end of this session for that discussion.
Now, for large models, we are focusing on deep learning, which is really natural language
pressing tasks. Large language models are computational models that have the capacity,
capability to understand and generate human models. Large language models
have the transmittive ability to predict the likelihood of work sequences or during a text
based on a given input. Example of how this has been done in the past, in Ngram models,
FKM will probably teach that actually based on traditional text, we try to estimate the right
word probability. They are usually trained on massive amount of public-care legal data.
Large language models have the transmittability to predict likelihood of work sequences or during
a text based on a given input. They are advanced programming models with multi-parameter
and exceptional learning capabilities. Separation model in transformers serves as a fundamental
building block for large language model tasks. Transmortem has a reference to visualize the
field of finality with the ability to handle sequential data efficiently, align for parallelization
and capturing language, penises, and text. One key feature of fellow learners is in-contact
learning, which we will talk about later. Now, we want to do a comparison of large
language models in comparison to deep learning on machine learning and deep learning. With
large language models, usually the training data are very large in the orders of
terabytes, basically. You don't have to directly identify any of the features or any of the variables,
it does automatically. And the models tend to be very complex. They are
complex because all they're dealing with are really complex problems. Now, one of the problems
they have, though, is that they are not easy to interpret. It is harder to interpret the
conclusions that they have. This is the concept with large language models, and we'll talk about
that later. They also have very high platform and they require a massive amount of compute power in
order to run. Really, we're talking another petafloat per second per day here, and they do require
a lot of money in order to do that. Now, natural language present tasks tend to be
in three major areas, which is understanding reasoning and then generation of new materials.
On understanding the four major areas there, we're looking at sentiment analysis,
this is where it takes a paragraph or a body of text and then interprets it to determine
the emotional condition. So, this was usually binary or a triple. It could be, oh, yeah,
this is a prophecy half. And it meant on this or negative sentiment or neutral.
They also can handle text classification. So, it's similar to sentiment analysis, but then
it requires a definite classification of that text. And one of the things it can also do is
natural language inference, which is the termination of given, whether it give or protest this
follow-up based on the given premise of the text in which they're dealing with.
Yes, of course, they might be understanding. And then in terms of reasoning, this is really where
the model must be able to comprehend any provided information that which
utilize reasoning to deduce answer where next year at least I have checked.
Then they can generate text. So, they can do summarization. You know, they can take a whole
concise, they can generate a concise abstract from a large body of text and they can do question
answering. So, the first model we'll talk about here is P5. P5 stands for text-to-text transfer
transformer. So, it can perform tasks such as translation, question answering, classification,
signature score or summarization. Now, it has a unified approach to problems. It basically
creates everything as text and then outputs as text as well. What is thought that allows
how to use the researcher of P5 to use the same model, the same post-function,
hop-up parameters, layers, SSTURA, across a diverse set of tasks. So, they treat every text
problem on the text and they use what they talk about, what are the SSTURA representation,
which is usually numbers. And the input is a common core project which produces about
really 20 terabytes of text extra from web edges each month. They clean up that in order to make
its process usable. The model itself is first portrayed on the data rich task before being
fact-tuned or in the downstream task. And the building block is safe attention. So, for example,
if you look at what we have in diagram here, the first top sentence on the left side has a prefix
of translating this to German, that is good. And it goes through the transformer and the
correct German response comma, that is good. Now, let's talk about the architecture of this T5.
So, confirmation fair was first introduced in the terminal, 37 people called at the
show it's all in it. That was by one analyst. It was a groundbreaking architecture that used
attention to add context to data. The encoding, in this case, has an encoding component
and a decoding component. So, the encoding component accepts input sequence and a map
after a continuous repetition that holds all the learning functions about the input.
And then the decoding component then takes the continuity of the token and then sequentially
generates output while also being fed its previous output. So, the encoding component accepts all
vectors in the input sequence at the same time, but for function encoding so that it knows the
order of input within the sequence of the input. And then it does that by adding extra vector to
each input by embedding it within the vector. And then for every odd input within the sequence,
it added vector created by cosine function and for every even, it adds a vector created by sine
function. Now, there is a linear layer just as you will see in the diagram on the bottom right.
This in the layer is a neural network that provides the vector, that projects the vector
produced by decoding component onto a much larger vector called a logic vector. Now,
the logic vector size is determined by a number of unique words in the model's vocabulary.
So, the job of the softbox layer, which is the last one before the output on the bottom right,
is to convert the logic score into probability. So, the word
or this input sequence with the output sequence with the highest probability in
the model vocabulary is chosen and then it's predicted as output during this time step.
The output is then fed back to the decoding component to help inform or provide context
to each prediction for the next layer. This is known as auto regression. Know that as input
flow from one encoder to the next, it also puts the next encoder in the stack. It's
simply happening with the stack of decoders. Now, let's go into details of the encoding and
decoding layer. So, within the encoder layer, you have what we call the safe attention. This
mechanism enables what you interact with each other, which is a part of that so that they can
figure out which other words they should pay more attention to. The encoder decoder attention
layer, which is within the decoding component, the goal of that layer is to help
the model align the words in the input sequence with the words in the output sequence.
And then the linear layer, which is the neural network layer, it's a neural network. But
in that project, the vector produced by the decoding component into a much larger
vector called a logic. And then the size of the logic, of course, as mentioned earlier,
is something but not a unique word in a word or vocabulary. The development of the
top model is to provide logistic probabilities. And that's really what happens within the
data form model. Now, you've seen this before, this is a standard transformer model architecture,
which we've had in earlier lectures. So, I won't really go into individual details of how this
works. Now, it's, as we mentioned, consists of both an encoder, it's because an encoder
decoder architecture, it's the encoder and encoder are really similar in size. They each
consist of 12 blocks each. And then each block comprises the safe attention, the optional encoder
decoder attention and a feed forward network. And that's, this is a standard transformer
architecture. Now, within the T5 transformer, attention is handled really in a unique way.
So, the model process, each input in a input sequence, each token input sequence, and they
assign different attentional scores to other tokens in the safe sequence. Now, this calls
determining patterns of each token's contribution to the model's understanding of the context.
And so, within that encoder decoder attention, so let's talk about this. So, what happens that
the queries come from a previous decoder layer and then the memory and keys come from the output
of the encoder. And it allows every question encoder to attach all the questions in the
input sequence. Now, that helps aligns the world in the input sequence with the words in the
input sequence. And we also have the encoder also contains safe attention. And the other part,
which is the marked safe attention in the decoder. There could be variance in the T5 architecture.
So, they are slightly three different variants that people talked about,
don't you know people that wish this was based upon? Now, the fact is really that
this distinguishing factor really is, it must be used by different attention mechanism in the mode.
Now, if you look at this, we have dark colors and then light colors, right? So,
the different color indicates the different performance. Dark, gray lines correspond to the
fully visible masking and then the light gray lines correspond to casual masking. So, we used the
dot that you can see in that diagram to denote a special end of sequence token that represent
the end of the prediction. The input and output are represented as x and y respectively. On the left
side, which is the first model we have on the left side, you have just the standard encoder,
decoder architecture, then you see it's usually a fully visible masking encoder and then the encoder,
decoder characterization with careful markings in the decoder, which is a light gray line.
In the middle, we have a language model consisting of a single transformer layer stack
and that is spread the concatenation of the input and target crossing using a car roll,
a causal mask throughout. On the right side, you have a prefix language model. This has
a prefix language model corresponding to a line with visible masking over the input.
So, the attention, this has the different attention mask patterns that you can have. The
attention mask pattern is a crucial component in large language models itself as a mechanism
to control which part of the input sequence the model should pay attention to during the training
or inference process. So, there may be four types of attention masks. You have what we call
full attention. So, in some models, every token is allocated to every other token input.
This is known as full attention and is often used in smaller models. If you have a scale
dot product attention to make completion more efficient, large models typically use scale
dot attention, scale dot product attention. This means that the tokens only attend to other
tokens within a certain distance and that distance is determined by a window size fixed
context length and you have what we call the masked attention. In this case, the model should
not tend to put your tokens to avoid the time leakage during training and a triangular attention
mask is used. This marking shows that each token can only attend to previous tokens in the sequence
and then you can have the case of attention heads. So, large language models like GPT 3.5,
employee multi-potential head, each head lands different attention patterns along the model
to capture various information within the data. I now have a couple of different aspects like
thinker, semantics, or sentiment. So, in this diagram that we showed here, the dark cell
at row i and column j, in the case of the second semicolon, it's allowed to attend
to input element j at time step i. So, for example, it has to input x1 at y1.
Now, looking at the performance of the various different models, you can see here that the
encoder, the encoder architecture, it's referred to the previous architecture
variants I would describe. P refers to the number of parameters in the 12-layer
base transformer stack and M refers to the complete power, the flux required
to process a sequence of using the encoder-decoder model. So, we evaluate each actor
variant using a denoicing objective and then autoregressive, which is commonly used
between objects. We consider the encoder-decoder texture with denoicing. Denoicing helps reduce
the randomness and corresponding input data. How is it there for fun? Now, when we see noise here,
we refer to, noise refers to random or unpredictable fluxion data that disrupts the ability
to identify type of path transmission. So, that when you have to watch noise in the system,
it results in reduced accuracy and then relapses of the motor's protection or output.
Now, in terms of the data that T5 uses, it uses what we call closer, clean, crawl, couples,
which I mentioned much earlier at the beginning of this. It's really a set of
friendship by text data that's extra for the web. And it's number to clean up. It uses
some simple heuristic operator to remove boiler text places, to duplicate, agree, retain line.
Each line must continue at least five words. And it discusses any page that's
right as three sentences and then removes any page also that may contain any item from the
list of dirty, not your obscene or the worst bad word. And of course, it also removes a
duplicating data. Now, what are these type of tasks that T5 does in downstream form? I think
they don't really serve. It can be used to measure general language and abilities. You can
check for sentences like subject judgment, different assessment analysis with it.
You can use it to paraphrase sentence or find some narrative between them.
You could also find natural language inferences to figure out what is happening within the
particular sentence. And then you can do sentence completion or core reference resolution or what
says at the end of the question. It's also got to help answer the question.
In order to train the model, we basically follow this very simple text. It goes ahead and
pretend using a pretend step of 2 to power 19 or 524,000 of variety of steps. And
it has a linear rate of 0.01 for the first 10 to power 4 or 10,000 steps. And then it reduces
the linear rate of 0.01 when it's pointing it. One of the things that T5 can do is also
progress objectives. It can figure out, it's sort of a mechanism where the model can gain
general purpose knowledge to apply to downstream steps. You can just see a sequence of token ideas
corresponding to tokenized text from only build text data, and then it can use this
token sequence to process, to produce both a corrector input sequence and a corresponding
output. And then it uses the sentence piece to encode the text for the token. So it's actually
quite good in doing that. And similar to the way the products are on supervised objective,
the prerate data set is a crucial component of transfer learning pipeline. And then on like
objectives of 8Mark, new pre-training data that I usually not should ask because I'm sure they are
so, but these four, these T5 uses high level approaches where it does
bust out and dish out and log in the model. It then uses different corruption strategies.
And it's trying to figure out what corruption sequence of data is. Now for performances,
these are performance resulting from pre-training on different data sets. So the first
public events are based on a new C4 database. Data set and the best performance comes from real
news like data set, but it was not the largest. Now this is a surprise because we
expect that the larger data would give best performance, but that's not the case.
The hypothesis is that the real news data is a lot more random
and it's a lot more reflective of real life. So in pre-training loss, we find out that really the
number of steps that it takes, if you look at what we have diagram here, we're having like
100 steps or 300, and the bigger number of steps, the less the training loss,
it's basically gets better. So the pre-training loss for C4 data set was as well as
a four-attachable trope data version. The size of the state of the person above
to keep in each data set. The first one, and that corresponds to the data set between 64 and 4000
times of 4k, and then using a smaller data set because it's a smaller training loss. So
the bigger data set, then the higher the data loss that you get.
G5 scaling. So G5 scaling refers to the
general expense at the cost in order to really maintain, to run a model. They are large,
they are very expensive, and generally, when you increase the compute power, you get better
performance. So with neural networks, it's usually the case that the bigger your power,
the more computing you have, the better. If you looked at Microsoft, I invested about $13
billion in OpenAI because of the sensitivity, a large portion of that fund was really for cloud
compute power instead of direct cash injection. So some reflection on G5. It's text-to-text.
It's really straightforward and high. It does what it does, and it's really good at it. It has
a user, the original Ecuador decoder, personal architecture, which works really well.
It uses twice as many parameters as Ecuador on the model like that, and it can do also
a supervised objective. So let's talk about in-contact learning. Now, the way large-language
model learns is they can take a new task from a small set of example that's presented within
the context, and the idea really is that they can learn from analogy. So if you're looking to have
very large data set for every task possible, it's not really applicable because it's not practical.
You can't have all of that. So what you need to have is a way for the model to learn
from what it is doing so it knows how to improve on it. And the way it wants to do that is really
to be able to figure out if there's serious correlation in the training data so it can
do that. Now, for humans, we don't really require large data set to learn most tasks. So
we can actually learn. And the idea really in meta-linear or zero-share transfer is to allow
the model to develop a set of broad skillset of particular abilities so that it can figure out
things at a good time. So if we take an example of some of the items that we in meta-learning,
basically we have the model learning via stochastic gradient descent where it's able to
develop on survival pre-training. It's able to develop a broad skills and for our permission
using this ability as interest time to address the data of a new task. So it's really, so if you
look at this on a diagram, the learning goes from left to right and then that's more or less an
aftereffect so you can have different effort coverage. With it in a loop, if we know how to do,
if we show you the example of 5 plus 80 plus 13, 7 plus 3 plus 9, if you have to figure out
a 1 plus 0 equals to 1, or a 3 plus 4 equals to 7, that is the in-context learning that we're
referring to here. There are different languages that are better at in-context learning. So
for example, one task that has been used is to figure out how to remove random symbols from a
word and then you can have large models making really effective use of that in-context information.
If we look at this place actually, we're talking about GA3 and it has like the large
ones that have 1.5 billion parameters require just a few shots. In fact, the few shots and the no prompt
tend to even work well, even though you don't have, the few shot is always slightly better than
the one shot approach that you have here. And if you go on the no prompt, it will eventually match
as none of the examples brought, eventually match the few shots as well. So let's talk about
GP3, which is a last set of models that I want to talk about. We know that even though GP3 is
based on transformer architecture, it's really a decoder only neural network. It does have embedding
really in order to be able to take input. It has and pass all of it on to the network, but it does
not have an encoder in the traditional encoder decoder transformer layer. So the goal really
for GP3 is to be able to predict the next test, given all previous tests. And it uses a very,
it's a very large autoregressive language. It can be used for a few short predictions. So you only
need to claim the few set of data and it knows exactly what to do. So if you look at the diagram
that we have here, it has a very similar to what we showed for T5. The only difference is that
it doesn't have an encoder. So if you take a transformer block and then you take the transformer
block, which is blown up for down the right, you see that it has the normalization layer that comes
with the multiple attention head and then it goes through the model that you have, which is really
the metrics, but the masking, the soft dropbox, it goes into the linear layer and then
does everything in tunnel layer and then goes out and passes the other layer. So it's,
this is the structure of what we have there. Now in terms of the GP3 training layer,
we can see here that it does, it uses, quite to me, you can have zero short, one short,
or even a few short, but the different layer, the GP3 that uses traditional,
uses traditional, fine tuning, which is not, which is not to use normally for GP3. It basically,
it's, the model itself is trained by repeated gradient of this using a large
data, and that's what it uses to control it.
The training data set is similar, it's based on the common crawl, which is up to
one terabyte of what is claimed and if it's used, it's an effective thing. So the training that I
tend to be, GP3 has several different training that can be small, can be large, medium,
it can be just the, the, the best known one, which is the GP3, what's on the five billion
parameters there. So for the columns there, you see the number parameter, number of layer,
the dimension of the model, which shows how many neurons you have in that particular layer,
and then the number of heads, and then the dimension of the heads there, and the batch size,
which is how was it started to talk of the data processing.
And I noticed that all the models here were trained for a total of 200 billion token.
And in terms of compute consumption, we can see here that the, the scaling law
shows that training for much larger models, you only use more than those for fewer tokens in
terms of CPU. So even though GP3 is almost three times larger, or 10 times larger than
Roberta, I'll show you in the diagram, both models took roughly 58 pF per day,
pF per second per day of computing during training.
Even though GP3 is bigger, it has, it is three, it has three billion parameters compared to
three 155 million for Roberta. So the last thing I want to talk about here is really the limitations
that we have for GP3. GP3, as wonderful as it is, it still has no limitations. It's
it's very well what it does, it has text synthesis, the quality of the text is high,
but sometimes if it is self, it does that
because it doesn't really have an understanding of, from a human point of view of the text of
this process. And so sometimes repeat itself semantically at a document level. It also can
sometimes lose coherence over sufficiently large, long passages. And in some cases it can
contradict itself. So occasionally it can contain non-sequital synthesis or paragraph.
For example, the sky blue and the sun is shining, the kid did not drink his milk.
Those sentences have nothing to do with digital. The first sentence sky blue and the sun is shining,
that's good, but the kid did not drink his milk has nothing to do with the first sentence.
It also has a problem lack of interpretability. That is not a problem that is unique,
this is a problem that is common to all large language models.
That's because it's not easily understood or not kind of interpreted. Now it may not work
by the novel input because it's based, it's resolved on what has been injected into it.
It retains biases of data that has been traded on. And that's actually quite important to know.
One of the major concerns of model is that they can transfer the
bias as in real world onto the large language model. And when we start trusting large
language models without questioning, we are making that bias a prejudice and
stereotyping into the large language model. And that is a special concern from a societal
perspective. So we need to be careful when relying, if I rely too much on GP3,
without thinking, as work continues to improve on GPT and large language models generally,
my belief is that some of these issues may no longer be there in the future.
They would result, people would find out how to resolve those problems.
You know, it's, some of the problems really is due to poor sample efficiency during pre-training.
If you don't have representative data, then there's no guarantee that you're going to have
representative model that can serve the society equally well. And I've talked about data perpetuate
and amplified symbiosis. Now there's another problem which, still there, which is multilingual,
is a majority of language model researchers are done in English. So that's where most of the body
of images of text and the purpose of the body of knowledge is. Now what I mean is that when we
try to process non-English languages, we don't have enough support and enough
data to be a good work of it. Thank you. I'll now hand over to Jerry to continue. Thank you.
VPT-3 was found to be able to generate programs, which was surprising because it was never
explicitly trained on code. However, when evaluated on the human eval benchmark,
which will be discussed later, it had a pass rate close to zero. And this begs the question,
is there, can there be language models that specializes in generating programs?
And to this end, there has been recently lots of progress in generating programs from language
models. And one such model is called CodeX, which is a specialized GPT model trained on code.
Now, there are many ways to evaluate the performance of generative models. And
usually the metric to evaluate this is called match-based metrics, which compares output
to a reference solution. However, this may not be viable for models that generate code,
because there may be too many different possible output programs that are functionally equivalent
to the reference solution for this metric to account for. So for example, functionally
equivalent code may use different methods to solve the problem. So for example, for sorting
algorithms, there are many different ways to implement one. For example, by using
deep sort, merge sort, quick sort, etc., they all achieve the same thing, but their code is
completely different. So their match-based metrics would be low, even though they should be very high.
And indeed, it was found that one such match-based metric called the blue score was found to be
unreliable. And so an alternative method is to use functional correctness instead,
which runs the output code on test cases to measure performance. And it is preferable
because it's similar to how humans judge code. So for example, code is usually evaluated based
on test cases passed instead of comparing to solution code in, for example, coding contests
or coding assignments in CS courses, for example.
And one way to evaluate functional correctness is to use the pass at K metric,
which calculates the fraction of problems such that at least one of K sample codes generated
passed all test cases for that problem. And this can be formulated as pass at K equals one minus,
and then brackets one minus pass at one to the power of K, where one minus pass at one is the
probability of an output code failing at least one test case. And this can be interpreted as the
result of evaluating the best of K samples. Now directly calculating the pass at K results
in a high variance. So instead N sample codes are generated, which is greater than or equal to K.
And then the number of past codes C is counted. And the estimator one minus and minus C choose
K divided by N choose K is calculating is calculated for each problem and averaged. Now this estimator
can be interpreted as one minus the total number of ways to choose K failed codes,
and divided by the total number of ways to choose K codes. And
this gives intuition that that estimator is unbiased. However, one can prove this rigorously
by considering that C is distributed by the binomial distribution with N trials and probability
pass at one. And then one can take the expectation over C and expand it to a sum and solve to get the
formula shown on the above. Now, even though that estimator is unbiased,
just directly plugging in the empirical estimate of pass at one into the formula for pass at K
would lead to a biased estimator, particularly it under estimates pass at K, because distributions
are skewed more to the right when taken and exponent greater than one. But its mode is
still to the power of K, so its mean would be greater than that. So a set of 164 problems
called human eval was created, each containing a function signature, doc string, body, and average
of 7.7 unit tests. And these were handwritten to avoid training on potential solutions found in
the training data set. Now, for the training, it involves fine tune GPT models up to 12 billion
parameters on code and is trained on a 159 gigabyte data set of unique Python files on GitHub.
And the learning rate was used was the same as the corresponding GPT model with a 175 step
linear wound up and cosine learning decay and trained on a total of 100 billion tokens with the
atom opt an optimizer with weight decay. And for the results, it was shown that the cross entropy
test loss on a held out validation set fowers a smooth power law. And when only one sample can be
evaluated, it was found that compared to randomly choosing a sample to evaluate, it's better to
choose the one with the highest mean log probability as it performs better. But choosing the one with
the highest sum log probability would perform slightly worse than random choosing. And the plot
on the left shows the pass at K versus K and the temperature. And it was found that the sampling
temperature that maximizes pass at K increases with the number of samples K. And this makes
sense because pass at K only cares about if one sample passes and sampling temperature controls
randomness when sampling, which in the context of generative models, it generates the next
token from a distribution of softmax of the logits, which are the unnormalized scores of tokens
divided by the temperature. So in this case, the highest pass at K for the best temperature
for pass at one is 0.2 and the highest for pass at 100 is 0.8. And these were used in the plot on
the right to plot the pass rate versus the model size as shown in the plot to the right.
Now Codex was compared to other models, including GPT models and the largest free model from
tab 9. And this was done by evaluating all of them on human eval with temperatures of 0.2,
0.4, or 0.8. And then the one with the best score was chosen from these three temperatures.
And then it was found that only GPT-Neal and GPT-J were the only GPT models that had pass rates
that are not close to zero. And these models are similar to Codex and trained on the pile
data set, which has 8% GitHub code. And it was found that as shown in the table to the left,
Codex 300M L performs GPT-J 6B, even though it has 20 times less parameters.
Now there may be code unrelated to translating natural language to code in the data set.
For example, there may be scripts or class implementations and so on. And these may
lower their performance. And so a set of training problems from relevant code was obtained from
two sources, competitive programming websites and repositories with continuous integration.
And these were used to do supervised fine tuning on Codex to create a version called CodexS,
which has shown to have improved performance. And it was found to prefer slightly higher
sampling temperatures than Codex, at least for a K greater than one, possibly due to a narrow
narrower distribution. And also it was found to outperform Codex by 6.5% on pass at one and
15.1% on pass at 100. And this was shown in the plot on the left. Now for the plot on the right,
it was found that the CodexS also significantly outperforms Codex,
when only a single sample can be evaluated. And the random sample is chosen, or when a mean
log is chosen, and also the theoretical pass rates, which is shown in the blue vines.
And so far we have discussed how CodexX, Codex generates code from doc strings.
But what about the other way around? And to this end, CodexD was created, and it's a version of
CodexX that generates doc strings from code. And each training problem contains the function
signature, the reference solution, and doc string. And there's no way to measure functional correctness
for doc strings. So instead, they graded 10 samples for each of 1,640 problems by hand manually,
which takes a long time, which is why only 10 samples for each problem was graded.
And then it was found that the pass at one and pass at 10 was found was 20.3% and 46.5%
respectively, which is slightly lower than that of CodexS. And some limitations of Codex
includes not enough or not sample efficient to train as the training data totaled hundreds of
millions of lines of code. And also the performance decreases exponentially in doc string length.
So synthetic problems created from assembling 13 building blocks that deterministically
modifies string input. So for example, convert to lowercase or remove every third char.
These were created, and it was found that when the number of chain components from these building
blocks increases, the pass rate decreases as shown in the plot. And finally, it can make mistakes
binding variables to operations, especially when there are a lot of them. The next model I will
be discussing is Llama2. Now Llama2 is a family of pre-trained and fine-tuned LLMs with billions
of parameters. And it can outperform other open source LLMs and be on par with some closed source
LLMs. Now the pre-training architecture and hyperbarreners were mostly adopted from Llama1.
So for example, it has a standard transformer architecture with renormalization, where the
inputs of each sublayer was normalized instead of the output. And this was shown to improve
training stability, and this was inspired by GPT3. And also the swiglu activation function,
which uses the swish function, was used. And it was found to allow more flexibility and
expressiveness in the feed forward layers, and therefore improve performance of transformer
models compared to standard activations like Rilu. And finally, instead of absolute positional
embeddings, they use rotary positional embeddings, which uses a rotation matrix instead of just
vectors for each token for the positional embeddings. And this shows relative positions
of tokens and allows a model to capture their dependencies. And this can improve performance
because changing positions of words in a sentence can change its meaning,
especially their relative positions. And now 7, 13, 34, and 70 billion parameters
were used for the family of models. And the context length, which is the amount of text that
can be processed at a time, was doubled from Lama 1. So now it's 4k. And the learning rate of
use was 0.0003 for smaller models and 0.00015 for larger models with group query attention,
which is a method to stabilize the performance for larger models.
And also it's trained using atom optimizer with weight decay with a cosine learning rate schedule,
and it was trained on two trillion tokens of data, which is 40% more than Lama 1.
And now the Lama 1 and 2 base models, along with other open source models, such as
MPT and Falcon, were evaluated on several benchmarks for comparison. So for code,
the average pass-at-one score on human EFL and another data set called MBPP is reported.
And then for common sense reasoning, world knowledge, reading, comprehension, and math,
the average of scores from different methods were reported. And finally,
the massive multitask language understanding, which evaluates a wide variety of tasks,
big bench hard, which evaluates a subset of big bench tasks, which evaluates a wide variety of
tasks that were found to be beyond the capabilities of current language models.
And also artificial general intelligence evaluation, which evaluates models based on
their performance on human-centric standardized exams, were also reported.
And this table summarizes the results discussed previously. And as shown, it was found that
generally the Lama 2.70 billion performs the best.
And now Lama 2.Chat is a version of Lama 2 with supervised fine-tuning through alignment techniques
and supervised fine-tuning with publicly available instruction fine-tuning data.
It was found that that quality is all you need as using less, i.e. thousands instead of millions,
but higher quality examples was shown to have improved results. And also RLHF,
which is reinforcement learning with human feedback, is applied after fine-tuning so that
the model can understand the user intentions to further align the model with human preferences.
Now, data of human preferences obtained from human feedback was collected and
for more diversity of collected prompts, binary comparison protocol was used to collect
feedback. So annotators would write prompts for the models and then for each prompt,
they would choose one of two responses from different variants of the model. So, for example,
with different temperature based on provided criteria, which in this case is healthfulness or
safety, and then they would rank how much better their chosen response is on a scale of four points.
And then, as I just said, the preference, it was given to healthfulness and safety,
and this data was received in batches over time, so at the reward model improved over time.
Now, human preference data was used to train reward model,
so that patterns in the preference can be learned by changing internal text distribution
of the base model, and it outputs a score based on prediction of the quality of the model based
on human preference given a prompt and model response, and these scores were used as rewards for
RLHF, and the reward model was initialized from the pre-trained model to avoid situations where
the model would end up favoring hallucinations, so i.e., giving the wrong incorrect or misleading
responses, and the same architecture and hyperparameters were used as well, but with
a regression head for outputting rewards instead of a classification head, as the rewards are real
numbers, and two RMS were used, one for healthfulness and one for safety, and later on we will be
discussing why two are used instead of one, so a binary ranking loss with the margin component was
used, where the margin component is a function of the preference rating, which is different for
each reward model, and this helps the reward model give more distinct scores for more different
responses, and the preference data was increased by combining with open sourced ones,
and it was trained with the same parameters as the base model, but only ran one epoch, as previous
studies have shown that it may overfit if more than one epoch was ran, and also slightly lower
learning rate was used, and here are the results for the chat reward modeling, so these reward
models were found to help perform STEAM SHP XL open assistant and GPT-4 on several human preference
benchmarks, so specifically the helpfulness reward model and safety reward model each
performed best in their own domain, so for example the helpfulness reward model performed best on
the meta-helpful data, the safety reward model performed best on meta harmless data and etc,
and this makes sense because they may sometimes have conflicts, so for example if a user were to
give the prompt how to make a bond, then it's impossible to have a response that is both helpful
and safe at the same time, and optimizing one reward model with both objectives would have
confused the model in that case, and therefore it would not perform well.
Now successive versions of RLHF were trained as more batches of human preference data were
received, and these were labeled v1 to v5, and RLHF fine-tuning was explored with two algorithms,
the first one is rejection sampling fine-tuning, so at each iteration k samples generated from
the model, and then the best one was selected using the reward model, these best samples were
used for a gradient update to tune the model for the next iteration, and this was only applied to
the 7b model, while the smaller models were fine-tuned on rejection sample data from the 7b model,
and later versions include best samples from all previous models and not just the proceeding one,
since for example the v3 was trained using only samples from v2 that was found that its
performance worsened in certain tasks, and sampling temperature was also adjusted for each
iteration because its optimal value significantly changed over iterations.
The second method is a standard method in reinforcement learning called proximal policy
optimization, which is on policy method that uses policy gradient updates to update the policy,
and it uses the reward model as an estimate of the reward function, and the language model
as the policy to optimize, and the policy was iteratively improved by sampling prompts from
the dataset and generations from policy, and then the policy, proximal policy optimization is applied.
A new technique from the paper called ghost attention or GAT was introduced,
and it helps control dialogue flow over multiple turns.
So initially the RLHF model sometimes forgets instructions in a dialogue after a few turns.
For example, when the first prompt is to answer with only emojis,
the model may do it for the first few prompts, but later on it would forget it and answer with
actual words, and this issue can be fixed with GAT and was applied after the version 3 of RLHF,
and the method works by synthetically concatenating the instruction to user messages
once it's defined, and is it was found to be consistent up to over 20 turns up to the context
length. Now for each prompt and a test set of helpfulness and safety,
three annotators judge the quality on a seven point scale, and the figure below shows the
when gray percent against GPT-4 for different versions of Lama 2 chat during the supervised
fine tuning and RLHF. So the plot on the left shows that when using the meta rewards models
judge the RLHF v3 and later versions L performs GPT-4 on both harmlessness and helpfulness,
however this may be unfair because the judge was made by the same company as Lama 2,
so the plot on the right shows the results when using the GPT-4 judge, and it was found that
still RLHF v5 both with no proximal policy optimization and with that L performs GPT-4
on harmlessness and helpfulness. Now Lama 2 chat was also compared with several other models
on human evaluation with over 4,000 diverse prompts with multi-turn prompts generated by
Lama 2 chat and or chat GPT, and for each prompt three human annotators rate how much better or
worse one model is than the other on a seven point scale, and this is shown in the plot below,
and it shows that when put against the other models shown here Lama 2 chat had a higher
win rate and a loss rate. Now for safety harmful data was filtered out during pre-training and
fine-tuning, and compared to before fine-tuning Lama 2 chat showed great improvement in truthfulness
and toxicity as its scores for truthful QA and toxigen improved, and also its scores for bold
also improved which shows a lowered bias, and to test robustness against attackers
red teaming was performed with over 300 people of different demographics and fields,
and they probed the models in various unsafe situations with simulated prompts,
and these insights were used for fine-tuning and feedback training to lower the rate of
violating responses. So for example for the 7B model the rate was lowered by four times,
and overall it outperforms many other models in helpfulness and safety based on human
graders judging. However a limitation is that while these safety tuning approaches fixed most
safety issues it goes too far in some instances which can cause the model to be overly cautious
and have false refusals, although this only happens 0.05% of the time on the helpfulness data.
The next model I will be discussing is mixed drill of experts. Now mixed drill 8 times 7B
is a sparse mixed drill of experts model that can outperform
mama270B and GPT 3.5 on most benchmarks such as math, math, cold generation, and multilingual tasks,
and the model basically uses a subset of parameters for each token and can change the size of
of the active parameters to make inference faster or have a higher throughput,
and this image illustrates the mixture of experts layer which will be discussed later.
So the Mistral 7B is an earlier version of mixed drill that has a similar architecture to mama,
but also has sliding window attention which limits the amount of tokens each token can attend to
by a window size W and this saves computation and memory, and this is possible with two other
methods used called rolling buffer cache and prefill and chunking, and this is illustrated in the image below.
Now mixed drill also has the same architecture and parameters as Mistral except that the
context length is quadrupled from Mistral to 32K and feed forward blocks are replaced by
eight mixed drill of experts layers and experts are individual feed forward networks
and generally mixed drill of experts output is some of the top products of the expert
and its gating network over each expert eye.
So the gating event network in Mistral takes us off max of top K logits of the linear layer
so then the total sparse parameter count can grow with the number of flares while the active
parameter count which is used for processing a token only grows with K and for mixed drill
the expert used is swiglu activation function and K equals two so this is illustrated by the
image shown here before where the router takes the inputs and it passes it to only two of the eight
experts with the highest logits and so then the active parameters would be from just
these two experts and the output would only depend on those two experts.
Now mixed drill was compared to Lama by evaluating them on several benchmarks similar to
in Lama2's paper and the results are shown in the table below and the columns from
heliswag up to arc challenge represents common sense reasoning and then natural questions
and trivia qa represents world knowledge humanevalent mvpp represent code and finally math and gsmak
represents math and from this table it shows that a mixed drill out performs Lama2 70b on
overall and it outperforms Lama2 even though it has over five times less active parameters
um and also compared to its earlier version mixed drill had mixed drills
multilingual data was significantly up sampled which allowed it to perform well on multilingual
benchmarks particularly on four different languages uh french german spanish and italian
and for each of these languages the um arcs c challenge heliswag and mmlu benchmarks are
reported um and it's shown that it mixed drill does better than Lama2 on all of them
um
and as for long range performance um mixed drill has good long range performance as
as 100 percent retrieval accuracy of the pasky retrieval task which measures the ability of models
to retrieve a pasky randomly inserted in a long prompt and the perplexity uh
the decreases as the context length increases where the perplexity is how um how um is that is
basically how um how um uh how unlikely is to um to be able to predict the uh the models outputs
and um also uh in in terms of the bias benchmarks uh mixed drill l performs Lama2 70b on the uh
bias benchmark for qa and also in the bias in open-ended language generation dataset uh
where it has higher scores overall compared to Lama2 and this represents less social bias
now uh mixed drill instruct is a version of uh mixed drill which with supervised fine-tuning
on an instruction dataset followed by direct performance optimization and and um the and
this was evaluated um using the large model systems chatbot arena uh where users would um
would have a would uh send a prompt to two models and then select which uh which model
they prefer based on the responses and the winning model would get a higher elo while the losing
model would get a lower elo and this um this elo is um is used to measure the performance
models or one way to measure the performance of the models and um as of december 2023
mixed drill instruct L performs other open-weight models on the MT bench which is a set of challenging
multi-turn questions um where uh users would uh have uh conversations um with the uh
with the uh model and um involves multiple prompts and also um mixed drill instruct was
ranked uh sixth place in the arena's elo and this was based on 200 000 human preference votes
now now we analyze the the router um so the distribution of selected experts using the
file datasets was measured and reported for the first middle and last layers um and uh this was
shown in the this is shown in the um graph on the left uh and as we can see uh only dm mathematics
from the file datasets um had significantly different distributions and um this is possible
this is possibly due to the limited coverage of natural language and um the synthetic nature of
the dataset and um also it was found that the distribution at the first and last layer is
very similar to the input and output and beddings respectively which suggests that the router has
structured syntactic behavior and this is also shown in the image on the right where as we can
see the um similar words would have the same colors and also like the indents for the indents
they're generally the same colors and also like groups of symbols uh similar groups of symbols
have the same color um the final model i will be discussing is um POM which stands for Pathways
Language Model uh and um it's a very big um 540 billion parameter model uh that uh using the um
pathway system and um it's uh it's a densely activated transformer language model that um
is trained on um 6144 chips from um google's uh tpu v4 uh chips and um so some features it has is
it's um as efficient scaling as it's scaled very well across thousands of accelerator chips in a
highly efficient manner and also um it has shown continued improvements from scaling as um
it's a uh it's a very big model like um with 540 billion parameters but it's um
it it's performance uh also uh grew with that size um so um
so it can perform reasoning tasks uh via multi-step mathematics and other breakthrough capabilities
and in fact it's actually um it actually uh has a dramatic jump in accuracy when uh come
from the 62 billion uh parameter version of the POM um compared to the um
the jump in accuracy from 8 billion to 62 billion parameters so there's a discontinuous
improvement um the where the um scaling behavior is uh not um where improvements and performance
is non-linear and um so so new capabilities emerge when the model achieves a sufficient scale um and
also um it has multilingual understanding as um uh it has more thorough work than earlier models
such as translation um also it it has improved accuracy on gender and occupation bias however
it still has issues with um other biases um for example it associates Muslims with terrorism
extremism and violence and so this is a work in progress um the the architecture uses a standard
transformer model with a decoder only set up and each time stamp can only attend to itself
and pass time steps um it also uses the swigloo activation function which as discussed earlier
it helps improve performance for um transformers and um it also has um parallel layers where each
transformer block is in parallel and the formulation um the parallel formulation is
similar to the standard formulation but the but the attention term is moved outside of the
multi-layer perceptron
um uh so three different models uh scales were compared uh so 540 billion 62 billion and 8 billion
and the number of flops per token is approximately equal to the number of parameters
uh and um the models are all trained identically except uh with the
hyper parameters shown in the table below which uh shows the number of layers uh the number of
attention heads um and the dimension of the model which refers to the number of neurons in each layer
of the network and number of parameters and batch size um
so the training data set consists of a high quality corpus of 780 billion tokens
representing a wide range of natural language use cases and is based on data sets used to train
the lambda model so the table below shows the proportion of data um for each data source
and um the multilingual corpus contains text from over 100 languages um and also uh five percent of
it comes from github code so if you ever published your code on github the authors of neural networks
will likely to thank you as you have contributed to the training of several models
um now here we show the training infrastructure where um all models are trained on tpu v4 pods
and um the training and evaluation code base is based on jax and t5x and um
um all models are trained on tpu v4 pods where palm 540b is trained over two uh two of those
pods and over a data center network using a combination of model and data parallelism
and um it uses um 3072 tpu v4 chips in each pod attached to 768 hosts
so here are the results um which are obtained by the palm 540b model across um 29 benchmarks
and uh and compared to uh prior state of the art the abbreviated as s sota in the table
and um this was done for um zero shot one shot and few shot where um for the few shots the number
of shots for each task are mentioned in the parentheses so this table shows that um
generally uh the palm performs better than the prior state of the art
um now um for the uh another um benchmark called the big bench um it includes over 150 tasks that
cover a variety of language modeling tasks including logical reasoning translation
question answering mathematics etc and um uh the on the left shows the evaluation of palm
compared to gp3 gopher chinchilla and also um and humans where the average human metric is around
150 while the best humans do around a hundred and um palm five shot um where which shown five
examples in training uh performs better than the average human at of around uh 10 to the 11 model
parameter so for evaluating reasoning um arithmetic reasoning is uh often uses uses grade school level
natural language math problems which require multi-step logical inference while the math itself
is trivial the um difficult part is transforming the natural language into mathematical equations
and for common sense reasoning it involves questions answering tasks which require strong
world knowledge but are not simply factual question answering and they require chaining
multiple logical inferences around the world about about the world
and also for chain of thought prompting um this was um shown to uh
achieve help llm's achieve significantly higher um accuracy um improvements by
generating intermediate reasoning steps before generating the final steps and in a few shot
setting these intermediate reasoning steps are manually written for the first for the few shot
examples um model will then generate its own chain of thoughts for the test examples and
only the final answer and uh while only the final answer is used for evaluation of these generated um
uh the generated chain of thoughts can um be useful for your analysis and model interpretability
which is one one of the major drop backs of llm's and um chain of thought prompting allows language
models to better perform multi-step reasoning tasks such as math work problems as shown in
this image here where the where the second question um it gives a wrong output for standard
prompting but uh correct for the chain of thought prompting um
so uh from chain of thought prompting um achieve strong performance on a range of arithmetic and
common sense reasoning tasks um
and uh as for the code tasks the um uh bomb can be used for two main types of code work the first
one is uh text to code uh which involves generating code from uh natural language description and
the second is um code to code which involves translation work particularly to translate
c or c plus plus programs to python um the um uh the current level of expertise is a
generation of python of a python function from the description but uh but currently it's unable to
generate an entire program uh but this is a very promising research area um and uh
transcoder data is downloaded from github and provides a few shot examples to provide training
to the bomb model uh and examples from the bomb color 540b model is shown in the image here
or in the top left uh it shows the gsm it shows a gsm 8k python question converted from the open
ai gsm 8k math data set in the bottom left it shows a transcoder example translating a simple
function from c plus plus to python and on the right it shows a converted human eval example
bomb included github code in its training set and a total of 39 billion code tokens were used
in the pre-training data set uh bomb supports additional languages such as java html javascript
python c php c sharp and c plus plus now a major risk of using this is that a generated code may
be wrong as there may be presence of several bugs um as for translation uh this task this task
involves rewriting one human language uh one human language into another one while preserving the
content semantics and style of the input so one one of one way is using um um english-centric
language pairs which is a traditional focus of past models and involves using english as the source
or target language so for example translating from english to french or from english to german
or vice versa for both of them and etc um another way is using uh direct language pairs where um
they directly translate between any pair of languages without involving english so for example
translating from french to german directly instead of going from french to english and
then to german and also um uh there are some um there are some extremely low resource
language pairs as in some cases one of the languages have little monolingual data such as
casak so for example french and german have about 24 and 26 billion tokens in training set
while casak only has around 134 million tokens and um this uh this table shows the results uh
the translation blue scores on traditional wmt language pairs and um
um uh use shot evaluation corresponds to five shots for palm and note that zero shot prompt
includes the source and target language names in the prompt while one shot and few shot don't
so languages must be inferred from the exemplars which may explain that the strong zero shot
performance in some language pair translation um in some language pair um and uh translation
quality is better when translating into english rather than out of english um and uh prompts can
deliver even more value than a single example and generalist models relying solely on self
supervision can match specialized models at a smaller scale and um finally uh we will
be discussing the limitations of palm and um so one of the limitations is that it contains and uh
it can contain an amplified biases in underlying data but uh this limitation is not unique to palm
but uh to other lms in general and um there's uh a general occupation bias and um
also toxic toxicity and bias such as um uh having some words like islam being associated with
highly charged terms and zero types such as terrorist violent and radical and um uh the
toxicity probability of the continuation as a function of um the toxicity probability of the
prompt um is um shown in this uh a graph and the human baseline represents the toxicity
probability of the original sentence continuation and um the the um so the toxicity probability
of continuation or tpc is more consistent with the toxicity probability of the prompt
or tpp than that of then the human tpc and this suggests that the model is strongly influenced
by the prompt style and is likely to respond like to like note that the palm 62 billion 540
billion models have very similar toxicity probabilities um and now we will uh now we show
a table that compares the lms of um the all the lms discussed in in this presentation so um these are
each of the lms have multiple versions or settings so only the most typical or the
largest one is picked for each one uh as uh having all of them would not fit in the page um
and finally uh we will be uh having um six questions for the discussion so question one
which is preferable unsupervised learning or reinforcement learning with human feedback
question two what makes a large language model large question three uh can language models be
used maliciously uh and how um question four um how can we reduce societal harm due to misuse of
language models uh question five uh how do we remove societal implicit biases from becoming
part of foundation models and finally question six what led to emergent abilities observed in lms
and here are the references used for the presentation thanks for watching