Hi, everyone. I am Haram and I am with
Marie-Anne Smith.
We will be discussing compressing and
sparsifying large language models.
Our presentation is divided into two parts.
I will talk about
sparsification of large language models and
Marie-Anne will discuss quantification of large language models.
Here is the outline for today.
I'll start off with an introduction.
I'll talk about what sparsity is.
Then we will extend the mixture of expert principle
and talk about G-shard.
And after G-shard, we will discuss our third paper, which is Colt T5,
a version of the Long T5.
We'll talk about its architecture, some evaluation and results.
And then I'll hand it over to Marie-Anne to talk about quantification.
So what is sparsity?
Sparsity uses the idea of conditional computation.
In dense models, all parameters are used for all inputs.
And sparsity allows us to only run some parts of the whole system.
And why we do that?
We do that because it helps with efficiency.
It helps with speed.
It's good for energy consumption.
And it's great for capacity generation.
So let's talk about what a traditional transformer model looks like.
So we have this input layer.
And we have the attention layer.
Then we have these output tokens.
These output tokens are then fed into the feed forward layer.
And then we get some output, which is fed onto the next layer.
So the key innovation here in the transformers
were the attention mechanism that allowed them
to consider the entire context of the input data.
And this was a substantial leap from the prior sequence models
that process data element at a time.
So there's a bottleneck here.
And the bottleneck is here.
So at scale, transformer needs to tackle more data and complex problems.
And with the huge number of parameters and operations needed,
it makes them very resource intensive
and leads to inefficiencies and limits their scalability.
So what's the solution for that?
The solution is conditional computing or sparse models.
So let's talk about it.
So we're going to cross this traditional architecture off
and we're going to make a few changes.
So if you look closely in this diagram,
we see that the changes we have made are over here.
So we have changed this feed forward network
into smaller subnetworks and we're calling them MOEs.
And then we have this gating mechanism
that decides which input tokens go to which experts.
And the rest of the model is same.
We have the input layer, tension layer, output tokens.
So yeah, what we did is we replaced this entire dense network
with smaller subnetworks
and we're essentially making it a divide and conquer problem,
which is going to be so good in terms of complexity
and computational resources.
So why are we doing that?
We are doing that because it's, as talked about earlier,
it's good for efficiency.
So a traditional GPT uses all neurons
in all matrices for forward passing.
So this entire network we see here,
all of these neurons are involved in every computation,
which is extremely expensive.
What if all the neurons are not needed
and we only need these orange ones?
We are essentially performing triple quadrupled
amount of compute that's essential.
What if we split this network into smaller subnetwork
and each performing a specialized task?
In terms of language translation,
if we take an example, this number one,
this expert would deal with punctuation, for example,
and number two would deal with article.
So we are dividing this huge problem into a smaller problem
and it is very good in terms of complexity.
So we saw that there was this routing mechanism
that decided which input tokens go to which experts.
So let's talk about it in detail.
So the routing mechanism is essentially the network
that decides which tokens go to which expert.
It's actually a learned process.
It's not static.
It learns and adapts through training.
So as the mixture of expert model is exposed to more data,
the routing mechanism defines and refines its criteria
for selecting the experts for different type of input tokens.
So over time, this learning process leads to specialization
of experts and each expert becomes more adept
at handling specific types of input tokens,
which improves the overall efficiency
and effectiveness of the model.
So at inference time, the routing mechanism learned behavior
allows the model to use only a fraction of the experts compute,
which is great.
So we are essentially performing this amount of computation
instead of using the entire network.
So let's talk about the paper.
The paper is called efficient large-scale language modeling
with mixture of experts.
So what they do here is they actually use this mixture
of expert models at scale and they see how this model performs
at scale compared to dense models.
So we see that this graph here on the x-axis,
we have dense training zeta flops.
And on the y-axis, we have an MOE speedup factor.
We'll talk about how this is calculated in the next slides,
but right now you can just think of it as how much more efficient
an MOE model is relative to a dense model.
And a speedup factor of 9 would indicate that
an MOE model can match the performance of a corresponding
dense model using 9 times less compute.
So let's talk about the results here.
We see that they have tested their model in three domains.
So they have tested in domain language modeling,
which is testing their model on data that it was trained on.
Then they have tested on out of domain, which is a red line,
which is testing their model on data that it was not trained on.
And then we have zero short priming.
So we see that the highest gain is for in domain language modeling.
So MOEs are most efficient when evaluated in domain.
And we see that the gain is 18 and around 16 or 18 here.
So dense models perform 18 to 16 times more better than corresponding
MOE models perform better than dense models.
So the lowest gain is for the zero short priming, but it's still better.
It's around four times better than a dense model.
So let's talk about how the speedup factor is calculated.
So here C of t is the computed cost function at a given performance level t.
So they use interpolation here since they have only discrete values
in order to know the continuous values they need to use interpolation.
So they use the highest known value and the lowest known value.
And then they use a ratio of how far the performance level t
is between the lower and the higher reference performances.
And then this is the computed cost function.
And then the speedup factor is just a ratio of the computed cost of dense and the MOE.
Let's talk about the experiments that they performed.
So they trained autoregressive transformer models that roughly match the sizes and
architecture of GPT-3.
They use pre-normalization transformer blocks and GLU activations.
And for their dense models, they use only dense attention unlike GPT-3,
which uses alternate sparse and dense.
And they use top two expert model.
And by top two, they mean that when the gating mechanism scores the input
based on their relevance and expertise, they use the top two scoring inputs from there.
So I want to talk about this table from the paper.
So if you look closely, we have the training cost of GPT-3,
dense GPT-3.
And then they compare it with their dense model and their MOE model.
So we see that the training cost of a 13 billion GPT-3 model is 32.67.
Zeta flops, that is.
And that of an MOE model of 15 billion sizes, just 0.3, which is a huge gap.
And we see that these expert models are much, much better performing as compared to dense models.
So they pre-trained their data, their model on a union of six English language datasets.
I have listed them here and the links are attached to if you want to take a closer look.
But I will not be going into too much depth about these.
So let's talk about the results.
So they evaluate their models based on two metrics.
They check perplexity as well as performance.
And the reason they choose to is because perplexity is not a great indicator of downstream performance,
task performance.
So they choose perplexity, which is the confidence that a model has on its predictions.
If it's higher perplexity, then that's not good.
The model's not confident.
And for the data specifics, for in-domain data, they use the reserved portion of the training data,
set aside to test the model's performance.
And for out-of-domain, they use the pile dataset.
Again, these are some of the results from the paper.
We, on the left-hand side, we have in-domain data.
So this yellow line is for MOE model and this red line is for a dense model.
We see that yellow line is constantly less perplexed.
So MOE is better performing for in-domain.
And even for the out-of-domain data, we see that the yellow line has lesser perplexity.
This actually, this gap actually closes at scale.
They don't talk about why, but the reason could be overfitting.
But still, it performs better than a dense model, constantly less perplexed.
Yeah, so these are some of the other results.
We see that, so this is a speed-up factor that we talked about earlier.
So we see that the best result is for common crawl.
And the reason for that is because it's closely related to their model's training data.
And we did talk about how their model performs best in in-domain settings.
And on the right-hand side, again, we see that this yellow line has the best accuracy,
which means MOEs are very good, especially when compared to GPT-3
and other dense models.
So their accuracy is lesser than the accuracy of MOE.
So why are we scaling?
We are scaling because it brings dramatic quality gains, as we saw in the previous results.
Especially for computer vision and language processing tasks,
it yields consistent gains and has led to better classification.
This brings me to our second paper, which is Gshard.
It's not really an ML paper and more of an engineering paper because they talk about a framework.
This is actually a Google's framework called Gshard,
where they try to build a one trillion parameter model, but don't quite manage to create it.
So they go with the next best thing that they did manage to train and create,
which was the 600 billion parameter model.
So what they do here is they build a huge MOE model, 600 billion parameter,
and they then use parallelization to split their data into multiple machines.
So it's the same concept as we discussed earlier, but it's coupled with partition.
So here I've written that the large model scale does not come from increasing the depth of the
transformer, which is the number of layers, but increasing the width of the transformer,
which is the MOE model, essentially.
So they combine it with a hard routing to parallelize onto 248 TPUs,
and they manage to train it in just four days.
And it is based on something that's called SPMD, which means single program multiple data,
and it's a concept used in parallel computing, where a single program is executed by processors
parallel, but each processor works on a different set of data.
So let's talk about the architecture of Gshard. So this is the traditional architecture. We've
seen that. And then this is the MOE architecture. We see that we have this feedforward layer,
which we have split into multiple networks, subnetworks, and then we have the gating mechanism.
So Gshard uses alternate MOE layers with feedforward layers. So we have this MOE layer,
then we have a feedforward layer, then we'll have another MOE layer, and then another feedforward,
so on and so forth. And then here is what Sharding really is. So they actually split this entire
network onto different machines. And this entire thing is actually done by the Gshard framework
itself, and the user does not have to worry about the hardware details, which is the great
thing about this paper. So every machine has one expert on it. So we have this one expert here,
and then this number E expert on this machine. And there are E different machines essentially.
So let's talk about the gating mechanism here. So this equation shows us the gating score of
each expert. So here this is the input, we feed it into the gate function and we get a score for
each expert. And this is what is happening inside each expert. So we multiply the input projection
with the weights, then we apply an activation function to it and multiply it with the
output weights. And then we the output of each expert is essentially the weighted sum
of based on the gating score. So if an expert has a gating score of zero, we don't route any input
to it, which intuitively makes sense. And they talk about the considerations that they had while
creating this gating function. So they talk about load balancing, they create their gating function
in a way that their input is uniformly distributed among each expert. So not a single expert has
burden and every expert essentially gets the same number of input tokens. And then they also introduce
an auxiliary loss, where the loss function penalizes if it constantly sends inputs to one
expert. So it actually appreciates if the distribution is uniform. And then they have
random routing. So random routing is where we send the input tokens to the top two experts.
But then sometimes if the score difference between the two experts is a lot, one has a very high
score and the other has very low, then they'll just neglect the low scoring expert in order to
reserve the capacity of each expert. So how do we implement Gshard? As I discussed earlier,
it's very efficient and easy to use. We do not do not users essentially do not have to do anything.
And everything has been handled. User only adds annotations using the annotation API. So the Gshard
framework comes with two main things. It comes with an annotation API that lets users decide
whether or not they want something to be replicated or distributed. So the framework
would essentially decide itself. 80% of the time the framework would decide for itself whether
certain inputs need to be replicated or distributed. But it lets the user have some control as well.
So users can decide if they want something to be distributed or replicated.
And then it comes with an XLA compiler, which is an accelerated linear algebra compiler,
which actually creates a compiled program based on the annotation API and it just
shards the input based on that. So these are some characteristics of the XLA compiler.
It has unified compilation across frameworks. So it can work with TensorFlow as well as PyTorch.
It handles the partitioning itself. So it breaks down large computations into smaller
operations. And then it handles data communication as well. So when we are talking about partitioning,
a lot of computation and communication needs to happen between partitions as well.
And the user does not have to worry about that because the XLA compiler will do it itself.
And we will talk about it here. So these are some things that some partitioning considerations
that the XLA compiler handles. The two main ones they talk about in the paper are padding
and halo exchange. And for example, if a certain tensor does not have even dimensions,
so it will not be uniformly distributed. So certain partitions would have more data than
other partitions. So what XLA compiler does in such cases is it pads the tensor with either
identity matrix or zero. And it then uniformly distributes that tensor.
And in some conditions, for example, in convolution tasks, we know that we have a kernel
and that sliding window needs to move over our input here. So in this animation, this sliding
window is moving over the input. But what if when it reaches this edge here, half of its data is
residing on the other partition. So what do we do in such cases? This area in this paper is called
halo area. And what the compiler does is when it reaches a halo area, it asks for other partitions
to send their halo areas and they do this halo exchange so that each partition has the entire
complete window so it can produce accurate results. And this, again, is handled by the XLA
compiler and we do not have to worry about it, which is the great thing about it.
Let's talk about the experiments they did and the data sets they use. So the data set is mined
from the web and it's not available to us. It has documents for over 100 languages
to and from English. So the model they train is for massive multilingual machine translation.
So it's a machine translation model and it's multilingual. So it translates from different
languages to English. The volume is huge. It's a total of 25 billion training examples.
And then they have imbalance in language pairs. So say they have languages that have
millions of training examples, but for some languages, they do not have a lot of examples
for it and they call them low resource languages. And for baseline, they actually train
bilingual neural machine translation models for each language pair and then they compare the
results with that. So these are some model variations. So they vary two variables. They
vary the number of layers in their models and then they vary the number of experts used.
So in this table here, we see that they have to start with 2000. They actually start with 128
experts and then they move to 512 and then they move to 2048, which is their largest model.
And then they start with 12 layers, 36 layers and 60 layered is their largest model.
So let's talk about some of the results. So we see that this blue line, so this is actually
blue score, delta blue score. So this blue line here is the performance or the delta blue score,
which is quality gain of MOE model with 36 layers. So we see that it performs the best and the reason
for that is because of the number of layers. So as the number of layers increase, the model
due to over parameterization gets to learn a lot. And then this brown line is the 12-layer model,
which also intuitively makes sense because we would not expect it to perform better than a
deeper model. And then we see that as the scale increases, the quality gain increases as well,
which is contributing to our hypothesis that models perform better at scale. So yeah, this is
from the graph that we just talked about. We see consistent quality gains with deeper models,
so we saw that the model with 36 layers performs better than the model with 12 layers. And then
we see that we see improvements for high resource task with more experts. So as the number of experts
increase, we see improvements. We see this graph going upward. So this is an other graph that
the model talks about. So let's first take a look at the red line here, which is the quality gain
measured in delta blue score, which is a standard metric for evaluating the accuracy of machine
translation tasks. We see that as we increase the model size, we start off with 37 billion weights
and then we move towards 600 billion. And as we increase the size, the blue line, this right here,
which is the training wall time, even as our model size increases, this blue line does not
increase exponentially, which means that our model is learning really well and is not
computationally expensive as compared to dense models. So if you direct your attention to the
dotted line here, it represents the computational cost in terms of TPU v3 core years. You'll notice
that as we move from a model with 37.5 billion weights to the one with 600 billion weights,
the computational cost increases only from 6 to 22 core years. This is just a sublinear increase
when considering the 16 fold increase in model size. So it means that MOE models are able to
achieve great translation quality in a fraction of time as compared to dense models. They actually
talk about the time that their dense model took and it was 235 TPU core years and this is just 22.
Let's talk about the training efficiency now. So deeper models are more sample efficient and
they converge faster with fewer examples, which is because of the acceleration effect of over
parameterization since deeper models have more parameters. We see that here, a model with 12
layer takes 995 billion tokens to reach a cross entropy loss of 0.7 while that of just that of
36 layers just takes 321 billion tokens, which is three times less than that. Let's discuss the
performance now. So the largest model, which is of 600 billion size, can be trained in four days
to achieve the best quality while that of 96 layers and 2048 cores took 42 days, which is 10 times
more time to train. They also talk about the memory consumption actually. So the memory
consumption in Gshard comes from three things. It's the replicated weights, which is in the
transformer feedforward layers, then they have distributed weights and then they have activations,
which is the output of each layer that is used in forward and backward paths. So if we look here,
we see that as we increase the number of experts, so we started off with 128 experts and then we
moved towards 2048 experts and as we increase the expert size, our activation weights and our
weights actually increase, which intuitively makes sense, but something really interesting
happens at the end. So we see that here, instead of the activation weights increasing, we see a
little decrease. The reason here is that as the memory size of the activation increases,
it cannot be spaced in one partition. So the XLA compiler actually rematerializes this and
just uses some of the activations in the memory and then the others are computed during the back
pass, which is another great feature of the XLA compiler. So what are the key takeaways here?
So Gshard uses SPMD framework for massive scaling, then it provides this annotation
APIs that let us decide which tensors we want on every machine and which tensors we want to be
split on every machine and then they are able to train a massive multilingual machine translation
model of a 600 billion parameter size in just four. Coming to the last paper, which is the
conditional long T5. It is a version of the long T5, which uses conditional computation in a very
different way. So the last two papers were talking about the same concept, which was the mixture of
expert model, but here we have a different concept. They actually use the sparsity in a very different
context, which we will discuss in the next slide. So we see that many natural processing tasks
benefit from long inputs, but processing long inputs is very expensive. Why? Because of quadratic
attention complexity. So every input has to attend to every other input, which is quadratic,
and when the input is too long, it's unfeasible to keep it in, to use it as it is. So as the input
increases, not all tokens are actually important. So it's the theory of bag of words. So in a bag
of words, only a few words are important, right? So this is the intuition behind conditional
long T5. The paper is called Faster Long Range Transformers with Conditional Computation. And
the intuition, as I discussed earlier, is that some tokens are more important than others,
and we can achieve better quality for lower cost by devoting more computation to important
tokens. And this is how they do it. So they have a light branch and they have a heavy branch. So
they route all tokens through the light branch. And only the important ones go through the heavy
branch. And the difference between these branches is that the light branch has light attention,
which is local attention, and light MLP layer. And the heavy branch has full attention and a
heavy MLP. So these are the three main components of quality five. They have routing modules that
decide which input tokens go through the heavy branch. Then they have conditional feed forward
in the heavy branch and a conditional attention layer in the heavy branch as well.
Again, here, the routing mechanism of quality five is learnable. They just multiply inputs with
a learned embedding to obtain routing scores and normalize it. And then they select the top
K highest scoring inputs, and they route those inputs through the heavy branch.
And here again, this is what the conditional feed forward looks like. We have the light branch on
every token, but only a certain amount of tokens would be fed on to the heavy branch based on
their score. This is the score that we calculated in the last slide. And then for conditional
attention, we know that most tokens have simple interaction, but some tokens benefit from heavier
processing. So conditional attention consists of light and heavy branches. And this is what it
looks like. So we see that some rows just have blue boxes, but some have additional purple boxes
as well. This is where we are adding heavy extra tokens for important input tokens. But
for local attention, we are just taking the local span of windows.
Let's talk about the training. So that we pre-trained on a C4 data set with a batch size
of 256. And they fine tuned using a constant learning rate of 0.001. And these are the models
they used. So they use three variations, a base model, a large and an extra large.
For a base model, it was $248 million. And for the extra large, it was $5.2 million.
These are the data sets. These are some of these are different, but most of them belong to the
scrolls benchmark on which Coal T5 actually achieves state of the art. These are the results. So
the average performance of the blue line is much, much better than the pink line. So the blue line
is Coal T5 and we see that it performs much better. And if we take a look at the time,
we see that it requires way less time as compared to the long T5 for inference as well as for fine
tuning. So as I talked about earlier, it achieves SOTA on the scrolls benchmark. We see that the
Coal T5 extra large model speed is lesser and has greater F1 score than the
Long T5 and greater exact match accuracy as well. So they actually, the way they scale is not in the
model size, but actually the input size. And we see that it's effectively scales to extremely long
inputs and achieves stronger performance. So we see that the blue line has greater F1 score.
And they start off with an 8K input length and they move towards 64K. And during all this time,
they take way less time as compared to Long T5 and has have greater performance.
They do some ablation studies as well. And we see that as we, they actually, one interesting thing
they do is they make the routing static. And as we make the routing static, we see that the
performance degrades. The score, if you see the score, it's actually way less than the baseline.
That actually contributes to the factor that it benefits from dynamically routing token
as it learns to identify and give more importance to important token. And this indicates that the
model is not just performing better due to having more parameters.
They also discussed some limitations of Colt T5 in the paper. They say that Colt T5 applies
conditional computation only in the encoder. And it does not apply conditional computation to the
decoder because it's complicated. And they leave that for future work. And they also talk about
its specialization over long sequences. So it has to be trained from scratch for other types
of sequences. This is a small comparison I did between the three models. So Mixture of Expert
uses a 1.1 trillion model parameter model and Gshard uses 600 billion while Colt T5 uses 5.3
billion. For sparsification, Mixture of Expert just splits the feed forward layer while Gshard's
splits the feed forward layer as well as does partitioning while Colt T5 splits by branching.
Sparsification for Mixture of Expert is in the feed forward layer. For Gshard, it's in the
feed forward layer as well. But for Colt T5, it's in all three layers. Mixture of Expert uses top
two experts. Gshard uses top two in random routing and Colt T5 does not use any. For attention,
Mixture of Expert uses dense attention. Gshard also uses dense attention, but Colt T5 uses a
mixture of both. And for specialization, Mixture of Expert specializes in large-scale data. Gshard
specializes in parallelization and Colt T5 specializes in long inputs. Now I will hand it over
to Mariam to talk about sparsification. Hi, so I will be discussing the quantization of LLMs.
Let me just fix sides a bit.
I think a couple of the slides are missing.
We'll see the coming slides. Now to overview their mixed precision quantization. So
every feature is quantized based on its magnitude. So let's say we have this input tensor.
And we have the weight matrix. Now the input tensor will be divided into vectors. And the
high-magnitude vectors will be identified. And they will be multiplied normally in floating
point 16. While the low-magnitude ones, they will be multiplied in int 8. So they are multiplied
with quantization constants, which convert the floating point 16 into int 8. And then the
matrix multiplication is performed. And then they are decontized to get the output in the final fp16.
So basically, but this bottleneck matrix multiplication part is carried out in int 8. So
this is the mathematical form of this, where the floating points, the total output is actually
the sum of the floating point matrix multiplication operations and the int 8 matrix multiplication
operations. This sf16 is the scaling factor, which is used to adjust int 8 matrix multiplication
back into floating point 16. This is basically the decontization happening.
Now discussing the vector-wise quantization, this is a form of a block-wise quantization,
but such that each row of the tensor or column of the tensor is used as a single vector,
and it is independently quantized. Now this improves the quantization precision for most
of the features. Now, for example, if this is the input matrix and this is the weight matrix,
a1, a2, a3, and b1, b4, and b7, these are, this is the matrix, this is the single operation of
multiplication that will form our output matrix. So these vectors are independently quantized.
They have their own scaling constants, and then the output is calculated. Once all the vectors are
placed together in a matrix and summed, and then decontized. This is the mathematical form,
where the output is actually the multiplication of the decontization scaling factor and the
in-date output. In-date output is calculated by independently quantizing a vector a and vector b.
Basically, the input vectors, let's say the input tensor is made up of these two vectors a and b.
So a and b will be independently quantized, and they will be multiplied with the scaling factor
to get our final output. Over here is the quantization function.
Now, going into more detail of the scaling constants, basically, what are the quantization
procedures that they're using? So they have displayed their experiments using
AvSmax quantization as well as zero-point quantization. AvSmax is symmetric. It scales the
input values via constant derived from the largest absolute value in the tensor. So basically,
it's 127, because int8, that's basically just 2 to the power 8 minus 1. So it's the total number,
it's the maximum number that can be represented in the in-date representation, and it's divided
by the maximum of that vector. So this ensures that the extreme values are captured, but it also
leads to less efficient use of the available bit range. The more efficient zero-point quantization
is the most efficient, the more efficient quantization technique is the zero-point
quantization. It is asymmetric. It involves shifting of the distribution of the input values.
So in this way, the entire range of the representation is used effectively, and this
accommodates asymmetric data as well. So in this procedure, we will divide twice the
maximum number of maximum bit representation divided, and we will divide it by the max minus min.
And then in the end, we will also add the vector multiplied by its minimum.
So this accommodates the entire range of the bit representation, and this also reduces quantization
error across the board. Now, these are some results from their paper. They've calculated their C4
perplexity, and as we can see in this table, excuse me.
As we can see in this paper, abs max and zero-point, abs max, row wise and vector
zero-point vector wise, they reduce the worsen as we scale, and after 2.7 billion parameters,
they perform worse. So after 2.7 billion parameters, the methods actually perform worse
than smaller models. Zero-point vector wise quantization performs worse after 6.7 billion
parameters. So you may notice that zero-point quantization has an advantage over abs max
quantization, but it's no longer advantageous when used with the mixed precision decomposition.
So as you can see, their method LLM in-date outperforms all existing methods,
and it's preserving the perplexity as we scale, and it's exactly comparable.
It's very comparable with the 32-bit flow transformer models.
So even though this was not a part of their main focus, but they've also given some results
related to the time complexity, so they've noticed that the quantization overhead can
slow inference for models with less than 6.7 billion parameters as compared to the floating
point 16 baseline. However, after 6.7 billion parameters, LLM in-date runs about twice as
fast for large metrics multiplications in equivalent to those in 175 billion models.
LLM in-date is twice as fast, and there's also to note that even though LLM in-date has some
more overhead for models smaller than 6.7 billion parameters, these small models usually fit on
most GPUs and quantization is not really needed in practice. Now moving on, we see that we are
able to quantize the parameters in the feed-forward and attention projection layers, but during
inference. But what about training and what about the attention function computations?
So this moves us to our next paper, which is 8-bit optimizers using block-wise quantization.
Now these perform optimization in neural networks by using 8-bit statistics to maintain the
performance level of 32-bit optimizer states during training. So this paper focuses on
optimization during training, and they are also not focused on the weights. Instead,
they are going to focus on the optimizer states, because optimizer states use about 33 to 75% of
the total memory footprint during training. So what are these optimizer gradient statistics?
So basically, regular optimizers in machine learning update model parameters
purely based on the gradient calculated from the current batch of data. But state-field
optimizers like SGD and Adam, they keep track of the past gradients and use this information to
inform updates. For example, SGD uses momentum for smoothing the updates, and Adam keeps track
of the squared sum of past gradients to adapt the learning rate for each parameter.
So this paper focuses on optimizing the memory footprint of these optimizer states.
Now they employ block-wise quantization, and this approach reduces the memory usage of the
optimizer states, allowing larger models to be trained within the same memory constraints without
losing the performance benefits that come from using stateful optimizer optimizers.
The key innovations in this paper are block-wise dynamic quantization
and the stable embedding layer. Now this block-wise quantization isolates outliers
and disputes the error more equally over all bits. Basically, over here, they break down the tensor
into smaller blocks or chunks and then normalize each block independently
for efficient computation and for processing in parallel.
And this is the mathematical form of it, and they use the normalization constant for block B,
which is the maximum absolute value within that block. So the quantized value of the vector is
divided by the normalization constant, and this fraction is subtracted from the
function mapping the jth element to its quantized form.
They are basically unique abs max quantization, which we will see later on.
Now why is this method good? Because it's robust to outliers. This is independent from intercore
intercore synchronization, because since we are dividing the blocks and those
computations are happening in parallel, so we don't need to do the intercore synchronization.
So this enhances the computational efficiency, and this method also guarantees that the largest
values are quantized without error. So this maintains the precision in the quantization process.
Now they've also introduced this dynamic quantization procedure. So
over here, this is basically a type of quantization where they are just for both small and large
magnitude values with high precision, and they are actually enhancing the dynamic tree quantization
for tensors that don't need a sign bit by repurposing it for better precision in the
presenting positive values. What this means is this is about adjusting the quantization technique
used in optimizers like Adam, which generally involves keeping track of the second state or
a running average of the gradients. Since these values are always positive, the sign bit typically
used to indicate negative numbers in binary representations don't need it. So the authors
utilize this redundant sign bit to increase the precision of the quantization, thus allowing
the optimizer to handle a broader range of values that the second state might encounter
during training. This modification has to maintain the fidelity of the optimizer state
representation. So this is especially important for large language models, which can have
significant variations in the scale of gradient information. So this allows accounts for a wide
range of magnitudes in this Adam optimizer. So the other key innovation is the stable
embedding layer. So basically traditional embedding layers can become unstable with lower
precision formats like 8-bit integers, because the reduced precision can lead to large errors
or instabilities in the training process. However, the stable embedding layer that they've introduced
they allow for the use of 32-bit optimizer states, even when the embeddings are quantized to 8-bit.
But this means that the calculations for updating the weights during training
can still use higher precision, even though the embeddings themselves use lower precision.
So the method they use is the layers initialized with heavier uniform initialization for consistent
variants, and then they apply a layer norm before adding the position embeddings. So this
ensures that the variant stays around one and it avoids large gradients that could destabilize
training. So this offers significant memory savings without altering the original optimizer
hyperparameters. And this also facilitates stable training, even when more aggressive
quantization techniques are used. These are some of the results. So as we can see,
this table basically describes the median performance on many NLP and computer vision tasks.
We will be focusing on this language model and transformer tasks. So this is for reference.
As you can see, this 8-bit atom, 8-bit optimizer's 8-bit atom reduces the time and mainly the memory
saved is huge. So from regular transformers, it's like 8.5 GB saved. So 8-bit is outperforming
in terms of memory and speed in all methods. So this is a pretty good paper, we can say,
but let's move on to the next paper, which performs fine tuning. So most of the times,
for most papers, we do not have the time or the resources to perform the complete training.
In most industrial use cases, we only need to fine-tune existing LLMs. So this paper,
Chlora focuses on the efficient fine tuning of those quantized LLMs.
Now, this fine-tuning LLMs is a memory-intensive procedure and models with like 65 billion
parameters require over 680 GB of GPU for the 16-bit fine-tuning. So Chlora reduces this average
memory requirements of fine-tuning a 65 billion parameter from 780 to 48 GB only. So this method
also reaches 99% of the performance level of chatGBT, while only required 24 hours of fine-tuning
on a single GPU. So these are really monumental and these are some amazing results. So let's go
into the detail of this architecture. Now, basically, normal fine-tuning is just the
base model and the optimizer states and this parameter updates and the gradient flow happens.
Happens normally. LLora was the quantization of the transformer model where it's a method that
reduces memory requirements by using a small set of trainable parameters. So all of the parameters
are not used for fine-tuning. Only a small set of trainable parameters are used which are
often termed as adapters. So the full model remains fixed and these adapters are only updated during
fine-tuning. So gradients during SGD are passed through the fixed pre-tuned model
into the adapter which is then updated to optimize the loss function. Chlora improves this method
by quantization the transformer model to 4-bit precision. So instead of a 16-bit transformer,
we are using a 4-bit transformer and we're also using paged optimizers to handle memory spikes.
So we will go into the detail of this innovation soon. So the key innovations of this paper are
they've introduced a new data type 4-bit normal float. So that is information theoretically
optimal for normally distributed weight. They also utilize double quantization to reduce the
average memory footprint. So what they're doing is they're performing quantization and then they
are quantizing the quantization constants as well. So this is double quantization and this reduces
the memory footprint and that's also using paged optimizers to manage memory spikes.
Now let's discuss the 4-bit normal float. So this quantization approach is different because
it balances the data across quantization bins more evenly. Traditional methods may not
distribute data as uniformly especially when there are outliers or a wide range of values.
So this method focuses on equalizing the number of values in each bin
and optimizing for a normal distribution. So this aims to minimize the information loss during
quantization process. So this is particularly suited to a neural network weights that usually
follow a normal distribution. So they spread out the outliers more evenly. Instead of putting them
together in a in a chunk or box and then quantizing them, they spread out the outliers more evenly
in the form of a normal distribution and this way you get a better representation of the whole
distribution with smaller number of bits. So this is more efficient than traditional methods.
Now double quantization. So this is a two-step process to compress the quantization constants
themselves which are used in the first quantization steps. So this further compresses the quantization
constants to save memory. They implement a secondary quantization process on the constants
themselves using 8-bit floats to reduce the memory footprint without memory loss. So this is
different from traditional single-step quantization by adding a second layer of quantization for the
constants. So this significantly reduces the parameter memory cost. Page optimizers are
automatic page-to-page transfers between the CPU and GPU. This is more on the computer network side.
So this is for LFE GPU processing. So when the GPU occasionally runs out of memory,
they will perform page-to-page transfers between the GPU and this CPU. This utilizes the NVIDIA
unified memory feature. Now let's compare clora versus standard fine-tuning. So these are some
quantized LLMs, OPT, bloom, pithya, and lama of different sizes from 125 million to 65 billion
with different data types. So they're evaluated on language modeling and a set of zero-shot tasks.
So here's the mean zero-shot accuracy using lama models with different 4-bit drill types. And as we
can see, normal float that they've introduced, normal 4-bit float, and dynamic quantization
outperforms the other methods in mean zero-shot accuracy, it's even outperforming the normal
float data type. Sorry, not normal float data type and the regular float data type.
So but we can see that double quantization only leads to minor gains, but this allows for a more
fine-grained control over the memory footprint to fit models of a certain size.
These are also some results on the pile common crawl dataset, and this is the mean
per-pexity for different data types. And as we can see, normal float plus dynamic quantization
is outperforming the other methods. Now this is a comparison with 16-bit fine-tuning of
Roberta and T5 models from actually 80 million to 11 billion. And now they're asking the question,
can the lost performance in 4-bit inference be recovered by conducting 4-bit adapter fine-tuning?
So they have quantized transformers to 4-bits and they are comparing the inference.
So in their method, they have connected 4-bit adapter fine-tuning with other methods,
they have not performed this adapter fine-tuning and only doing 4-bit inference. So as we can see,
we observe that for both datasets, we observe that 16-bit, 8-bit, and 4-bit adapter methods
replicate the performance of the fully fine-tuned 16-bit base model.
This suggests that the performance loss due to the imprecise quantization can be fully recovered
through adapter fine-tuning after quantization. And now discussing clora with chatbot state of
the art. And as you can see, Guanaco is the model that they have used with clora. And as we can see,
the mean accuracy or zero-shot accuracy, this model is outperforming all the other models.
So we can safely say that it is possible to fine-tune a quantized 4-bit model without any
performance degradation. These are also some results with the different sizes of Lama fine-tuned
and the corresponding datasets. And as we can see, all of the results are very comparable
to the Lama with no fine-tuning results.
Now moving on to our next paper, BitNet scaling one-bit transformers for large-language models.
This is pretty surprising to read at first about having one-bit transformers.
So we will go into the detail of this paper and see how they're actually implementing this.
This is a very interesting paper. So now this is a scalable and stable one-bit transformer
architecture. They introduce BitLinear. They basically convert nn.linear layer,
the linear layer of the neural network into a BitLinear layer. And that is
created to train one-bit weights from scratch. So they are performing training from scratch,
but they are using one-bit transformers. So a one-bit precision for the weights.
So they are directly training on the one-bit precision weights rather than
reducing the precision after training. Now some of the key innovations of this paper
are quantization-aware training. So these models perform well even when their weights are limited
to one-bit representation. And in contrast to other models where they quantize models
after training, so they are quantizing during training. So the training happens with those
one-bit representation of the weights during runtime. So they're also deploying different
optimization techniques such as model parallelism with high precision for optimizer states and
gradients and employing large learning rates to handle the challenges with training low precision
weights. Now this is an architecture diagram. This is the detail of the BitLinear layer.
And this is the overall architecture. They will basically replace the linear layers with BitLinear
layers. The input comes in, a layer normalization is performed, and then absmax quantization is
performed to convert the weights into one-bits. And then that is decontized and the output is
produced. And each of the, there are, there's like two blocks of the BitLinear layer in every
feed-forward network. And they are followed by a Gal U. And the BitLinear, like in every,
in the attention projection layers, in the attention layers, in the feed-forward layers,
BitLinear is applied to convert the weights into one-bit. So the novelty of BitLinear basically
lies in its ability to maintain the training stability and model accuracy even with the
extreme quantization of weights to one-bit. So which is obviously not commonly found in other methods.
Now, the weights are basically binarized using a sine function, which assigns minus one or one
based on the weight sign. So if a weight is greater than zero, it's given a value of one. And if
it's less than zero, then it's assigned a value of minus one. So a scaling factor is computed to
minimize the difference between the binarized weights and the original weights. So the weights
during computation, they are minus one and one. And then a scaling factor is computed for during
the decontization procedure to minimize the difference between the binarized weights and
the original weights. The activation functions are quantized to 8-bit precision for the tensor
during training and per token during inference for efficiency and stability. So weights are quantized
to one-bit and activation functions are quantized to 8-bit during training. And during inference,
it's quantized per token. Now, these BitLinear weights, they are binarized and then they are
centralized to have zero mean. So basically, once we get a weight, we first centralize that to have
a zero mean. And then we will get its sign plus one or minus one. And then a post and then a scaling
factor is applied post binarization to align with the original weight distribution.
The activation functions in BitLinear are quantized to B-bit precision. In these experiments,
they have been quantized to 8-bit precision abs max while ensuring the outputs variance is
maintained for stability. This is done by scaling to the range and performing layer norm.
And activations before non-linear functions are scaled into the range zero and Q8 by subtracting
the minimum of the inputs that all values are non-negative.
For the full precision computation, the variance of the output
the variance of the output is at the scale of one with standard initialization methods,
sample climbing or heavier initialization, which has a great benefit to the training stability.
So to preserve the variance after quantization, they introduce a layer norm function before the
activation quantization. So in this way, the variance of the output y is estimated as
just the expected value of the ln function, expected value of the ln function,
which is equal to one. So BitLinear uses this variance for its layer norm calculations.
They also perform model parallelism using group quantization and normalization. So they partition
the matrix multiplication on multiple devices and that's how they do the model parallelism.
But there is a problem with that. All of the parameters which we discussed over here and
for our matrix multiplications, alpha, beta and all, they are calculated from the whole tensors.
And so these tensors are not independent along the partition dimension. So what they do is they
divide the weights and activations into groups and then independently estimate each group's parameters.
So for a weight matrix w, we will divide it into g groups along the partition dimension
and we then estimate the parameters for each group independently.
And this formula is indicating that for each group g, that for each group g of
weights in the matrix w, we calculate the scaling factor and normalization factors
based on the values within that specific group. So this allows for localized calculations within
each group, facilitating model parallelism without the need for extensive synchronization
across different parts of the network. So this reduces network IO while performing model parallelism.
So during training, they use a straight-through estimator, mixed precision training and a large
learning rate. So what a straight-through estimator does is it uses a method that bypasses
this non-differentiable functions to approximate the gradients during back propagation. So
basically, since we know that our weights are just one bit, if we allow that to pass through our
back propagation, that is going to reduce our weights. So that's going to mess up our upgrade
basically. So straight-through estimator, it estimates the gradients of a function.
As specifically, it ignores the derivative of the threshold function and passes on the incoming
gradient as if the function was an identity function. So basically, when we binarize the
weights, their gradient becomes zero. So during back propagation, we just bypass the
binarization function and directly pass the incoming gradient to the next layer.
So one challenge for the optimization is that a small update on the latent weights
often makes no difference in the one-bit weights. So this results in a biased gradient,
an update, which are estimated based on the one-bit weights, especially at the beginning
of the training. So a straight-through estimator ignores those threshold layer and just passes
directly on the next layer. They also deploy mixed precision training. So they use both low
precision quantization for weights and high precision storage for optimizer states and
gradients to maintain training stability and accuracy. They also employ a large learning
rate to overcome the insensitivity to one-bit weights to small updates, which helps in achieving
faster convergence and compensates for achieving faster, compensates for initial training phase
challenges. Now, discussing the energy consumption of BitNet, there's a huge
bump in the energy consumption. As you can see, matrix multiplication, but let's say
m multiplied by n and n multiplied by b. These are two matrices, vanilla transformers. The
expected energy consumption will be the product of these dimensions, while BitNet
uses a sum of these products. So this is like a big bump. So this BitNet chains one-bit
transformers from scratch. So it obtains competitive results in an energy-efficient way.
So in the next slide, we can see some of these results. So BitNet significantly
outperforms state-of-the-art quantization methods. And as the model size scales up,
the cost of savings becomes more significant. The difference becomes more significant
while achieving competitive performance with the models trained with floating point 16. So
as you can see over here, let's compare our 30 billion parameter model and the energy difference
is just huge for between 32-bit and even 16-bit. So BitNet uses only a small fraction of the
energy that other quantization methods and regular methods use.
Now, these are some zero-shot results.
They are comparing the inference energy consumption with the accuracy. And as we can see,
BitNet is outperforming the FP16 transformer significantly. The accuracy is comparable or
actually even slightly greater, while the energy consumption is much less.
Now, this is some comparison with FP16 transformers. And they are comparing the loss this time. So as we
can see, BitNet achieves a significantly better loss. And while the inference cost is much smaller,
to get the same performance as the FP16 transformers.
These are also some results. As we can see, if we actually try to perform quantization to just
one bit, BitNet has, it's the only one that's using training bits for the weights,
just one bit for training weights, for training as well as inference. And we can see the, if we
compare the accuracy of, if we just interpolate one bit weights and we interpolate the accuracy,
then BitNet is really, really, it's actually performing as good as, almost as good as 8-bit
weights. And as the model size increases, the energy cost reduction ratio increases by 38.8x
for 30 million parameter model. So in this table, I think we've already discussed.
Moving on, so with some more downstream tasks, with the, it's, BitNet is more stable than FP16
transformer with the same learning rate. We can see we employ a very large learning rate for
BitNet to account for the small, the really small weights. So if, if comparing it to an FP16
transformer, it's, it's like the FP16 transformer can even perform at all at this learning rate.
And these are also some different, different learning rates deployed and the perplexity
is compared. So this learning rate actually performs best with the lowest perplexity.
So this means that a large learning rate results in better convergence.
Now, this is some comparison with post-training quantization. And as we can see, BitNet
outperforms all of these post-training quantization methods.
While, and it's, it's actually the one that's closest to the regular transformer,
transformer with 16-bit weights and 16-bit activations. So, and as compared to that,
BitNet only has one bit weights and eight bit activations. These are some zero short and few
short results. And as we can see, BitNet performs best among all of these.
And these are also some more results with different data sets. And as we can see,
BitNet performs best in all of these tables. And they also have,
yeah, it's, it has the highest or pretty comparable accuracy among all data sets.
Now, so the key takeaways from this paper is that BitNet achieves competitive performance
and task outcomes while greatly reducing the memory and energy demands compared to traditional
models. It follows a similar scaling law as full precision models. So this indicates strong
potential for scaling up further in size. So fusion plans for this paper include
including the size and training steps of BitNet and exploring its application and other architectures.
This is a comparison chart that I've made discussing the four quantization procedures
that we, I have discussed. So as we can see, as far as precision is concerned,
LLM is 8-bit quantization, 8-bit optimizers are 8-bit quantization as well.
Chlora is 4-bit and then BitNet is 1-bit bits while we had 8-bit activations.
The techniques to use are vector-wise and mixed precision decomposition.
8-bit optimizers use block-wise quantization and dynamic double quantization of a double quantization
and also quantization of optimizer states. Chlora uses double, sorry, 8-bit optimizers use
dynamic quantization of optimizer states and Chlora uses double quantization and
based optimizers as well as the normal flow, the new data type. And BitNet uses a bit linear layer
and group quantization. The key innovation for LLMinted is that it maintains full precision
performance with 8-bit bits. 8-bit optimizers preserve optimizer performance
and Chlora enables large, large model fine tuning on the standard hardware and GPU
and BitNet skills transformers with just one bit precision. LLMinted experiments were done up to
175 billion parameters. Chlora used up to 65 billion parameters and BitNet just used general
large language models but they've added in the future work to use larger models.
LLMinted has no degradation. 8-bit optimizers are very comparable to 32-bit optimizers and
Chlora is also very close to state-of-the-art models and BitNet is competitive and comparable
to full precision transformers. LLMinted efficiency is that it reduces memory footprint by 50%.
8-bit optimizers also do significant memory savings and Chlora does efficient fine
tuning on limited resources and limited GPUs and BitNet reduces memory and energy consumption
by a big margin. The applications of LLMinted just include general large-scale LLMs
and 8-bit optimizers are optimizers for various tasks, not just large language models or
transformers and Chlora does fine tuning of large language models and BitNet is for training
large language models with using only a fraction of the memory and energy. So yeah, this is the
end of my presentation.