Hi, I'm Cole Wyatt.
And I'm Carter Blair.
And we'll be presenting on scaling laws.
So we'll begin by giving some information about scaling laws, kind of, we'll go over
the paper that introduced it, and then some follow up results.
And then we'll talk about immersion abilities, which call into question a little bit, kind
of, the idea of smooth scaling laws.
And then we'll talk about some other results that also complicate the story about immersion
abilities.
So there's a few motivations to be interested in this.
The first one is the scientific problem, which is actually studying how the model performance
changes with increasing scale.
So this is something we can address experimentally, and we can try to extract some underlying
trends and test hypotheses.
Then there's obviously some significant engineering importance.
So training frontier models is becoming increasingly expensive, costing sometimes millions of dollars
for a single training run.
So it's very important to be able to predict the optimal way to set the size and the number
of training tokens for your models just to save money for the same performance.
And finally, there's some AI safety importance.
So, so models have often demonstrated these unexpected emergent abilities.
We'd like to have some tools to tell us what level of capability we should expect the next
generation of frontier models to be at.
And this could give us some, some early warnings about maybe when it's time to slow down or
make preparations for certain kinds of risks.
Okay, so we'll begin by talking about Kaplan 2020.
And this was the paper that kind of introduced scaling laws.
And the main question, the main thing they were trying to look at is, is there a relationship
between kind of your inputs, so compute data or the number of parameters and the performance
of the model.
And so the main idea here was that they just train models of vastly different scales in
terms of both, in terms of data compute and the number of parameters.
And then the, they find that the final loss is predictable.
And it's related to the scale of each underlying input.
And they offer a predictive framework for predicting the final loss given these inputs.
And they make certain practical recommendations about how big your network should be with
a certain amount of data.
They also find that you shouldn't train to convergence and they find a critical batch
size.
So their main results are that performance depends strongly on scale and weakly on model
shape.
I'll go through these quickly and we'll go into more depth later.
Performance scales with each of compute data and the number of parameters when not bottlenecked
by the other two.
Performance improves predictably if we, predictably if we scale the number of parameters and the
amount of data in tandem.
But if we stop increasing one of those, we're going to get diminishing returns.
Also training curves are predictable.
So if we see the initial part of a training curve, we can roughly predict what the final
loss is going to be, which can be super useful if you want to figure out how much data or
how many parameters you want to use to get a certain final amount of loss.
So we can predict how well models are going to perform on out of distribution data only
by looking at the validation accuracy on the training data.
So there's this kind of reliable transfer and large models are more sample efficient
than small ones and convergence is super inefficient.
They also find this critical batch size and it's roughly a power of only the loss.
So to begin model performance depends mostly on scale.
So we can see here in the bottom plot that we look at varying kind of different model
parameters and then we can see kind of the relationship that has with loss.
And overall, like especially for the attention head dimension, it like really doesn't matter.
You're going to get about the same amount of loss for any attention head dimension.
As for aspect ratio and the feed forward ratio, there's a bit more of a relationship
between those and the final loss, but it's still overall quite weak compared to the relationship
with scale.
So just as a note moving forward, a lot of the graphs look like they have a linear trend,
but they just look like that because a power law is going to show up linearly on a log
scale graph.
So this is kind of one of the main figures and the finding is that loss predictably goes
down as you scale compute data set size and the number of parameters.
But importantly, these graphs all assume that when you're varying say compute, you're not
bottlenecked by the data size or the number of parameters.
So these test loss smoothly decreases in terms of one of these factors when not bottlenecked
by the other two.
So they also find that as you can see, training curves kind of follow these predictable patterns
and the parameters are roughly independent of the model size.
So for a relatively small model, the first purple line, the shape is roughly similar
to that final yellow line, which is a model with a billion parameters.
And so by extrapolating that early part of a training curve, we can roughly predict what
loss we can achieve by training for much longer.
They also found that the transfer of models is quite predictable.
So here we see the test loss on the training distribution on the x-axis and the loss on
some other distribution on the y-axis.
And roughly there's some linear relationship between these.
So as you decrease loss on the training distribution, you can expect to decrease loss on other distributions
as well.
They also found that large models are much more sample efficient than small models.
So they can reach the same level of performance with fewer optimization steps.
So here we can see if we have some fixed data set size, say a billion tokens in the data
set, the larger models achieve significantly lower loss than these smaller models.
Yeah.
And the reason could be because these large models, while they're taking maybe the same,
they're seeing the same amount of tokens, they have many more parameters.
So that is in a way costing much more compute to see that same amount of data.
And hence, but hence they learn more.
They also show that convergence is inefficient.
So when working within a fixed compute budget and without any other restrictions on the
model size or available data, so you just assume you have like infinite storage and
this massive infinite data set, or just big enough that it's not going to bottleneck you
at all, that you can attain optimal performance by training very large models and stopping
significantly short of convergence.
So for example, if we look at this orange line and we say, let's say we have this much
compute and the lowest intercept on this line from one of the training curves comes
from a model that's very far from convergence.
So if we were to train the smallest model to convergence, we might achieve like six
loss.
Whereas if we train just a huge model or a much bigger model with the same amount of
compute, we can achieve somewhere around five units of loss.
So they also found that performance improves predictively as long as we scale up the number
of parameters and the amount of data in tandem, but we get diminishing returns if either of
those is held fixed while the other increases.
And the performance penalty depends predictively on this ratio of the number of parameters
to the power of 0.74 over the amount of tokens in the data set.
And every time we increase the model size by eight times, we only need to increase the
data size by roughly five times to avoid a penalty.
However, this like particular relationship is later called into question.
As I think we'll see in the next paper presented.
Yeah, two papers from now.
And they also found this kind of ideal batch size for training models, and it's roughly
a power of the loss only and it continues to be determinable by measuring the gradient
noise scale, and it's roughly one to two million tokens at convergence for the largest
models we can train.
So yeah, the idea is that you might need, if your gradient is super noisy, you kind
of maybe want to have bigger batches so that you get a more reliable direction.
So the main takeaways from Kaplan are that the loss scales predictably with model scale.
So you can kind of predict what the loss will be just by looking at the scale of the model
and the model shape.
So the feed forward ratio, the aspect ratio, or the dimension of the attention heads just
doesn't really matter.
Like it matters to some extent, but the main driver of increasing performance is scale.
And the amount of embedding parameters doesn't really matter.
And we can predict the final loss of a model based on only the early part of a training
curve.
So this is nice as Cole mentioned from an engineering perspective.
We want to figure out how big our models should be to achieve some certain loss.
And you can kind of run a bunch of little training runs to kind of predict what the
final loss will be for your final full training run.
And they also found, importantly, that training these models to convergence is inefficient.
You can do much better by just training a bigger model, not all the way to convergence.
And they found this ideal batch size, which is a power of loss only and doesn't depend
on the model size.
OK, so after this work came out, people are interested in whether they could find similar
scaling laws for transfer, because typically a large foundation model is fine tuned for
some kind of downstream task.
So this is a practical importance.
What Kaplan had all found in 2021 was that pre-training can be particularly valuable
when the fine tuning data set is not very large, and which is kind of natural if the
fine tuning data set is larger than the pre-training data set, then the pre-training data set is
just kind of injecting out of distribution noise.
They were also able to model this effective data transfer from the pre-training with another
power law, and they used this measurement to construct a measure of similarity between
data sets, which comes from one of the parameters in their power law.
So it's sort of the idea being that you can measure how close one data set is to another
based on how useful the pre-training is.
And finally, they looked at ossification, which is the idea that pre-training could
actually reduce performance.
OK, so this power law is a little bit confusing, so it's kind of worth taking a close look
at this graph, maybe pausing the video.
But the idea is that with some amount of fine-tuning data, DF, which is provided to a pre-trained
model, we can see how far ahead the pre-trained model is compared to a model which is trained
from scratch.
So both models get this fine-tuning data set of size DF, but one, the pre-trained model
also has access to some pre-training data.
And by measuring how many additional tokens of fine-tuning data need to be, or I guess
in this case, characters, need to be trained on by both models, or by the trained from
scratch model to catch up with the pre-trained model so that horizontal line, then we see
how much the effective data has been transferred to the pre-trained model.
So that's the advantage that it gets from the pre-training, and it's DT.
So here N represents the non-embedding model parameters.
We saw earlier that the number of embedding model parameters doesn't matter that much,
and in the last paper.
And then we see this, we have the scaling law where the effective data transferred is
related by a power law to constant times the amount of fine-tuning data to the alpha
and times the number of parameters to the beta.
So beta doesn't depend on the data sets, it depends only on the model architecture, which
is one useful result that this can kind of be factored out.
And then the K and alpha depends on the data set, and you'll see that actually a smaller
alpha indicates more closely related data sets, because when the alpha is smaller, we
have gained more, we've kind of already factored in more advantage from the pre-training.
So a smaller alpha will correspond to a larger K, which means that there's a more significant
head start before we even start seeing fine-tuning data.
So then with a more dissimilar fine-tuning data set, there's kind of more rapid gains
from this fine-tuning data, because the fine-tuning data looks different from the pre-training
data.
So then they compare the similarity of text to Python and 50% Python code, 50% text to
Python, and propose this alpha as a similarity measurement, and you can see that it's a lot
smaller in the second case with a much larger K.
So lastly, so this concern about ossification, you can see that sometimes the pre-training
does hurt, but only when the model size is relatively small compared to the amount of
the training data.
So the takeaways are that the scaling laws continue to be pervasive, show up all over
the place, in transfer learning as well as in pre-training, that pre-training can have
significant benefits, particularly when it's hard to find fine-tuning data, and that it's
possible for pre-training to hurt, but only when there's very little data available, or
when the model size is very small compared to the amount of data.
Okay.
So after these results came out, there was this theoretical investigation by Hutter of
how the observed scaling laws could be explained mathematically.
So this is coming from the fact that usually in statistical learning theory, you expect
scales of learning to have exponents of, in power laws that have exponents of one-half
or one, so yeah, particularly the normal, yeah, so normally when you see a number of
examples, for instance, the standard deviation scales down as one over square root of n, so
this is what you'd typically expect, but the power laws in Kaplan at all had values of
the exponents that were lower than one-half, and Hutter tried to explain this with infinitely
parameterized models, and he was able to find some models that matched this behavior.
One thing that he, and possibly they mentioned, but didn't pursue was trying to scale the
model size up with the amount of data, which is more in line with what's actually happening
in practice, but looks less analytically tractable.
In any case, after this paper came out, and then the next paper actually found that the
ordinary exponent one-half scaling laws came back, and that the lower values were kind
of a methodological error, which is what maybe should have been expected, though it's
worth noting that maybe this doesn't fit the exact ordinary circumstances of learning theory
because of the changes in model size.
So kind of as a response to the papers by Kaplan at all, this paper training compute
optimal large language models came out from Hoffman et al. in 2022, and they were trying
to answer pretty much exactly the same question, maybe with a slightly different focus, which
is on what is the optimal trade-off between model size and number of tokens given a fixed
compute budget.
So they were trying to maybe approach this from more of an engineering lens, but it was
the exact same problem, still looking for scaling laws to inform how to spend compute
between tokens and parameters.
And what they found was that models were actually significantly under-trained, perhaps because
people were following the scaling strategies suggested by Kaplan, and it would be better
to train them closer to convergence.
And in fact, this model size and the number of trained tokens should be scaled equally,
so this should be scaled up by the same proportions with each other.
And in particular, it's kind of a practical demonstration of this.
They introduced this Chinchill model, which outperformed the larger Gopher model by training
on more tokens, even though it was a much smaller model.
So the main methodological detail that they fixed was that the learning rate schedule should
depend on the number of tokens.
So this was just a knob that I guess Kaplan would almost have forgotten to turn as they
were trying different settings of their hyperparameters, which is kind of maybe a natural error.
But normally, when you know how many tokens you're going to be training on, you'd probably
be likely to choose your learning rate schedule based on that.
So by doing this properly, they were able to get kind of more value out of their training
tokens, which then led to them recommending that you train more tokens and scale down
the model size.
And this rule doesn't really depend on the model size.
So explicitly, their goal was to find the optimal parameter count and token count, given
a fixed compute budget, which they expressed as this optimization problem.
And they tried three fairly similar approaches to estimating those values.
So first of all, they tried various learning rate schedules for each parameter count, which
is how they probably departed from Kaplan's results.
So in their first approach, they trained several models of different parameter size.
And for a given compute level, they just checked which combination of parameter size and number
of tokens had been optimal.
And then they fit both of those separately as power loss.
So for instance, if you look at the leftmost chart, just imagine finding the point, which
is the lowest on that curve, and then they extracted from that the optimal values for
the training tokens and the parameters corresponding to the color and the, yeah, I guess, I guess
in this case, maybe that's only showing the one, yeah, only showing the values of one
parameter.
But in any case, it's kind of a simple estimation problem.
So then they, for the second approach, they did almost exactly the same thing.
They just trained each model to completion to with a certain fixed amount of compute
and then compared which ones did the best.
And then again, they fit each of these values and they obtained almost exactly the same
exponents with approach two as with approach one.
So both were almost exactly one half for the exponents of both the number of parameters
and the amount of data.
And finally, they tried to minimize, they tried to fit a model that took into account
both the parameters and token counts at once and kind of fit them jointly.
And this is a slightly different approach.
They got slightly different values for the exponents, but still pretty close to one half.
Okay, so their conclusion from this was that with GoFers compute budget, a smaller model
should have been trained in more tokens and they put their money where their mouth was
and actually did it and trained Chinchilla, which was a 70 billion parameter model with
trained on 1.4 trillion tokens, which I think kind of blew out of the water the amount of
training data that anyone had used prior to that.
And some advantage of this, well, first of all, it turned out to have better performance,
but it also had reduced inference time and fine tuning time because it's a smaller model.
So it's a more lightweight approach as well because, yeah, so the training costs were
fixed, the kind of inference time costs were then saving on the inference time costs.
And you can see a head-to-head comparison of these models in terms of their hyperparameters
here, in particular, the GoFers model is significantly larger.
Okay, and then here we have various comparisons between the two.
Everywhere that's in the blue is a task where Chinchilla is outperforming GoFers on the top
left and then they also had some few shot tasks where Chinchilla outperformed GoFers
as well.
So the takeaways were that data and parameters should be scaled together.
They still don't recommend training models all the way to convergence.
They just recommend training for longer, closer to convergence than Kaplan had all suggested.
And yeah, I guess the final takeaway is to pay attention to the learning rate schedule.
Okay.
Okay, so now we'll kind of change gears.
So we talked about these nice smooth scaling curves so you could predict the performance
of a model very cleanly from the amount of compute and the size of the model, the amount
of data, and then emergent abilities kind of come along and they kind of throw a wrench
in that.
So at all 2022 looks at emergent abilities and their main research question is just basically
a survey of all these different emergent abilities and they kind of talk about some potential
causes of these emergent abilities.
So yeah, in the original scaling laws paper we have a figure from the left where it's
compute goes up, loss goes down, it's a very smooth relationship.
And then on the right hand side we see emergent abilities.
So here it's like you increase compute and the accuracy of doing modular arithmetic just
like is flat, it's zero until you kind of hit this magic, 10 to the 22 flops and all
of a sudden performance just shoots up.
So it's not a smooth relationship at all.
It's just kind of this like certain point where capabilities just kind of like really
quickly increase.
And they find a bunch of these kind of emergent abilities.
So some of the tasks are from Big Bench and yeah.
So they take a closer look at kind of what could be causing this and they kind of talk
about how some of these tasks are just like inherently discontinuous.
So for example, on exact string matching, a model might give an output that's like absolutely
nothing like the target output.
So if you're trying to get the model to say hello and it just outputs like a random string,
it's going to get a score of zero.
And then some of you try to like a bigger model and you try to get it to output just
hello and it outputs H-E-L-L-U.
It's like pretty close.
It's almost like the exact output you want, but it's like just a little bit off and that
still gets a score of zero.
So there's really like no differentiation between these two outputs, even though like
qualitatively the second one is like much better and then like a perfect response gets
a one.
So you kind of like there's this just very discontinuous metric.
So maybe they say that some of these tasks are hiding information that cross-entropy
loss is capturing and maybe this is why you see the smooth relationship between the amount
of compute and cross-entropy loss, but this very discontinuous relationship between the
amount of compute and some of these tasks.
But they kind of say maybe this isn't the case because emergent abilities are observed
on classification tasks as well.
But I think, yeah, I think we'll get into this later, but these classification tasks
also hide some degree of information.
So they also look at the relationship between perplexity and emergent abilities.
They think maybe there's some relationship there.
So just as a quick intro, perplexity is basically how surprised a model is by text.
So for example, we see a high perplexity on this high perplexity row.
The model has like even once it's already seen say the quick brown, it's still the pretty
surprised by Fox.
I think it only thought Fox was coming next was say a probability of 0.05.
So it wasn't really expecting Fox to come next, even though that's something that it's
a real utterance and it's a very common utterance.
However, if the model had low perplexity, by the time it's seen the quick brown Fox, it's
almost certain or by the time it's seen the quick brown, it's pretty certain that Fox
is going to be next.
So when Fox appears, it's not surprised.
And they plot.
So here on the plots, we see on the on the far left hand side, we see compute and performance
on MLU and we see it's kind of it's got this emergent ability at about 10 to 22 flops.
And we also see this on the middle plot with the number of parameters at about 10 billion
parameters, performance just shoots up and kind of, I guess, disappointingly, the same
as true for the relationship between perplexity and accuracy.
It's like, once perplexity kind of reduces to a certain level or yeah, reduces to a certain
level, you kind of just see this like huge jump on performance on MLU.
So there's like, again, kind of not smooth relationship between perplexity and performance
on MLU.
So overall, immersion abilities should probably be viewed as a function of many related variables.
It's not, they're not just, as we've seen, like a function of how much compute you throw
at it.
And the analysis they do doesn't really get to the bottom of why these abilities emerge.
And even though we can predict the loss just by using like the model scale or the amount
of data and compute, we can't use the loss to predict what abilities a model might have,
which could have important safety implications if you can kind of, you kind of never know
what a model is going to be able to do, just given the loss it achieves.
Okay.
So then this paper by Schaefer et al. in 253 asked if immersion abilities were a mirage.
So they try to argue that the apparently sudden emergence of new abilities in large language
models actually results from the metrics chosen to measure them.
So in other words, there's kind of no real discontinuity and ability.
It's just discontinuity in the measurement chosen by the researcher.
So kind of arguing this out explicitly, if you choose a nonlinear discontinuous metric,
for instance, the accuracy on a full word or a complete response, as Carter discussed,
you can show this sudden jump when a linear continuous metric would not show any jump.
They argue this explains the claims of emergence on published benchmarks in the vast majority
of instances, and they try to drive this point home.
Then they try to produce apparently emergent abilities of their own by changing the choice
of metric to something that's discontinuous or nonlinear.
So in particular, they look at these big bench tasks, and they find that over 92% of the immersion
abilities on big bench come from one of these two metrics, the multiple choice grade,
which requires that the highest probability mass is on the correct option or exact string match,
which is one if the output string exactly matches the target string.
So the multiple choice grade is clearly discontinuous.
There's a discontinuity when two options have the same probability mass,
and exact string match, they look into how this changes with the models per token accuracy.
So as kind of a theoretical model, they assume a standard scaling law on the cross-entropy
loss on a per token basis, and they show that there's this nasty kind of exponential relationship
with between the accuracy and this per token correctness.
So then they argue that if taking many samples from a poor model,
you might never see a perfect match. So you'd have to take many more samples than
might typically be taken just to observe any instances of correct behavior, which seems to
indicate that the model doesn't have an ability at all, when in fact it's just maybe it's making
progress towards having that ability, but it doesn't get every token right.
So what they suggest is using the token edit distance instead, which has a much less nasty relationship.
Well, yeah, so instead of scaling with this kind of power of the number of tokens,
it's just multiplicative with the number of tokens.
This position is a exponential. So they look at some examples. So for instance,
the InstructGPT or GPT-3 family is supposed to have emergent earth particularities,
but by switching from exact string match token edit distance as they suggested,
these abilities appear gradual instead of sudden.
So, yeah. So they, so the takeaways from this are that most of the cases of emergent abilities
are just depend on the metric. And then I haven't gone, I didn't go into this much,
but by, this is kind of a toy model, but by deliberately choosing a core metric for a vision
task, they're able to induce this apparently emergent behavior. And it's, but it's also worth
noting that some candidate emergent abilities did remain. For instance, the blue and normalized
aggregate score metrics that were not notably discontinuous or nonlinear, and they still show
these sudden sharp increases in performance. Okay.
Okay. So then way at all looks at when inverse scaling can become U-shaped. So
I'll start by looking at inverse scaling and kind of what that is. And then
I'll talk about U-shaped scaling. So the main question here is over what scales does
inverse scaling on certain tasks hold? So Mackenzie 2022 held this competition to
find tasks where bigger models performed worse. And they were able to find 11 tasks
for smaller models ended up performing much better than like much larger, like an order of
magnitude larger models. And one of these tasks was the modus tolens classification. So modus
tolens is this, the structure is just if P then Q, not Q, therefore not P. And present, present
models with a mold, they present models with a modus tolens argument, not just the logical
structure, but like an actual example and ask whether it's valid. And so humans often make
mistakes on this. They think it's invalid when it's actually valid. So what they find is that
kind of their hypothesis is that these smaller models kind of learn to imitate humans.
But the larger models kind of learn to correct the fallacy. So way at all 2022 looked at these 11
tasks. And they found that if you keep increasing scale even further, eventually, the performance
will go up again. And this held almost across the board for all of the 11 tasks. And so you
can see modus tolens is shown in the little green highlighted box. And so when they trained this
palm model with as they trained it more or increase the size, it starts by going down at first and
then eventually starts going up. So they kind of explain this. I'll quote the paper here. They say
we do not experimentally investigate how or why U shape scaling occurs, but we hypothesize that it
can happen when a task contains a distractor task. And so this distractor task, as I mentioned before
with this modus tolens, it's the distractor task is kind of imitating humans flawed reasoning. And
then this the true task which you wanted the model to do is to tell you whether a modus tolens
is accurate. But these smaller smaller models kind of get distracted by the task of imitating
humans fallacies. So even large models on some of these tasks can perform at random. So inverse
scaling occurs where performance begins random and then goes to worse than random and then the U
shape scaling can kind of bring the performance eventually back up to random. But random is still
not great performance. It's really bad. So these inverse scaling tasks aren't solved, but I guess
the narrative here is that there's some hope that if you just keep scaling up, maybe performance will
keep going up. They look at a couple of ways to kind of improve performance on these inverse
scaling tasks. And in particular, they look at using in context learning with so giving the model
an example of doing the task correctly. And they also look at prompting the model to perform
chain of thought reasoning. And they find pretty much across the board that if you use, if you give
the model an example, I guess, yeah, it helps performance, I guess, a little bit. However,
if you give it an example and prompt the model to engage in chain of thought reasoning, then
it helps performance quite a bit. And it almost across the board gets the model across the board.
Yeah, it gets the model to above average. So the main takeaways here that increasing scale
can turn these inverse scaling, these instances of inverse scaling into U shape scaling.
And inverse scaling may not be a big issue because for a lot of these tasks, like the
performance eventually started to improve. But there's still room for improvement.
Like I just mentioned, even scaling up to like 540 billion parameters still maybe only gets you
to random performance on some of these tasks. And maybe just using techniques like one shot
prompting and chain of thought can help. So the next paper looks at
if we can kind of transcend scaling laws or get better than predicted performance by just using
new training techniques. So they propose this new training procedure where they first take
the palm base model, and then they use an extra 0.1% compute on the same data to train with an
objective that just combines prefix language modeling and longshore span corruption. So an
infilling task and infilling tasks are basically where you're not getting, you're not, you're
taking out words or sequences from the middle of the string and getting the model to kind of
infill that. So it has context on either side as opposed to prefix language modeling,
where the context only comes at the start. And in particular, they kind of use a mixture of
denoisers for this infilling task. And this involves regular denoising. So the noise is just
sampled as spans or sequences and replaced with sentinel tokens. And these spans are
uniformly sampled with a mean of three, a mean length of three and a corruption
rate of 15% overall. And they also use extreme denoising where the corruption rate is up to
50% and the spans of missing tokens can be up to a length of 32. They also look at sequential
denoising where noise is always sampled from the start of the text to a randomly sampled point
in the text. And they find that this method is just like way better than only using prefix
language modeling. So they get huge compute savings. So for the 540 billion parameter model,
the savings are approximately 2x. So this is equivalent to training or equivalent to
saving about four and a half million TPU hours. And so you can kind of look at these graphs
in two ways. In the graph on the left, we can say, okay, say we have a fixed compute budget of
three, the 23 training flops. If you use this kind of training method proposed by Tay et al,
you can get, let's say, your score goes out by like quite a bit. So your performance on these
NLP tasks, kind of, you can see there's like a noticeable improvement. But you can also look
at it from another way. And you can say, say we want to get a certain level of performance,
how much training are we going to need to get that level of performance? And this is where you
kind of get that 2x number. So as you say you want to get 66, this metric of 66 on these NLP tasks.
And if you use UPOM, you can do it with about half the training as less than half of the training
as would be required with just the typical POM training without this kind of extra infilling
training. So the main takeaways here that maybe scaling laws only hold for autoregressive training
or prefix language modeling, and maybe it's, maybe if we come up with new training schemes
like UL2, we could get unexpected extra performance. So it's kind of, yeah, maybe model performance
isn't as predictable as we thought it was. That's, yeah, that's everything. And this is,
I'm just, you can't ask questions.
Oh, questions in my five minutes. Thanks for watching.
Yeah, thanks.
Hopefully this was helpful to people.