Hi, now let's start.
Today we are going to introduce those famous pre-trained models.
We will start from the question, why we need pre-training.
Normally, when a new task comes, we need to train a new model.
The drawbacks are, it is computation-expensive and consuming,
and it also requires a lot of storage space and annotated data.
There has been some solution like model compression, acceleration,
visual learning, which aims to solve these problems.
But the straightforward question is, whether we could do transfer learning?
So when a new task comes, they can only find part of the model with low data cost.
The goals for computer vision language modeling is similar.
The only difference is that their data modalities are different,
which leads to the difference in how their features are extracted.
It has already been widely applied.
We know that TITOS has absorbed many pre-trained models for computer vision,
like VGGFamily, ResNetFamily, InSectionFamily, MobileNetFamily, and so on.
These pre-trained models have already been developed and open to public since 2012,
as the computation in the image met gave the momentum.
From language modeling, the emergence of models like VIRT in 2018
has significantly impacted natural language processing tasks.
These models included here are the many models we will introduce today.
These models begin to emerge around 2019.
That was a promising year of NLP.
The next question is, where we can start from?
You know that there are many tasks in NLP.
Here we will provide a quick review on these tasks.
The first task is the complexity parsing.
The goal of this task is to understand the task.
It analyses the structure and syntax of the task,
breaking sentences into tree-like structures
to determine the dependency relationships between words.
These downstream applications include machine translation and question answering systems.
The goal of machine translation is to automatically translate tasks from one language to another.
The input is a source language test that needs to be translated,
and the output data is the translated task in the target language.
And the third task is the question answering.
Even though there are many kinds of methods for question answering,
the goal of question answering is to generate relevant answers to user queries
based on the given context or set of documents.
The input is a question or query and plus a context.
And then it will retrieve a set of documents which contains information that is relevant to the query.
And the output is the generated answer to the question.
Now, we came about the problem that if we need to train a pre-training model for a general language,
we need to train it on less equal amount of data.
However, many of these tasks are supervised tasks,
which requires extensive manual annotation, much like an image net.
Nevertheless, language data inherently possesses semantic information and coherence.
And we leverage these features to train an unsupervised training model.
Now, the researchers come out a task named the next word prediction.
The input of model is a sequence of tasks.
Then they go into the word embedding layer.
It lets each word in the input test to a dense vector representation.
Each word has a corresponding word embedding vector,
which captures the semantics and contextual information of the word.
Then they input the embedding vector into our transformer.
Then predicts the next word by learning patterns and context.
The model output is a probability distribution,
which represents the likelihood of each possible next word occurring in a given context.
The most common next word will have the highest probability in this probability distribution.
The next word prediction is inherently on unsupervised tasks.
Now coming to the word embedding layer,
the goal of word embedding is to map words from this great symbolic to a continuous vector space.
It aims to capture the semantic information on contextual relationships of words
so that similar words in the vector space have similar vector representation.
There are two traditional words embedding methods, continuous back of words and skip grand.
The simple goal is to predict a target word based on the surrounding words in the context.
The input consists of the surrounding words within a fixed size contextual,
typically a few words, and the output is the target word.
The symbol implies a shallow fit for word neural network architecture.
The input is the average of the word embedding vectors of the context words,
which is then passed through a hidden layer to predict the target word.
The skip grand model's objective is to predict the surrounding words in the context based on the target word.
The input in is the target word, and the output consists of the surrounding words.
And the skip grand uses a neural network architecture opposite to the symbol.
It maps the input to multiple outputs through a hidden layer.
Global vectors for word representations main goal is to learn word vector representation
based on global vocabulary statistics.
It constructs a vocabulary co-occurrence matrix with a complex window
and then learn the cinematic relationships between words.
Now we see another problem.
The word embedding vectors typically obtain from word to back and close aesthetic word embeddings,
and they are one-to-one projection.
Meaning each word has a fixed vector representation without considering context.
That means the usage of the learned embedding model is we can retrieve the embeddings for each word when we call the embedding layer.
But the problem is many words have polysomy issues.
A single word can have different meanings in different sentences.
For example, in the case of words, Python and Pandas, they can both represent the nearby PI leaves
and also refer to a kind of animal.
The way to solve this problem is the contextualized word embedding.
The primary goal of contextualized word embedding is to capture the schematic variations
and polysomy of words in different contexts.
The model uses all preceding words of the target word to predict the target word.
And intuition comes out.
Why do we not incorporate right content into input to predict the target word?
By incorporating more information in this manner, we can potentially enhance prediction accuracy.
However, it's crucial to be mindful of two important points.
The first concern is the issue of data leakage.
We cannot include the predicted word as input.
The second is the sequence structure.
We cannot mess it as the sequence order is important and contains some information.
So researchers developed bidirectional language models to solve this problem.
Here, the architecture is a little different than birth.
It consists of left to right and right to left to modules.
Not the same as birth consists of one whole module.
ELMO is the abbreviation of embeddings from language model.
The bidirectional language model is the foundation for ELMO.
The input is a sequence of tokens.
The language model learns to predict the profitability of next token given a history.
In the forward path, the history contains words before the target token.
The predictions in both directions are modeled by multi-layer LSTMs with hidden states.
Then these two kinds of hidden states goes into the sub-max localization.
The output of sub-max layer is the probabilities of word prediction.
The model is trained to minimize the negative log-likely hood,
which means to maximize the log-likely hood for true words in both directions.
Here, the parameter stands for LSTM, embedding layers, and sub-max layers.
We still have a question.
If we train on a supervised test, how it catches the representation
and will these features be effective enough for the downstream tasks?
So let's check the representation catch by ELMO training.
In ELMO, different layers of bi-LN produces different hidden states,
each containing different types of information about the test.
To utilize this information for downstream-specific tasks,
ELMO learns a task-specific linear combination that aggregates all layers of the hidden states.
Here, gamma and s are different types of hidden states.
Here, gamma and s are the parameters learned during downstream tasks on tuning.
Gamma is a scaling vector which is introduced to correct the mismatch
between the distribution of bi-LN hidden states and the distribution of task-specific representations.
s is the linear coefficient.
Learned for each end task and normalized by the sub-max to keep the constraint a sum to one.
The hidden representation learned by top layer in bi-LN module
contains much better representation for cinematic tasks.
This task enthuses the meaning of a word given a context.
The one learned by first layer is better for same task.
It infers a grammatical role of a word in one sentence.
Who knows, it's that after proving the capability of ELMO,
their researchers can stack information from different layers
together to help to improve variety of LLP tasks.
Then the question is, we have obtained the model.
Then how to apply to the downstream task?
Take those output embeddings and feed them into whatever architecture we want to use for specific tasks.
This is the first choice.
And the second choice is that one can update weights for their downstream specific network
but keep the ELMO parameters frozen.
The third one is that it depends on the performance.
If the performance is not good, then one might choose to find the whole model.
Here we can see massive improvements across six benchmark data sets.
The question answering and textual entitlement and so on.
We now answer the question, whether it solves the core problem of polysomy.
Let's take a look at the contrasting examples provided in the paper.
If we were to use the original globe word embeddings,
it based solely on the words embedding in space.
We would get many similar problems.
Not only including the core polysomy of play, but also varieties of installations of play.
However, if we were to use ELMO, it would search for genetically similar elements of play in some contexts.
For example, if it refers to the sparse game or stage performance, ELMO would only find the play with the same meaning.
However, ELMO contains some drawbacks.
It easily lists LSTN instead of transformer.
It has to be claimed that the transformer has better feature extraction capability than LSTN.
At that time, the transformer was actually proposed.
Someone claimed that if ELMO used transformer instead of LSTN, it might achieve better performance.
The next question is that, is ELMO enough as a pre-trained model?
Whether we just stick to ELMO as pre-trained model and leave the improving place for downstream tasks and their model training?
So, why we still pursue pre-training models?
This is an image from the superglue paper.
The main point of this image is to illustrate how much large language models underperform compared to elements underglue dataset.
Glue dataset is a benchmark.
It collects of diverse natural language understanding tasks.
These tasks are used to evaluate the performance of NLP models.
These tasks include the tasks we just mentioned for ELMO,
a sentiment classification, text matching, question pairing matching, and so on.
Each task has its own training and task being set,
so researchers can compare the first web capability of their models.
Here, each column stands for future language model.
Each point stands for the performance on this model, one specific task.
And the blue dotted line is the average of this model.
While the black line stands for the human performance.
So, the answer of our question is,
the initial ELMO model is far from reaching the level of human understanding of language task.
This is why researchers need to continue their efforts in pre-training language models.
We know that there are two earnings.
The first one developed by Baidu is enhanced representation through knowledge integration.
There inside is the random masking invert good enough.
We know that there exist some phrases where several words together represent meaning.
The strategy of granting masking can disrupt the integrity of phrases or words combinations.
Another problem is the generalization capability.
For example, previous, the model only see the Apple watch.
Now, as Apple has released Apple Vision Pro, can the model recognize it as a product of Apple?
Or it can generate embedding stands for these phrases,
so that embedding closes to other Apple products in embedding space.
So, they proposed whole word masking in time to mask entire words as units maintained the interpreting.
Then the first question is, to which level they need to mask?
There are two levels, face level and entity level.
For example, in face level, it will mask something like a series or they will mask a proportion of phrases in a sentence.
In entity level, it will mask JK Rowling, so they will mask out some name entities such as personal names, organization names, product names.
Comparing to basic level, the basic level randomly masks out one Chinese character in each word.
Then more questions generated.
Firstly, since this is an unsupervised learning, how did they recognize the entity and phrases to mask?
What we concern is whether they include other supervised information, whether they need extra information.
They use automatic part of speech tagging tool and name entity recognition tool like spacing,
well, JK, stand for NLP to identify the phrases and entity, so they can avoid human annotation.
The second question is, what is the relation between two levels?
The answer is, these three levels are masked unsequentially, first masked in basic level, then entity level and then phrase level,
so the final masked input includes all kinds of masks.
Lastly, how did they label the output?
Since it is contextual learning, the continuous mask of words won't affect training people.
The input output on that is just the same as birds.
For the architecture, learning is not a layer transformer as a basic encoder, just like what Judy and Bert did.
Learning also incorporates conversation data into training data, finally focusing on two aspects, reference relationships and cinematic consistency.
The motivation here is, for example, if we mask the words in the red line and only train on the last two sentences,
we won't know they present for laptops.
We also don't know what user is picking and buying.
If just give last two sentences to the model and fill in the blanks, it may directly output to buy a computer.
Let's check the performance.
It shows that it improves a little bit on this NLP task compared to birds.
Many of these tasks are for cross mingle because in Chinese, they always use multiple words.
We just take a glance because this paper is not our target.
This paper just had the same abbreviation with another earning.
Now, we consider another problem.
That for most current pre-training language models, they require a lot of computation resources.
How can we reduce the cost?
As we have mentioned, others might think about the data perspective, use future learning or know the perspective like model compression.
But currently, we are working on pre-training large language models.
We cannot consider trade-off between performance and time consumption.
We cannot sacrifice the performance.
So some researchers think that whether they can change the task after sequence generation task is quite time consuming.
Whether they can change the original sequence prediction to a binary classification task, this binary signal is whether this token has been replaced or changed.
For example, here two words are must.
And one is the, and another is eight.
It means that the chip might first cook the meal than 80.
So eight is a word that might be substituted.
Then a question comes out that whether this design is reasonable, whether a model train on discrimination task can substitute sequence-to-sequence pre-trained model.
The answer is that it is somewhat reasonable.
The discrimination task also requires the model to capture the grammical, semantic information in the given sentence.
For example, the difference between these two sentences is the verb.
So this word is of highly flexibility to be other words for the given context.
But for the word, it is of common usage to be used before or not.
So it is unlikely to be replaced.
So the language model needs to know how the words work here.
Then it can distinguish whether the word here is of highly flexibility.
Another perspective is that it is more like a side effect.
The language model can learn whether the word is not only the flexibility, but also prep usage here.
So it can be handled arrow and typos in some sentences inputted by the user.
Then we face a problem that again this is an unsupervised learning.
How can we generate the data without annotation?
The most straightforward method is to randomly sampling other words in corpus to substitute the target word.
But if we apply this method, then the native sample we obtained is not distinguishable.
It is meaningless.
Again, our target is to train a large language model which can represent meaningful information from sentences.
We also need to train a powerful discrimination model.
So we need to generate reasonable sequence data here.
Then what is the simplest method for this sequence generation task?
These researchers think about using a small bird to generate a sequence based on the mask's synced sentence.
So this is the lowest cost method to produce more distinguishable hair.
There are several problems also came up.
Whether it improves comparing to a single small bird, since it already trained on a pre-trained model.
If it just improves a little bit, then the total commutation cost will also surpass most training models.
Then it is not reasonable.
And the small question is that whether they will find to a small bird or just frozen up the small bird.
The answer is yes that they will find to on the model, but in a way to save the floating point operation.
So in order to compare the benchmark setting, they would compare the performance on Google data set with same floating point operations.
We will check this later in the performance part.
Another question is that if the output of this model is binary signal, then how do you apply this model for downstream task?
So regardless of its training, we first assume it already possesses more of the capabilities of the language model in this part.
The output is a probability vector.
It can be regarded as embedded output.
So it just needs to pass the output to another module and to be fine-tuned by adding another module, maybe a small neural network.
For classification tasks, typically one or more fully connected layers are added on top of the election model.
And for sequence labeling tasks, it might involve adding a classification layer on the top of articles for each token to predict level.
The design here is it randomly samples a position from inputs to be masked.
Then this mask tokens are predicted by a small bird, denoted as the generator.
Then the discriminator trains on a binary classification task.
The label is whether the packet word is replaced or not.
The architecture of this discriminator is asperd.
The difference with GET and GAN here is since the word is masked and discrete here.
So the gradient of this discriminator cannot be passed to the generator, a little similar to Ralu.
So as they are not connected, they can only set the loss target of generator is the stilled stainless bird.
The loss of generator is a negative log likelihood, just the same in other large language models.
The loss of the discriminator is a cross entropy, because it is classification task.
Then they are trained at the same time as a linear combination.
Then let's compare ELECTRA to GAN. ELECTRA is quite different with GAN if even they have similar architecture.
The input of ELECTRA is the real test, not noise, and the output is real test, not fake.
And it's generated not inch to deceive the discriminator.
From the gradient perspective, it cannot slope from the discriminator to the generator.
But also, and thus, they considered whether performance could be improved by sharing weights with the discriminator.
After all, the discriminator is only trained on a single binary classification task, so the training might be a little difficult.
During their trials, this method can help, and here they just put some metrics in paper that didn't visualize it.
The second considering is, based on their architecture and task, what is the smallest bird that can possess the most fundamental capabilities?
So they try to reduce the layers and check the performance.
Here the X label in image is the size of generator, and the Y label is the glue performance.
The conclusion for all there is, the performance is best when the size of generator is half or 25% of the discriminator,
comparing to other ratio setting between generator and discriminator.
The inside here is a strong generator will also enhance the difficulty of discriminator training.
The third one is the gradient issue.
The author used other laws together with some tricks to pass the gradient from discriminator to the generator.
Here the X label shows that the original electron upperforms the one adding other tricks, so we won't go into details.
Another trick is that they try to train generator first, then visit in the first phase,
and initialize the weights in discriminator weights by generator weights in the second phase.
Then they train discriminator in same steps.
Then let's check the performance.
The left one is the zoomed out version of the one on the left, right.
On the vertical axis, we have the glue scores, and on the horizontal axis, we are measuring floating points operations.
The conclusion is that, the electron always outperforms bird with the same flowing points.
The goal here is to check whether the electron enhance the training efficiency.
Here the metrics are training an inference, floating point operations counts, and the number of parameters.
The speed up is compute based on the flow.
In order to train on a single GPU, the author creates electron small with bird small as the based model.
Then they compare it to L-mode GVT and bird.
The conclusion is, no matter under a floating million parameters or a hundred and ten million parameters,
under the same level of parameters, electron always outperforms bird.
Then the author also check how about the performance of a larger electron to compare with the robot.
Here the metrics are floating points.
We can see that under same level of floating points operations, the electron always outperforms robot in multiple classes.
Here is another earning.
It has language representation with informative entities.
Another insight is whether we can incorporate structured entity information into the earning.
For example, here the person has two identity, the songwriter and the writer.
So the relation between this person name entity with different items are different.
We also want to incorporate this relation in the model.
However, we want this additional information can help pilot on a few tasks like relationship.
Here the input is text and entity with relations.
The architecture consists of two parts.
The input of first part is only the sentence and the input of second part is the embedding output of first module and the entity embedding.
Here our concern is the task.
They prepare an entity relation prediction task.
They randomly mask some token entity alignments.
Then let model predict all corresponding entities based on align tokens.
So here partly unknown, partly unmasked.
Here another concern is how they merge to get a better embedding output that represents both information.
In the second part, both entity and tokens will pass into the multi-head and the attention independently to project them into same embedding space.
Then they are merged according to the non-entity alignment relationship,
depending to the entity to the first token.
Then they go into a fusion layer to fuse.
Here since it is an entity relation classification task, the gloss is cross-enderman.
To apply this model on downstream tasks,
the only effort is to modify the input.
So count the LLP tasks.
They just leave the placeholder as blend.
And for entity in typing or relation classification,
they replace placeholder as special tokens that used for this task.
The performance is that Ernie aims to improve those name entity tasks and relation tasks,
so it only outperforms Bert in this task.
Now we consider another problem.
Bert is not good at generating tasks,
because it is trained on hold sentences with mask words.
It cannot generate words on partial sequence data like GVD input.
So Bert only acts as encoder.
For sequence-to-sequence task, it needs to be trained decoder.
So the question comes out,
how to absorb sequence-to-sequence task into Bert?
To answer this question,
we first check the elements in different exceeding language models.
So there are multiple kinds of LLP tasks.
However, they can be classified as three types of tasks.
The bidirectional language model, which Bert includes.
And the second one is the left-to-right language model.
It's totally single direction.
The third one is sequence-to-sequence task.
During the first sentence,
we can see information from right side of the target word as input.
But in the second sequence,
we can just do single direction prediction.
So it contains both parts of Bert and GVD.
The task is actually decided by its input and output.
For LLP, Bert, GVD, the input needs to be lost.
And output, or is the probability of word prediction.
So they find that the core of language model is lost.
This is also a natural way to unify language models.
So the author called it unitLM.
Then the problem is from the perspective of mass metrics.
Whether we can leave the inputs and output as seen,
but vary the mass metrics to control different tasks.
Thus, we can control the network training
by just changing this mass metric.
From previous description,
this must indicate whether the input can contain
which kinds of information.
The left side, or the right side, or combination.
There are other explosions in this paper to improve the accuracy.
Here, our concern is the improvement on each task
and all kinds of tasks, unitLM performance.
Here are the performance of summarization task,
extractive QA task, the question and response generation task.
Next, we want to check how pre-training helps with the downstream task.
This is a figure from paper,
visualizing and understanding the effectiveness of Bert.
From the figure, we see that if we want to compare
the model trained from scratch
and the fine-tuned model that trained from pre-trained models,
their training gradient curve is totally different.
We can see that the fine-tuned model
has faster gradient descending at first.
And here is another perspective on how pre-training helps.
Here are the figures of error surface,
which visualize the millions of ways into 2D or 3D figure.
The meaning of this figure is,
if the figure is smooth, then it is more generalization capability.
We can see that the fine-tuned Bert has smaller platforms
than the one trained from scratch.
So the model fine-tuned on pre-trained models
will have more generalization capability
than the one trained from scratch.
Thank you.