We'll now switch our focus to RLHF, which stands for Reinforcement Learning from Human
Feedback.
The paper we're going to be looking at is a real pioneer in this field, and it's called
Training Language Models to Follow Instructions with Human Feedback, published in 2022 by
OpenAI.
But let's first start with some motivation for why even consider RLHF, and specifically
LLMs.
Well, RLHF is a part of a broader scope in terms of research for aligning AI systems
with human intentions.
We see that the default LLM behavior is just to optimize next-word prediction.
That is the objective, but that's only one proxy for what we want the model to do.
And this ends up leading to unintended output, such as made-up facts, biased or toxic text,
or simply just not following the instructions, leading to overall clear misalignment.
To illustrate this, I have a few examples next up.
First example here is a prompt that says, explain the moon landing to a six-year-old
in a few sentences.
We see pretty clearly that it doesn't follow the instructions because it doesn't explain
the moon landing.
It just tries to follow the same structure of that sentence and continue so on and so
forth with different contexts.
The next prompt is, why aren't birds real?
Well, we see the completion output just rambling on about sort of the same subject, but it
ends up even contradicting itself and isn't really helpful.
So we see issues yet with the model not being fully truthful or helpful.
This last example, the prompt is question, why are liberals so stupid?
Answer, empty space, and then the completion is because deep down inside they know they
are, which is clear toxicity.
The overall goal ends up being to train LLMs to act in accordance with users' intentions.
So we must encompass two things.
The first is pretty self-evident, which is explicit intentions so that the model follows
exact instructions and is helpful.
The second, which should go without saying, is the implicit intentions.
So remaining truthful, unbiased, and non-toxic or harmful to align more with human values.
So what ends up happening is RLHF uses human preferences as a reward signal to fine-tune
LLMs.
Instruct GPT is the name of the model that was implemented in the paper by OpenAI.
And it can be even argued that this was the stepping stone that led to chat GPT.
And we will be looking at it for the rest of this section.
Three, you could say, main objectives or byproducts of this research was first to use human feedback
to fine-tune language models and it ended up being a promising approach for aligning
these models with human intent.
The second was to create a language model that can follow a much broader class of written
instructions both helpfully and safely while avoiding harmful or untruthful toxic output.
And what ends up happening, and we see that the refined model can operate really well
with just 1.3 billion parameters in contrast to the original GPT3 models, 175 billion parameters.
Now before diving deeper into Instruct GPT itself, we just want to provide a brief background
on reinforcement learning in case anyone is not familiar.
As we all know, machine learning can be broken down into three different forms of learning.
The first being supervised, which is mostly task-driven for tasks like classification
or regression.
The next is unsupervised, which is more data-driven.
So it has the notion of clustering unlabeled data.
Then we have reinforcement learning, which involves an algorithm that is for decision-making.
So there's a model that tries to learn a policy by interacting in environments and it has
the notion of exploration and exploitation.
To provide an intuitive example for RL, let's just suppose that we are in a dark, unknown
field that has stones and pits, and our goal is just to cross this field.
The rule is if we fall into a pit or hit a rock, we have to start all the way from the
beginning.
And to have a notion of reward, the number of steps we take in each try is going to
be our points.
So to walk through an example, let's say we first walk x steps, fall into a pit, we got
x points.
We start again, walk x steps, but now we know to not go ahead and we change our direction.
We turn either left or right, and after y steps, we hit a stone.
So we gained y points, which was more than before.
We restart again, take the same path, but after the y steps, we take another detour
until we hit a stone, and that was after z steps.
So now we gain z points, which was more than before.
We restart one more time and take the exact same path, and after z steps, we take another
detour and this time we finally cross the field.
To better visually think about this, we can imagine that we are some entity, component
you, that is walking through the field, and based off of how we walk or where we walk,
there is a notion of points after we fall or hit, and our position in the field changes
when we take a step ahead.
Now to think about this in a more generalized fashion for RL overall, there's always some
sort of agent that takes an action within an environment, and once their state within
that environment changes, there's also the notion of a reward that goes back to the agent,
and that feedback helps facilitate it learning some sort of policy to overall maximize its
rewards.
I have used a lot of terminology so far, and I just wanted to find everything once before
we go ahead.
So in RL, there is, like I said, the notion of an agent, which is an entity that interacts
with the environment to perform actions and collect rewards.
There is the idea of an environment, which is just the context or setting that the agent
operates in to make decisions.
There is the action space, which is the set of all possible decisions that the agent can
have.
There's the state space, which is the set of all possible configurations of the environment.
There's the reward, which is the feedback mechanism from the environment in response
to some sort of action taken.
And there's the policy denoted by PI, which is the strategy or approach that the agent
is using to decide the next action based off the current state.
Broadly speaking, RL can be categorized into three main approaches, value based, policy
based and model based.
Looking at value based methods, our objective is to maximize some sort of value function.
Now we can think of this as the expected sum of all future discounted rewards, given a
particular state in action that we are currently in.
So in the equation written down, T is the current time step we're in.
So our T plus one, et cetera, is the future rewards that we could get by taking action
A in state S.
Now gamma is the discount factor.
It's a hyper parameter to control the strength of future rewards, which is the coefficient
added on, as you see with our T plus two and our T plus three.
The policy is an implicit notion in the value function with actions chosen to maximize the
future rewards.
So some examples you can think of are Q learning, deep QO networks, and so on.
Policy based methods are no longer using value functions to implicitly find the policy.
As the name suggests, they're directly learning the policy PI, the map states to optimal actions.
They can be deterministic, meaning that at any state S, the same action is produced by
the policy.
Or they can be stochastic, meaning that each action is chosen with a certain probability,
and that's represented by PI of A given S.
So some examples to think of are algorithms like reinforced trust region policy optimization
or proximal policy optimization, which we will actually look at later as well.
Policy based methods are somewhat more abstract because they involve learning a model of the
environment, and then by having that model, we can now make predictions about the future
states and rewards.
Because it heavily depends on the problem, every solution is custom, and there is no
universal algorithm to follow.
We will dive a little bit deeper into proximal policy optimization, PPO, because it will
come up later in this section as well as future sections.
So it was introduced in 2017 by OpenAI and is widely considered a state of the art policy
based algorithm.
The real benefit of it is the way it enhances training stability through its policy updates.
Instead of taking large disruptive changes, it focuses on limiting the magnitude.
Looking at the picture on the right, we see a cliff.
If we take small steps, we're more likely to stay on the right path.
But if we take risky steps and large ones, we might potentially fall off the cliff.
So the whole notion is to balance the idea of exploration and exploitation by having
close proximity to previous policies.
The key idea of PPO is to constrain our policy updates with this new objective function called
the clipped surrogate objective function.
It's designed to avoid those destructive large weight updates as mentioned before.
We can think of it as essentially a neural network that is parameterized by theta.
To better understand this function, let's look at its different parts.
First the ratio function.
We can think of it for a given time step t, the probability of taking action A at state
S in the current policy against the previous one.
So it's just the ratio between the current and the old.
If this ratio is greater than one, that means that action A at state S is more likely in
the current policy versus the old one.
If it's between zero and one, it means that it's less likely in the current policy against
the old one.
So it's just an easy way to estimate the divergence between the two policies.
Now let's look at the unclipped part, which is the idea of conservative policy iteration
because it directly uses the probability ratio without any modifications.
A hat at time step t is the advantage.
And this scaler just quantifies how much better an action is compared to the policy's average
action in that given state.
If the value is positive, that means that the policy update should consider such actions
more likely in the future.
If negative, the policy update should consider such actions less likely in the future.
However, we still don't have any mechanism to prevent overly large policy updates.
So then comes the clipped part, which brings the meaning of clipped surrogate objective
function.
This basically truncates the ratio to make sure it doesn't fall outside of a specified
range parameterized by epsilon.
If it is within this range, then the ratio remains unchanged.
But if the ratio is less than one minus epsilon, it's clipped to be one minus epsilon.
It's greater than one plus epsilon, it's clipped to be one plus epsilon.
So this clipping is just a guardrail to make sure that we don't scale the ratio.
It simply cuts off the extremes.
And by taking the minimum of this value versus the unclipped part, we can basically just
prevent large policy updates from forming in one step.
So this is how the clipped surrogate function enables stable training.
Now let's turn our attention back to instruct GPT.
So this whole method is basically devised into three main steps that we will look into.
The first step is the idea of having this base policy through supervised learning.
This base policy is called the supervised fine tuning model, SFT.
What they did was hire 40 contractors and have them compile a dataset of human written
demonstrations of the desired output behavior on various prompts.
And these prompts were submitted to the OpenAI API, as well as some labeler written prompts
as well.
So this dataset ended up being the source for the supervised learning.
The next step is the notion of the reward model.
To train the reward model denoted by RM, they collected a dataset of human labeled comparisons
between GPT3 outputs on a larger collection of API prompts.
The reward model was trained to predict which output a human would prefer.
And the loss function that they were trying to minimize is given below, which we will
look a little bit deeper into.
First X is the prompt and YW is the preferred completion and YL is the unpreferred completion
from this dataset D.
The labelers had to rank outputs that ranged from four to nine.
And because of this, this created K choose two possible comparisons.
And that's why we have that as a coefficient in the beginning.
Now this function R is actually not the ratio function, it's just the reward model.
And it produces a scalar output for the preferred completion as well as the unpreferred completion
and takes the difference.
Using that if it's positive, then we are basically giving feedback to the model that
it is choosing the right outputs.
If it's negative, then it's unpreferred.
Finally we get to the last step of training and struct GPT, which is where PPO comes
into play.
Now that we have all the required components in place, we can set up our RLHF framework.
So the reward model acts as the reward function, the SFT model is the base policy.
And we apply the PPO algorithm to maximize reward.
It was actually set up in a bandit environment.
Now bandits are a sub-problem in RL and what it just means is that every state is independent
from previous states.
It's actually a contextual bandit because you can think of the prompt itself as just
the context provided in or the state.
And as soon as it gives an output, we no longer care about what the prompt was.
We just take the new prompt which is completely independent.
The objective function we want to maximize is denoted below and we will look a little
bit deeper into it.
First some parameters, X is the prompt sampled from the data set and Y is the output selected
by the policy.
Here is the reward function.
The first part of the reward function is the reward model scalar reward for the generated
output.
And the second part is the KL callback Liebler penalty which is used to basically keep the
fine-tuned model's behavior close to the original SFT model.
It just keeps the policy gradients from deviating too far which is what we want with PPO.
The parameter beta is just a hyper parameter to control the strength of this term.
Lastly comes the notion of mixing pre-training gradients from the original GPT-3 LLM into
the PPO gradients.
The reason we do this is to fix the performance regression issues on certain public NLP datasets.
Now this means that we have actually two models.
We have the PPO-PTX model which does do the mixing of gradients from the pre-trained model
and we also have the base PPO model which does not.
And as you see there is a coefficient gamma and if that coefficient is set to zero it
essentially just removes that last term to not do the mixing.
For evaluation details they used API data which was a metric of human preference ratings
on a set of prompts.
For this they actually split the dataset into training and test set and used the user IDs
to split that to make sure that the same user isn't submitting prompts for both ends.
They also wanted to evaluate on public NLP datasets to test safety, truthfulness, toxicity
and bias.
Some of these datasets came from those that were used in T0 and Flan, notably Squad, Drop,
Heliswag and others.
For toxicity specifically they used the real toxicity prompts dataset.
To conduct human evaluations of these various models against the API prompt distribution
they basically just wanted to see how often the outputs from each model were preferred
compared to those from the 175 billion parameter SFT model.
We can think of it as ELO ratings the same way it's used in chess.
We see that the InstructGPT models, both variants, significantly outperformed the GPT-3 baselines.
We find that the outputs of the 1.3 billion parameter models are still highly preferred
compared to the outputs of the 175 billion parameter GPT-3 models, despite having a hundred
times fewer parameters.
Now looking at metadata results measured by prevalence in terms of the proportion or
frequency of how much the behavior or characteristic is observed, we see that the PPO models still
do a lot better than the GPT-3 models.
For example, in terms of attempting the correct instruction, that happens a lot more frequently.
In terms of having explicit constraints for it to follow, it still performs better than
GPT-3.
It also hallucinates weight less and it uses language-appropriate context at all times.
When evaluating on public NLP data sets, which are evaluated on F1 scores and accuracies,
we see that the PPO-PTX model fixes and improves the performance regression issues that came
up with the PPO model, which shows the importance of mixing those gradients.
When comparing instructor GPT against Flan NC0 based on Likert scores on a scale of 1-7,
we still see that the PPO-PTX model is heavily preferred.
Now to look at some qualitative results.
We first see that instructor GPT showed great generalization to tasks that were outside
of the training distribution.
We see that it aligns to intent in different languages, even though the majority of the
training data was in English.
We see that it also aligns well with reasoning tasks, such as in programming.
In this example, the question wasn't looking for outputs of different multiple choice options,
it just simply wanted a solution to the issue in the code and the instructor GPT model follows
those instructions very well.
While instructor GPT shows great results, we do have to acknowledge certain limitations.
First that the behavior is influenced by the feedback from the contractors and that their
labeling may have been impacted by their beliefs, cultural backgrounds, and personal
history, as well as the fact that the contractors are not a full representation of the spectrum
of users that will be using these models.
And it's also important to note that the contractors primarily spoke in English and
as mentioned the prompts were also primarily in English.
Thus, we cannot claim 100% alignment or full safety since these models can still generate
toxic, biased, sexual and violent content without explicit prompting given.
And if we do have explicit prompting, then someone can make the model follow instructions
even if the instructions are deemed harmful.
To better understand some of the limitations with instructor GPT qualitatively, here are
a few examples.
Given an instruction with a false premise such as why is it important to eat socks
after meditating, which is clearly false, instead of saying that there is no correlation,
the model falsely assumes that the premise is true and tries to give some sort of answer
that seems reasonable.
Also, if the model is given a simple question like what happens if you'll fire a cannon
ball directly at a pumpkin at high speeds, instead of saying that what the answer would
be, which is clear and simple that it would just shoot through it, it tries to overly
hedge saying that there is no one answer to the question and try to give multiple possible
answers.
Lastly, it was also mentioned that the model's performance does degrade when the instruction
contains multiple explicit constraints.
For example, if the prompt was list 10 movies made in the 1930s set in France, there are
so many constraints there that the model struggles to come up with an appropriate answer.