Hello everyone, my name is Mohamed and in this presentation together with Yunyi we'll
present for you the topic of large multimodal models.
So let's have a quick review of what we will cover.
Basically we will cover eight models or eight papers.
Actually the last one, Germany, is more of a technical report.
So the models are Flamingo, visual instruction tuning, Lava, InstructBleep, Poly, Poly3,
Emo2, InternVL and Gemini.
So from these models the first four will be presented by me and the next four by Yunyi.
Let's go for Flamingo.
So Flamingo is called the GPT-3 Momentum Multimodal Vision Language Tasks.
Let's see what is Flamingo.
Flamingo is a visual language model capable of multimodal tasks like captioning, visual
dialogue, classification and visual question answering.
Here you can see an example of visual question answering.
For example, take this photo here, there's a CD and a floppy disk in this image.
And when asked what do you think the capacities of these are, the model or Flamingo is able
to identify those objects and give the information about their capacity.
As you see 1.44 megabits for floppy disk and CD 700 megabyte.
Another example is the ability of Flamingo for visual dialogue.
For example, in this image there's a bowl of soup with a monster on the top.
And when the user asks what is in this picture, the model says it's a bowl of soup with a
monster face on it and then asked what's the monster made of.
It's able to say of course it's wrong and then user corrects the model and model is
asked another question and answers it.
And you can see here an example of understanding the video.
For example, if you take this one here, these are the frames of a video.
There's a pen here, there's a scissor and a rubber band.
And when the model is asked to identify the objects, it's able to name them scissor, pen
and a rubber band.
What are the motivations behind Flamingo?
One of the important aspects of intelligence is the ability to quickly learn tasks given
short instructions.
And we like model to learn the environment to make better use of the data and we like
our multimodal systems which will handle vision and language tasks to achieve this property.
Prior to Flamingo the dominant computer vision paradigm was larger scale pre-training and
task-specific fine-tuning.
But there are some problems with this approach such as need for thousands of training samples,
need for task-specific hyperparameter tuning and also needing significant computational
resources.
So basically the authors ask, can we train a multimodal model that has good performance
in few-shot regime?
Another ability that we want our models to have is ability to handle open-ended tasks.
Multimodal models prior to Flamingo like clip and align show good zero-shot performance
but they are not flexible.
They lack the ability to generate language.
By taking inspiration from NLP domain we can see that large language models like GPT-3
are flexible few-shot learners and when we give them a few examples of tasks in the form
of a prompt plus a query, the language model generates a continuation to produce the predicted
output.
And the key factor of their success is larger scale pre-training.
Observing this the authors say that in principle image and video understanding tasks such as
classification, captioning, question answering are basically text prediction problems with
visual input conditioning.
So they ask this question, can we learn a model capable of open-ended multimodal tasks
via pre-training the same ways done for large language models?
There are some challenges for creating multimodal generative modeling.
One of the challenges is that training large language models is computationally expensive
and we like to save resources by when I say we actually the authors like to save resources
by starting from a pre-trained language model but we know that the language models are not
able to handle inputs of different modalities.
So we like to give our models disability to handle multimodal input while they retain
the knowledge of the original language models that we want to use.
So for that authors are proposing this solution where they interleaving cross-attention layers
with language only self-attention layers that are kept frozen during the training.
And don't worry we'll discuss cross-attention later in our slides.
The other challenge is that we want to enable our model to get both video and image inputs
but we know that these are high-dimensional data so flattening them to one-dimensional
sequence as used in text generation is costly and this is exacerbated by quadratic cost
of self-attention.
A secondary goal that we want to achieve is the unified treatment of images and videos
in our model.
The proposed approach by the authors is using a perceiver-based architecture with a fixed
number of visual tokens for both images and the videos and again don't worry we'll discuss
perceiver in later slides in more detail.
The other challenge is having heterogeneous training data.
Large models we know that they require vast training data sets but existing image text
data sets such as those used in clip and align are not general enough to reach GPT-3
style few-shot learning.
There are large internet-based text-only data sets but not for multimodal data and one scalable
approach that can be used is scraping webpages with interleaved image and text but the problem
with that approach would be such images and text are often only weekly related.
So the authors proposed the following approach where they want to combine web scraping with
existing paired image text and video text data sets.
So Flamingo let's recap what we have for Flamingo as goals so Flamingo will be a visual language
model that accepts interleaved inputs as you see text, image or video and it will be given
to the Flamingo and Flamingo will give us at the output of text.
This framework will enable a broad range of tests for Flamingo to complete such as open
and the test and close and the test, visual question answering and captioning are examples
of open and the test and classification for close and the test.
The first goal is leveraging pre-train models to save computation for example for vision
they use encoder from clip and for the language component they use frozen chinchilla and the
second goal is bridging these pre-train unimodal models harmoniously using the perceiver resampler
and the cross attention.
So for achieving these goals let's see what is the architecture that the authors have
designed.
Here you can see the input it's a text interleaved images the images are taken out of the input
and they are given to vision encoders will we keep them frozen during the training the
output of vision encoder goes to perceiver resampler and the output of perceiver resampler
comes here at these cross attention layers that are named gated extension dense and
the text of the input is taken also and it comes directly to the gated extension.
At this point they are mixed this is a cross attention layer and the output goes to a frozen
language block and then basically this is repeated for a couple of times not actually
a couple of times but a few like for a few times until at the output you have the output
text and pink color here shows components that will be trained from scratch and the
blue color shows the components that will be kept frozen during training.
So Flamingo tries to model this probability that you see here which is probability of
the text token that will be generated next given the visual condition so that is equal
to the multiplication of probabilities of the ELF token given all the prior tokens text
tokens coming before it as well as the image token coming before it.
Now let's take a look into vision encoder and go a bit into detail so this is the vision
encoder and the vision encoder that you Flamingo uses F6 normalizer free resnet or NFnet in
short it is pre-trained as dual encoder using contrastive loss employed by a clip and Bert
is used for text encoder and it is discarded after pre-training.
There are slight differences to clip for example global average pooling is used here in Flamingo
to produce the vision embeddings instead of the global attention pooling and the resolution
of the images used for this pre-training step of the encoder are 288 by 288 pixels and the
dimension of the output embedding is 1376.
So the output that vision encoder generates is a 2D special grid of features which is
flattened to 1D and for videos the frames are taken out and basically they are sampled
at one frame per second and then the generated features for each frame are concatenated to
each other.
Please also note that vision encoder is frozen after the pre-training step.
Now let's take a look into Percever Sampler and why we need it.
So as we said the variable number of input frames are processed because you have videos
in the input so the vision encoder will produce a variable number of features and that's why
we need Percever which will output a fixed number of visual tokens in the case of the
paper it is 64 so that we can limit the complexity of attention.
So let's take a look into Percever Sampler architecture here.
As you can see the frames of the video are given to vision encoders.
Basically different set of features is created for each frame and after adding a temporal
encoding to the features that vision encoder produces all the features are flattened and
are given to attention.
There are some learned latent queries here that you can see these latent queries not
only we will treat them as queries but we concatenate them to the flattened generated
features and we will give them to an attention layer and then the output will be given to
a feed forward layer and then we have the final output.
Because the number of queries is always fixed it is fixed to 64 we will always have 64
tokens at the output.
So let's see conditioning the language model and how it will happen.
As you can see as I mentioned earlier the output of Percever Sampler comes to this cross
attention and the text also comes here and then the output goes to a frozen language
but let's see what is the architecture of this gated extension dense layer.
We can see that the vision inputs come here and the language input comes as queries they
are given to this cross attention layer after that we have a tannage gating then there is
a feed forward again a tannage gating and then we have our frozen self attention for
language component and feed forward again frozen.
And as you can notice there are some tannage gates here basically the reason that we put
them is that at the initialization where the pink layers are not trained we want at
least like a good performance as the frozen language part so these will be initialized
to zero there will be an alpha parameter as you see here so this will be set to zero so
that the original performance of the language component is retained.
So after each layer there is like a layer norm such as the GPT tool style.
About the Flamingo training data Flamingo is trained on image text pairs video text
pairs and web page data as you can see this is kind this is one of the image text pairs
there is image of Flamingo and caption for that then video text pair you can see in the
middle there are frames of video and a caption describing what's going on in the video and
this is kind of web page data where like it says welcome to my website there is image
of a dog and then it says this is a picture of my dog and then there is a cat and etc.
The Flamingo training objective is negative like the average of negative lug likelihood
of the next token based on the previous tokens and images and this like expectation happens
over the data sets and because we have multiple data sets there is a there is a summation
over all of them and of course we need to weight like or balance each data set and here
dm denotes the mth data set, lambda m is a positive scalar rate for the mth data set
and similar to vision encoder pre-training tuning these weights or this lambda m is important
for good performance and as we can see the accumulation strategy is used over the loss
for all the data sets.
Let's see the evaluation data sets we can see that we have two kind two types two categories
of tasks open-ended and close-ended we have image benchmarks and video benchmarks and
for open-ended tasks we can see that we have captioning, visual question answering, etc.
and for closed-ended tasks we can see that like some examples are classification or image
plus text classification and visual dialogue and you can see that there are some gear signs
basically that means those data sets have been used for hyper parameter tuning and model
training and those that don't have such sign means that they are unseen to the model and
only we use them for testing.
Let's see the main results here the like we can see different data sets the data sets
that we just discussed in the previous slide and we can see the relative performance of
32-shot flamingo which is 80 billion parameters and we can see those are the pink color like
bars and we can see some gray colored bars which show the previous state-of-the-art zero
or few-shot models and like they are relative to the state-of-the-art fine-tuned version
and we can see that like flamingo consistently outperforms the state-of-the-art fine-tuned
and also few-shot models that come prior to it it also on some data sets you can see that it
completely like puts a new state-of-the-art in the performance in the right hand side you can see
another diagram which tries to show the effect of scale scaling and also the number of shots the
horizontal axis is the number of shots we can see that it ranges from one shot to 32 shots and we
can see that as we go for go for higher shot numbers the performance in the performance improves
and scaling the model from 3 billion to 9 billion to 80 billion we can see that it enhances the
performance of our model the next paper or the model that we will discuss is visual instruction
tuning and the model introduced here is Lava so this paper introduces Lava it is a large
language and vision assistant it is an end-to-end trained large multimodal model that connects a
vision encoder and an LLM it is instruction tuned on multimodal language image instruction
following data and for creating such data the paper uses language only GPT-4 which is interesting
and just to see what it is capable of doing let's see in a qualitative example we can see this
image and when the model is asked what is unusual about this image it is able to say the unusual
aspect of this image is a man ironing clothes on the back of a minivan this is not a typical
place to perform this activity as one would usually iron clothes in a more stationary and
safe location and etc what is the background to this work well this work is inspired by
large multimodal models that come before it such as Flamingo and also it is affected by
inspired by instruction tuning for large language models and as an example like another
qualitative example to see how instruction tuned LLM looks like let's see this for example we have
instruction explains humans behavior and the behavior that we give is cry and it's able to
say there could be many reasons why a person might cry they could be feeling sad scared angry or etc
also as I mentioned this work is inspired by the prior LMMs one of them is blip2 the other is
Flamingo Flamingo we discussed earlier but blip2 we won't discuss it but what are the problem with
these prior work well it turns out that prior methods generally lack instruction following
capabilities so the question that authors ask is how can we create such multimodal models that
follow humans intent and the proposed approach is visual instruction tuning before we go to visual
instruction tuning let's see what is the instruction tuning method used for LLMs well there are two
ways to collect the instruction tuning data where the humans give the instruction also humans give
the answer it has high quality but it is hand written by humans so it has a high cost and the
other way is the like human is involved but the data is mainly generated by machines so there's a
need for a strong LLM based teacher like chat GPT and that makes of course the cost more affordable
so let's see how we can use chat GPT for creating instruction tuning data you can see a seed
instruction output pair here explain humans behavior and the behaviors cry and a reference
answer is given by the human then also there's like another one recommend a movie for me and
another answer is given and then we ask the model please generate new instruction output pairs that
meet the following requirements and it starts to generate some of the prior LLMs that have used
this technique are alpaca vicona GPT for alpaca and we can see that the data source for alpaca is
GPT 3.5 for vicona is shared GPT where there's a GPT and human involved and GPT for alpaca which
uses GPT for text only and for tulu there there there's mixed data sources
so now let's go for visual instruction tuning give an instruction and the image we want the model
to follow instruction and give the desired output for that we need three components a visual encoder
a cross-modal connector and a language decoder so these are the things that we need a strong
pre-trained vision and language models cross-modal connector and after we have these we will do a
fine tuning and we will tune the model for following multimodal instructions but what is the problem
the problem is that as we saw all the previous teachers used for generating these instruction
following data are actually text only models like GPT 3.5 and the others so how we are going to
create such data the authors proposed GPT assisted visual instruction data creation
which i will discuss in this slide so you can see that like there's an image here actually like
they use microsoft coco common objects in context this is one image from that dataset and there are
two contexts for it a caption that describes the image a group of people standing outside of a black
vehicle with rice luggage and there's another context provided which which is the layout
basically you can see that objects are boxed and we have the information or coordinates of the boxes
there's also an instruction what are the challenges these people might be facing
and then there's output they may have be having difficulty fitting all luggage into the back of
this uv and so on so the way that GPT 4 is used is that it is given the caption context and it is
given the layout context and then also an instruction and an output and we give a couple
like a few more in context examples of visual context instruction output triplets and then
for a new image we give the new context for caption new context for layout and then we
ask the model please generate new context instruction output triplets that meet following
requirements and the GPT 4 starts creating this data using this technique the authors create
lava instruct 158k where there are 58k conversation examples 23k detailed description and 77k
complex reasoning just to see how a single sample looks like we have here the same image
from the previous slides there's captions and boxes the first type of response is conversation
the example is what type of vehicle is featured in the image and the answer is an SUV
then there's detailed description response type where there's a detailed description of the image
and the last one is complex reasoning response type where we can see the question is what challenges
do these people face and the answer is well they have hard time to fit all the luggage into the back
of the suv so let's see what is the architecture of lava lava has again three components vision
encoder which is clip v it large and it it uses 14 image patches the projection is just a linear
layer and the language model can be Vekona Loma to chat MPT chat and etc we can see that image
comes here goes through vision encoder and embedding is created that embedding is projected by this
projection layer to a new embedding and along the language language tokens these are given to the
language model and language model generates the required output
for training lava there are two stages the first stage is pre-training for feature alignment
the language model is frozen vision encoder is frozen and the projection layer can vary
for that purpose the data that is used is a filtered cc3m subset which has 595k
samples the second stage is end-to-end visual instruction tuning the vision encoder again
is frozen but the projection layer and language model can vary and the two tasks are used for
this end-to-end visual instruction tuning phase visual chat which is lava instruct 158k that we
just saw how is created and it is for open-ended user-oriented visual tasks and the other task
that they use for end-to-end training is science qa multimodal reasoning dataset for the science
domain after the training lava it shows some emerging properties as we discussed the datasets
used for two stages of training were cc3m and instruction tuning coco but these were only
common concepts so the domain was limited and no human name annotations were mentioned
and no explicit ocr and ocr is like text in the image yet we can see that the lava is able to
handle some of the tasks related to like these points for example when asked what is the name of
the person here it says this is Elon Musk and even in a more challenging scenario where the face of
the one he has been replaced with that of Elon Musk the model is still able to identify him
for the evaluation the authors again like suggest the GPT assisted method and as we can see they
give the caption context they give the layout context and they give the instruction and they
give the output generated by different models for example model one model two and after giving
the output of different models they ask the model we would like to request your feedback on the
performance of two AI assisted assistance with the following requirements and the model starts to
giving score to model one giving score to model two and it and the authors also required the model
to give some intuition or reasoning for the scoring that it provides to make that it is
consistent for example it says assistant one provides a concise and accurate answer to the
question however assistant two went above and beyond by not only identifying the con concepts but
also doing such and so so this this helps us make sure that it is consistent in the scoring
for the evaluation they create another benchmark lower bench or in the wild the features of these
benchmark are like designed such that it is a challenging data set because it requires
knowledge beyond training data it also requires multi-lingual understanding and also perception
of subtle details these like because it has these challenging features during the evaluation we can
like evaluate the consistency and prompt robustness of the models that we evaluate just to have some
examples of lower bench you can see here a traditional Chinese dish dish and for example
one of the questions asked is what is the name of the restaurant and the model is supposed to
understand I guess Chinese script from here like from from the pole and understand the name
and tell the name of the restaurant and here in another example we are looking into a refrigerator
filled with food and one of the questions asks is what is the brand of the blueberry flavored yogurt
and the model is supposed to like be able to read the brand and tell it
we can see here the results of evaluation on the lava bench we can see that lava outperforms blip
to and open flamingo consistently for conversation detailed description and complex reasoning and
overall the next one that we will discuss is instruct blip so first let's see what is capable
of doing uh for example here when asked what could have happened based on the current scene
the model is able to say based on the current scene in the image it is possible that a hurricane
or severe weather event caused significant damage and so on or here for example we have a painting
and when asked introduce me this painting it is able to name the name of the painting it's also able
to name the painter who created this artistic painting and also the model is able to describe
in detail for example mentioned the white pearl earring and other features of the painting
so what is the motivations behind instruct blip the goal is that authors want a single
model to solve arbitrary tasks specified by user they also see that instruction tuning in lm's is
promising and it has recently been leveraged in lm's like blip too but they say that these are
preliminary and generalizing to diverse vision language tasks is still a challenge prior to
instruct blip two approaches are used for achieving these goals the first approach is multitask
learning uh where they formulate formulate all tasks into the same format and the problem
with this approach is that it doesn't generalize to unseen tasks the other approach is extending
a pre-trained lm with a visual component and train it with image caption data as we saw for
example for flamingo and the problem they say that these models have is that they're struggling
to generalize beyond visual description tasks
the tasks and data sets that the authors use are described in this slide where they have
11 vision language categories the categories are image captioning visual reasoning visual
conversational qa and other categories so counting the data sets within each of these
categories overall there are 26 publicly available data sets these data sets are transformed to
instruction tuning format and 10 to 15 instruction templates are used for every task as you can see
there are yellowish color data sets those are 13 held in data sets and there are white data sets
and those are 13 held out data sets on top of that the authors withhold four task categories
and they use it only for testing by by this like for example visual reasoning all the data sets
are completely withhold video question answering the model doesn't see any of these data sets so
it's it doesn't see the entire task category the other task category that will not be seen
by the model is image classification and visual conversational qa so the first time that model
will see these is during the testing we can see here the architecture that is used for
instruct blip we have again an image encoder there's a large language model which is kept frozen
also that's the case for encoder and there's a qformer and we can see that for qformer again
there are some learned queries and learned queries along the instructions are passed to qformer
let's see what happens inside qformer inside qformer you have queries learned queries you
have instructions in the form of tokens they go through a self-attention layer and the outputs
goes to a cross attention the other input for this cross attention is the image embeddings
produced by the image encoder and after cross attention it goes through a feed forward and then
you have the like newly created tokens at the output so these newly created tokens go through a
fully connected layer and then you have another set of outputs which alongside the instructions
they are given to the large language model and the response is generated as a novelty for this
paper the instruction tokens interact with query embeddings through self-attention in qformer
so the novelty is instruction-available visual feature extraction
there are some implementation details one of the details is related to balancing training
datasets the author says that to avoid overfitting on small datasets and underfitting larger ones
they use a sampling strategy and their strategy is basically if you have s1 through sd
datasets the probability of sampling from each dataset is proportional to the square root of
size of that dataset over the summation of a square root of sizes of other datasets
the other one is related to inferior methods they use two generation approaches
for majority of datasets such as image captioning model is directly prompted to generate
and for other tasks like classification and multi-choice vqa a vocabulary ranking is used
the other there are like details about the architecture as well the image encoder that
they use is vitg with 14 image patches the large language model is either flanty5 which is an
encoder decoder transformer instruction tuned from t5 or vicona decoder only transformer
instruction tuned from loma we can see here the evaluation for instruct blip
instruct blip models are here and these are blip2 models and flamingo and we can see that for
different tasks such as captioning visual question answering and others like scientific
question answering the instruct blip models consistently outperform the other models such as
blip2 and flamingo the last one that i will discuss is poly let's see so here are some
qualitative examples for example for this image when asked generate the out text in english it is
able to generate a cellar filled with barrels of wine and we can see a couple of other english
example additionally it's able to also generate out text in french in thai for example here
and in chinese in the last image here so what are the motivations behind poly the authors
say that increasing the network capacity has been a successful trend for example for language
models t5 and gpt3 have great performance vision models such as vit as they go larger they improve
the performance and this is the case also for language vision models such as flamingo but the
scale distribution is not equitable in large capacity language vision models usually the
language component is much larger and the other problem is that these models are english only
so given these let's say problems the poly has been designed to satisfy the following goals
they want to reuse large unimodal backbones and they want their model to benefit from jointly
scaling vision and language in a more balanced parameter share between language and vision
components and they want to enable knowledge sharing between tasks by casting them to a
generalized vqa like task and also they train a new high volume dataset of tens of billion
image taxpayers across 100 languages not only english
so let's have a recap of what is poly designed for poly aims to do both unimodal and multimodal
tasks it enables knowledge sharing by casting all tasks to a generalized vqa like task
basically the framework is as follows image plus a text string is input and at the output you have a
text and it uses pre-trained unimodal models to transfer existing capabilities of those models
and also reduce the training cost and visual token are passed to encoder decoder via cross
attention in a similar manner to some of the models that we saw before this is the architecture
basically there's a v it as vision encoder part and there are transformer encoder and decoder
and they enable basically this vision language tasks for poly
let's see in more detail what each of those components are so for the vision we can see this
like a v it component here the component that they use is the largest vanilla v it
that they call v it enormous it's the largest ever trained it has four billion parameters
and they say that scaling up v it on multimodal data not only does not saturate but has higher
return in terms of accuracy improvement per parameter or number of flops well we know that
this is not the case usually actually going beyond some threshold in the scale of v it on like tasks
such as classification doesn't give you much better performance but they say that that's not true
for this case where the like you have multimodal data the language component is mt5 backbone
it's trained on a mix of tasks to avoid catastrophic forgetting and given like these points the overall
model will be v it enormous or v it g and one of these like language components mt5 large or mt5
xx large so the data that poly is trained on looks like this these are some examples
this is for example a free stock photo of matrix and sidekick the ocr are card the card is written
here a telecom is written here and there's a number here 5624 and you have here like this
image and the out text is in french also there's ocr in french and you have this image there's a
tie out text for it and chinese out text for this scene so these like these are some examples from
the data set that they use and it's called webbly data sets it's built from image text on public
web covering 109 languages it has 10 billion images 12 billion out text and 29 billion image ocr pairs
but only top 10 percent scoring are used which is around 1 billion for the training of poly
here is a like statistics of the data set we can see that as we could like guess from the beginning
largest chunk is for english then japanese chinese and other languages and some medium
sized languages like turkish and malay and then some smaller like corpse of data for languages
such as oigur and you can see like a comparison of the data set used by poly and those that have
been previously used for example you have the data set for clip 400 million for a line 1.8 billion
lite 4 billion but these two last columns are for poly webbly basically out text has 12 billion
and the webbly ocr has 29 billion pairs and these are the experimental results there are like a couple
of sorry there are a few like experiment results on many task categories but for just as an example
i've brought here the results for captioning we can see that poly is able to consistently out
perform the previous methods including flamingo here and the other experimental result that i've
brought here is about the effect of scaling as we can see there are three colors here and the
vertical axis shows the absolute score difference between like the this the model
denoted by blue color here and the other scaled up versions of that model so the blue color
basically shows a poly with three billion parameters the language component is large
and the vision component is vitg the green the red color shows poly with 15 billion
parameters the language component is xx large the vision component is vitg and there's this
yellow color showing a poly with 17 billion parameters the language component is xx large and
the vision encoder is vit enormous and there's also like this yellow bordered white color
which shows the same poly model with 17 billion parameters as the yellow one but there's a high
resolution training phase involved for the vision component and we can see that for tasks such as
captioning which are these like three first tasks here actually scaling up the vision component
gives much better absolute score difference compared to scaling up the language component
and for other tasks like visual question answering we can see that like the language scaling up the
language component gives maybe more increase in the absolute score but overall and on average we
can see that there's better return for scaling up the vision component
and from here like for the next four multimodal models yunyi will continue thank you for your
attention